<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>

<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Poetics (English). Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Aristotle</author> &responsibility; &fund.AnnCPB; </titleStmt>
			<extent>About 146Kb</extent> &Perseus.publish; <notesStmt>
				<note anchored="yes">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Aristotle</author>
						<title>Aristotle in 23 Volumes, Vol. 23, translated by W.H. Fyfe.</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1932</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English </language>
				<language id="greek">Greek </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>May, 1993</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>wpm</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Tagged in conformance with Prose.e dtd.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>July 27, 1993</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>em</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Put Bekker line 1 milestone tags at the beginning of each section so that the
					incoming list creator would work. Changed RREFDECL.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>1/1999</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>lmc</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Corrected two typos in 1449a.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>5/27/09</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>RS</name>
					<resp>(n/a)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: aristot.poet_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2010-12-14 16:47:30  lcerrato
fixed three typos based on user report

Revision 1.2  2010/06/16 19:18:48  rsingh04
cleaned up bad place tags in a few texts and cleaned up the document format

Revision 1.1  2009/10/09 19:49:17  rsingh04
more reorganizing of texts module by collection

Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:12:40  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.13  2009/09/08 20:28:34  lcerrato
fixed typo

Revision 1.12  2009/07/24 16:49:45  rsingh04
fixed cvs log keyword


Revision 1.11  2009/07/15 19:25:41  student
edited entity tags CEH

Revision 1.10 2009/06/09 18:13:54 student
fixed bibl errors - zr 

Revision 1.9 2009/05/27 15:55:14 rsingh04 
added cvs log keyword 
				</item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text n="Poet.">
		<body>
			<head>Poetics</head>
			<p>
				<milestone n="1447a" unit="section"/><milestone n="8" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="1.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The text here printed is based on Vahlen's
					third edition&lpar;<placeName key="tgn,7012329">Leipzig</placeName>,
					1885&rpar;, and the chief deviations from it are noted at the foot of each
					page. The prime source of all existing texts of the Poetics is the eleventh
					century <placeName key="tgn,7008038">Paris</placeName> manuscript, No. <date value="1741">1741</date>, designated as Ac. To the manuscripts of the
					Renaissance few, except Dr. Margoliouth, now assign any independent value, but
					they contain useful suggestions for the correction of obvious errors and defects
					in Ac. These are here designated &ldquo;copies.&rdquo;V. stands for
					Vahlen's third edition, and By. for the late Professor Ingram Bywater, who has
					earned the gratitude and admiration of all students of the Poetics by his
					services both to the text and to its interpretation. Then there is the Arabic
					transcript. Translated in the eleventh century from a Syriac translation made in
					the eighth century, it appears to make little sense, but sometimes gives dim
					visions of the readings of a manuscript three centuries older but not
					necessarily better than Ac, readings which confirm some of the improvements
					introduced into Renaissance texts.</note> us here deal with Poetry, its essence
				and its several species, with the characteristic function of each species and the
				way in which plots must be constructed if the poem is to be a success; and also with
				the number and character of the constituent parts of a poem, and similarly with all
				other matters proper to this same inquiry; and let us, as nature directs, begin
				first with first principles.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="1.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Epic poetry, then, and the poetry of tragic drama, and,
				moreover, comedy and dithyrambic poetry, and most flute-playing and harp-playing,
				these, speaking generally, may all be said to be "representations of life."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The explanation of <foreign lang="greek">MI/MHSIS</foreign>, as Aristotle uses the word, demands a treatise; all
					that a footnote can say is this:&mdash;Life "presents" to the artist the
					phenomena of sense, which the artist "re-presents" in his own medium, giving
					coherence, designing a pattern. That this is true not only of drama and fiction
					but also of instrumental music ("most flute-playing and harp-playing") was more
					obvious to a Greek than to us, since Greek instrumental music was more
					definitely imitative. The technical display of the virtuoso Plato describes as
					"a beastly noise." Since <foreign lang="greek">MI/MHSIS</foreign> in this sense
					and <foreign lang="greek">MIMHTH/S</foreign> and the verb <foreign lang="greek">MIMEI=SQAI</foreign> have a wider scope than any one English word, it is
					necessary to use more than one word in translation, e.g. <foreign lang="greek">MIMHTH/S</foreign> is what we call an "artist"; and for <foreign lang="greek">MI/MHSIS</foreign> where "representation" would be clumsy we
					may use the word "art"; the adjective must be "imitative," since
					"representative" has other meanings.</note>
				<milestone n="1.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But they differ one from another in
				three ways: either in using means generically different<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., means that can be divided into separate categories.</note> or
				in representing different objects or in representing objects not in the same way but
				in a different manner. <milestone n="1.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>For just as by
				the use both of color and form people represent many objects, making likenesses of
					them&mdash;<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>some having a
				knowledge of art and some working empirically&mdash;and just as others use the
				human voice; so is it also in the arts which we have mentioned, they all make their
				representations in rhythm and language and tune, using these means either separately
				or in combination. <milestone n="1.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For tune and rhythm
				alone are employed in flute-playing and harp-playing and in any other arts which
				have a similar function, as, for example, pipe-playing. <milestone n="1.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Rhythm alone without tune is employed by dancers in their
				representations, for by means of rhythmical gestures they represent both character
				and experiences and actions.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><foreign lang="greek">PA/QH KAI\ PRA/CEIS</foreign> cover the whole field of life, what men do
						(<foreign lang="greek">PRA/CEIS</foreign>) and what men experience (<foreign lang="greek">PA/QH</foreign>). Since <foreign lang="greek">PA/QH</foreign>
					means also "emotions" and that sense may be present here, but as a technical
					term in this treatise <foreign lang="greek">PA/QOS</foreign> is a calamity or
					tragic incident, something that happens to the hero.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="1.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But the art which
				employs words either in bare prose or in metres, <milestone n="1447b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>either in one kind of metre or
				combining several, happens up to the present day to have no name. <milestone n="1.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For we can find no common term to apply to the mimes
				of Sophron and Xenarchus<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Sophron and Xenarchus, said
					to he father and son, lived in <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, the elder a contemporary of Euripides. They wrote
					"mimes," i.e., simple and usually farcical sketches of familiar incidents,
					similar to the mimes of Herondas and the fifteenth Idyll of Theocritus, but in
					prose. There was a tradition that their mimes suggested to Plato the use of
					dialogue.</note> and to the Socratic dialogues: <milestone n="1.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> nor again supposing a poet were to make his representation in
				iambics or elegiacs or any other such metre&mdash;except that people attach the
				word poet&lpar;maker&rpar;to the name of the metre and speak of elegiac
				poets and of others as epic poets. <milestone n="1.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				Thus they do not call them poets in virtue of their representation but apply the
				name indiscriminately in virtue of the metre. <milestone n="1.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For if people publish medical or scientific treatises in
				metre the custom is to call them poets. But Homer and Empedocles<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Empedocles (floruit <date value="-445">445</date> B.C.) expressed
					his philosophical and religious teaching in hexameter verse, to which Aristotle
					elsewhere attributes genuine value as poetry, but it is here excluded from the
					ranks of poetry because the object is definitely.</note> have nothing in common
				except the metre, so that it would be proper to call the one a poet and the other not
				a poet but a scientist.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="1.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Similarly if a man makes his representation
				by combining all the metres, as Chaeremon did when he wrote his rhapsody <title>The
					Centaur</title>, a medley of all the metres, he too should be given the name of
					poet.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Chaeremon was a tragedian and rhapsodist.
					The <title>Centaur</title> was apparently an experiment which might be classed
					as either drama or epic. Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1460a">Aristot. Poet.
						24.11</bibl>.</note> On this point the distinctions thus made may
					suffice.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="1.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There are certain arts which employ all the means which I
				have mentioned, such as rhythm and tune and metre&mdash;dithyrambic and "nomic"
					poetry,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The traditional definition is that the
					Dithyramb was sung to a flute accompaniment by a chorus in honor of Dionysus;
					and that the Nome was a solo sung to a harp accompaniment in honor of Apollo,
					but it is not clear that Aristotle regarded the Dithyramb as restricted to the
					worship of Dionysus. Timotheus's dithyramb mentioned in <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1454a">Aristot. Poet. 15.8</bibl> cannot have been
					Dionysiac. But there is good evidence to show that the dithyramb was primarily
					associated with Dionysus.</note> for example, and tragedy too and comedy. The
				difference here is that some use all these at once, others use now one now another.
					<milestone n="1.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These differences then in the
				various arts I call the means of representation. <milestone n="1448a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="2.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Since living persons<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Literally "men doing or experiencing
					something."</note> are the objects of representation, these must necessarily be
				either good men or inferior&mdash;thus only are characters normally
				distinguished, since ethical differences depend upon vice and virtue&mdash;that
				is to say either better than ourselves or worse or much what we are. It is the same
				with painters. <milestone n="2.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Polygnotus depicted men
				as better than they are and Pauson worse, while Dionysius made likenesses.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Polygnotus's portraits were in the grand style and
					yet expressive of character&lpar;cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1450a">Aristot.
						Poet. 6.15</bibl>&rpar;: Aristophanes aIludes to a Pauson as a
					"perfectly wicked caricaturist": Dionysius of <placeName key="perseus,Colophon">Colophon</placeName> earned the name of "the man-painter" because he always
					painted men and presumably made "good likenesses."</note>
				<milestone n="2.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Clearly each of the above mentioned
				arts will admit of these distinctions, and they will differ in representing objects
				which differ from each other in the way here described. <milestone n="2.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In painting too, and flute-playing and harp-playing, these
				diversities may certainly be found, and it is the same in prose and in unaccompanied
				verse. <milestone n="2.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For instance Homer's people are
				"better," Cleophon's are "like," while in Hegemon of <placeName key="perseus,Thasos City">Thasos</placeName>, the first writer of parodies, and in Nicochares, the author
				of the <title>Poltrooniad</title>, they are "worse."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Cleophon wrote "epics" (i.e., hexameter poems), describing scenes of daily life
					in commonplace diction (cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1458a">Aristot. Poet.
						22.2</bibl>): Hegemon wrote mock epics in the style of the surviving
						<title>Battle of Frog and Mice</title>: of Nicochares nothing is known, but
					his forte was evidently satire.</note>
				<milestone n="2.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is the same in dithyrambic and nomic
				poetry, for instance . . . a writer might draw characters like the
					Cyclops as drawn by Timotheus and Philoxenus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Both famous dithyramhic poets. There is evidence that
					Philoxenus treated Polyphemus in the vein of satire: Timotheus may have drawn a
					more dignified picture.</note>
				<milestone n="2.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is just in this respect that tragedy
				differs from comedy. The latter sets out to represent people as worse than they are
				to-day, the former as better.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="3.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A third difference in these arts is the manner in
				which one may represent each of these objects.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="3.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For in representing
				the same objects by the same means it is possible to proceed either partly by
				narrative and partly by assuming a character other than your own&mdash;this is
				Homer's method&mdash;or by remaining yourself without any such change, or else
				to represent the characters as carrying out the whole action themselves.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="3.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These, as we
				said above, are the three differences which form the several species of the art of
				representation, the means, the objects, and the manner.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="3.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It follows that in one respect
				Sophocles would be the same kind of artist as Homer, for both represent good men,
				and in another respect he would resemble Aristophanes, for they both represent men
				in action and doing things. And that according to some is the reason why they are
				called "dramas," because they present people as doing<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">"Drama" being derived from <foreign lang="greek">DRA=N</foreign> "to
					do."</note> things. <milestone n="3.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And for this
				reason the Dorians claim as their own both tragedy and comedy&mdash;comedy is
				claimed both by the Megarians here in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, who say that it originated in the days of their democracy,
				and by the Megarians in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The inhabitants of <placeName key="perseus,Megara Hyblaea">Megara Hyblaea</placeName>.</note> for it was
				from there the poet Epicharmus<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Epicharmus of Cos
					wrote in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> burlesques and "mimes"
					depicting scenes of daily life. He and Phormis were "originators of comedy" in
					that they sketched types instead of lampooning individuals (cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1449b">Aristot. Poet. 5.5</bibl>): of Chionides and Magnes
					we only know that they were "early" comedians, i.e., in the first half of the
					fifth century B.C.</note> came, who was much earlier than Chionides and Magnes;
				and tragedy some of the Peloponnesians claim. Their evidence is the two names.
					<milestone n="3.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Their name, they say, for suburb
				villages is <foreign lang="greek">KW=MAI</foreign>&mdash;the Athenians call them
				"Demes"&mdash;and comedians are so called not from <foreign lang="greek">KWMA/ZEIN</foreign>, "to revel," but because they were turned out of the towns
				and went strolling round the villages&lpar; <foreign lang="greek">KW=MAI</foreign>&rpar;. <milestone n="1448b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>Their word for action, they add, is <foreign lang="greek">DRA=N</foreign>, whereas the Athenian word is <foreign lang="greek">PRA/TTEIN</foreign>. So much then for the differences, their number, and their
					nature.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="4.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Speaking generally, poetry seems to owe its origin to two particular causes, both
				natural. <milestone n="4.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> From childhood men have an
				instinct for representation, and in this respect, differs from the other animals
				that he is far more imitative and learns his first lessons by representing things.
				And then there is the enjoyment people always get from representations. <milestone n="4.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> What happens in actual experience proves this,
				for we enjoy looking at accurate likenesses of things which are themselves painful
				to see, obscene beasts, for instance, and corpses. <milestone n="4.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The reason is this: Learning things gives great pleasure not
				only to philosophers but also in the same way to all other men, though they share
				this pleasure only to a small degree. <milestone n="4.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				The reason why we enjoy seeing likenesses is that, as we look, we learn and infer
				what each is, for instance, "that is so and so." <milestone n="4.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If we have never happened to see the original, our pleasure
				is not due to the representation as such but to the technique or the color or some
				other such cause.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="4.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We have, then, a
				natural instinct for representation and for tune and rhythm<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">It is not clear wheter the "two general causes" are (1) the instinct
					for imitation, (2) the natural enjoyment of mimicry by others; or whether these
					two are combined into one and the second cause is the instinct for tune and
					rhythm. Obviously this last is an essential cause of
				poetry.</note>&mdash;for the metres are obviously sections of rhythms<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">e.g., the rhythm of the blacksmith's hammer or of a
					trotting horse is dactylic, but the hexameter is a "section" or slice of that
					rhythm; it is cut up into sixes.</note>&mdash;and starting with these
				instincts men very gradually developed them until they produced poetry out of their
				improvisations. <milestone n="4.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Poetry then split into
				two kinds according to the poet's nature. For the more serious poets represented
				fine doings and the doings of fine men, while those of a less exalted nature
				represented the actions of inferior men, at first writing satire just as the others
				at first wrote hymns and eulogies. <milestone n="4.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				Before Homer we cannot indeed name any such poem, though there were probably many
				satirical poets, <milestone n="4.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> but starting from
				Homer, there is, for instance, his <title>Margites</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A famous burlesque which Aristotle attributes to Homer. "Other
					similar poems" must mean other early burlesques not necessarily attributed to
					Homer.</note> and other similar poems. For these the iambic metre was fittingly
				introduced and that is why it is still called iambic, because it was the metre in
				which they lampooned each other.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Since the iambic
					came to be the metre of invective, the verb <foreign lang="greek">I)AMBI/ZEIN</foreign> acquired the meaning "to lampoon." There is probably
					implied a derivation from <foreign lang="greek">I)A/PTEIN</foreign>, " to
					assail."</note>
				<milestone n="4.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of the ancients some wrote heroic
				verse and some iambic. <milestone n="4.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And just as
				Homer was a supreme poet in the serious style, since he alone made his
				representations not only good but also dramatic, so, too, he was the first to mark
				out the main lines of comedy, since he made his drama not out of personal satire but
				out of the laughable as such. His <title>Margites</title> indeed provides an
				analogy: as are the <title>Iliad</title> and <title>Odyssey</title> to our
				tragedies, <milestone n="1449a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>so is the <title>Margites</title> to our comedies.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="4.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> When tragedy and
				comedy came to light, poets were drawn by their natural bent towards one or the
				other. Some became writers of comedies instead of lampoons, the others produced
				tragedies instead of epics; the reason being that the former is in each case a
				higher kind of art and has greater value.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To consider
				whether tragedy is fully developed by now in all its various species or not, and to
				criticize it both in itself and in relation to the stage, that is another question.
					<milestone n="4.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> At any rate it originated in
				improvisation&mdash;both tragedy itself and comedy. The one came from the
					prelude<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Before the chorus began &lpar;or in
					pauses between their songs&rpar; the leader of the performance would
					improvise some appropriate tale or state the theme which they were to elaborate.
					Thus he was called <foreign lang="greek">O( E)CA/RXWN</foreign> or "the
					starter," and became in time the first "actor."</note> to the dithyramb and the
				other from the prelude to the phallic songs which still survive as institutions in
				many cities. <milestone n="4.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Tragedy then gradually
				evolved as men developed each element that came to light and after going through
				many changes, it stopped when it had found its own natural form. <milestone n="4.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Thus it was Aeschylus who first raised the number of
				the actors from one to two. He also curtailed the chorus and gave the dialogue the
				leading part. Three actors and scene-painting Sophocles introduced. <milestone n="4.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Then as to magnitude.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>Being a development of the Satyr play,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A Satyr play was an interlude performed by a troupe
					of actors dressed as the goat-like followers of Dionysus. Hence <foreign lang="greek">TRAGW|DI/A</foreign>, "goat-song." Aristotle seems so clear
					about this that he does not trouble to give a full explanation. But we can see
					from this passage that the Satyr plays were short, jocose and in the trochaic
					metre which suited their dances, and that in Aristotle's view tragedy was
					evolved from these. No example of a primitive Satyr play survives, but we can
					make inferences from the later, more sophisticated <title>
						Cyclops
					</title> of Euripides and the fragments of Sophocles' <title><foreign lang="greek">*)IXNEUTAI/</foreign>, The Trackers</title>. We cannot be
					certain that Aristotle's theory is historically correct; the balance of evidence
					is against it.</note> it was quite late before tragedy rose from short plots and
				comic diction to its full dignity, and that the iambic metre was used instead of the
				trochaic tetrameter. <milestone n="4.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> At first they
				used the tetrameter because its poetry suited the Satyrs and was better for dancing,
				but when dialogue was introduced, Nature herself discovered the proper metre. The
				iambic is indeed the most conversational of the metres, <milestone n="4.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and the proof is that in talking to each other we most often
				use iambic lines but very rarely hexameters and only when we rise above the ordinary
				pitch of conversation. <milestone n="4.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Then there is
				the number of acts. The further embellishments<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Masks, costumes, etc.</note> and the story of their introduction one by one we
				may take as told, <milestone n="4.21" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> for it would
				probably be a long task to go through them in detail.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="5.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Comedy, as we have said, is a
				representation of inferior people, not indeed in the full sense of the word bad, but
				the laughable is a species of the base or ugly.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">"Ugly" was to a Greek an equivalent of "bad." The persons in Comedy are
					"inferior" &lpar;see chapter 2.&rpar;, but have only one of the many
					qualities which make up Ugliness or Badness, viz. the quality of being ludicrous
					and therefore in some degree contemptible.</note>
				<milestone n="5.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It consists in some blunder or ugliness
				that does not cause pain or disaster, an obvious example being the comic mask which
				is ugly and distorted but not painful.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="5.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The various stages of tragedy and the
				originators of each are well known, but comedy remains obscure because it was not at
				first treated seriously. <milestone n="1449b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>Indeed it is only quite late in its history<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Probably about <date value="-465">465</date>
					B.C.</note> that the archon granted a chorus for a comic poet; before that they
				were volunteers.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In the fifth century dramatists
					submitted their plays to the archon in charge of the festival at which they
					wished them to be performed. He selected the number required by the particular
					festival, and to the poets thus selected "granted a chorus," i.e., provided a
					choregus who paid the expenses of the chorus. The earlier "volunteers" had
					themselves paid for and produced their plays.</note>
				<milestone n="5.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Comedy had already taken certain forms
				before there is any mention of those who are called its poets. Who introduced masks
				or prologues, the number of actors, and so on, is not known. <milestone n="5.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Plot making &lsqb;Epicharmus and
					Phormis&rsqb;<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Epicharmus and Phormis, being
					both early Sicilian "comedians", are appropriate here. Either part of a sentence
					is lost or an explanatory note has got into the text.</note> originally came
				from <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, <milestone n="5.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and of the Athenian poets Crates<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Fragments of his comedies survive, dating about the middle of the
					fifth century B.C.</note> was the first to give up the lampooning form and to
				generalize his dialogue and plots.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="5.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Epic poetry agreed with tragedy only in so far as it
				was a metrical representation of heroic action, but inasmuch as it has a single
				metre and is narrative in that respect they are different. <milestone n="5.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And then as regards length, tragedy tends to fall within a
				single revolution of the sun or slightly to exceed that, whereas epic is unlimited
				in point of time; <milestone n="5.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and that is another
				difference, although originally the practice was the same in tragedy as in epic
					poetry.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="5.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The constituent parts are some of them the same and some
				peculiar to tragedy. <milestone n="5.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Consequently any
				one who knows about tragedy, good and bad, knows about epics too, since tragedy has
				all the elements of epic poetry, though the elements of tragedy are not all present
				in the epic.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="6.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> With the representation of life
				in hexameter verse<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., epic poetry.</note> and
				with comedy we will deal later. We must now treat of tragedy after first gathering
				up the definition of its nature which results from what we have said already.
					<milestone n="6.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Tragedy is, then, a representation
				of an action<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Margoliouth's phrase "a chapter of
					life," illuminates the meaning, since <foreign lang="greek">PRA=CIS</foreign>
					includes what the hero does and what happens to him. (Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1448a">Aristot. Poet. 2.1</bibl> and note.)</note> that is
				heroic and complete and of a certain magnitude&mdash;by means of language
				enriched with all kinds of ornament, each used separately in the different parts of
				the play: it represents men in action and does not use narrative, and through pity
				and fear it effects relief to these and similar emotions.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The sense of "the pity of it "and fear lest such disasters might
					befall ourselves are not the only emotions which tragedy releases, but Aristotle
					specifies them as the most characteristic. For <foreign lang="greek">KA/QARSIS,</foreign> see Introduction.</note>
				<milestone n="6.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> By "language enriched" I mean that
				which has rhythm and tune, i.e., song, <milestone n="6.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				and by "the kinds separately" I mean that some effects are produced by verse alone
				and some again by song.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Since the representation is performed by living persons, it
				follows at once that one essential part of a tragedy is the spectacular effect, and,
				besides that, song-making and diction. For these are the means of the
				representation. <milestone n="6.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> By "diction" I mean
				here the metrical arrangement of the words; and "song making" I use in the full,
				obvious sense of the word. <milestone n="6.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And since
				tragedy represents action and is acted by living persons, who must of necessity have
				certain qualities of character and thought&mdash;for it is these which determine
				the quality of an action; <milestone n="1450a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>indeed thought and character are the natural causes of
				any action and it is in virtue of these that all men succeed or
					fail&mdash;<milestone n="6.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> it follows then that
				it is the plot which represents the action. By "plot" I mean here the arrangement of
				the incidents: "character" is that which determines the quality of the agents, and
				"thought" appears wherever in the dialogue they put forward an argument or deliver
				an opinion.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Necessarily then every tragedy has six constituent parts, and on these its
				quality depends. These are plot, character, diction, thought, spectacle, and song.
					<milestone n="6.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Two of these are the means of
				representation: one is the manner: three are the objects represented.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The "means" are diction and music: the "manner" is
					"spectacle": the "objects" represented are actions or experiences and the moral
					or intellectual qualities of the dramatis personae.</note>
				<milestone n="6.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> This list is exhaustive, and
				practically all the poets employ these elements, for every drama includes alike
				spectacle and character and plot and diction and song and thought.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The most important of
				these is the arrangement of the incidents,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e.,
					"plot," as defined above.</note> for tragedy is not a representation of men but
				of a piece of action, of life, of happiness and unhappiness, which come under the
				head of action, and the end aimed at is the representation not of qualities of
				character but of some action; and while character makes men what they are,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>it's their actions and experiences that make
				them happy or the opposite. <milestone n="6.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> They do
				not therefore act to represent character, but character-study is included for the
				sake of the action. It follows that the incidents and the plot are the end at which
				tragedy aims, and in everything the end aimed at is of prime importance. <milestone n="6.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Moreover, you could not have a tragedy
				without action, but you can have one with out character-study. <milestone n="6.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Indeed the tragedies of most modern poets are without
				this, and, speaking generally, there are many such writers, whose case is like that
				of Zeuxis compared with Polygnotus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Zeuxis's
					portraits were "ideal" (cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1461b">Aristot. Poet.
						25.28</bibl>).</note> The latter was good at depicting character, but there
				is nothing of this in Zeuxis's painting. <milestone n="6.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A further argument is that if a man writes a series of speeches full of character
				and excellent in point of diction and thought, he will not achieve the proper
				function of tragedy nearly so well as a tragedy which, while inferior in these
				qualities, has a plot or arrangement of incidents. <milestone n="6.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And furthermore, two of the most important elements in the
				emotional effect of tragedy, "reversals" and "discoveries,"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See chapter 11.</note> are parts of the plot. <milestone n="6.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And here is further proof: those who try to write
				tragedy are much sooner successful in language and character-study than in arranging
				the incidents. It is the same with almost all the earliest poets.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The plot then is the
				first principle and as it were the soul of tragedy: character comes second.
					<milestone n="6.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is much the same also in
				painting; <milestone n="1450b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>if a man smeared a canvas with the loveliest colors at random, it
				would not give as much pleasure as an outline in black and white.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Selection and design are necessary for aay work of
					"representation."</note>
				<milestone n="6.21" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And it is mainly because a play is a
				representation of action that it also for that reason represents people.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.22" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Third comes
				"thought." This means the ability to say what is possible and appropriate. It comes
				in the dialogue and is the function of the statesman's or the rhetorician's
					art.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Cf. chapter 6.</note>
				<milestone n="6.23" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The old writers made their characters
				talk like statesmen,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Or "in the style of ordinary
					people," without obvious rhetorical artifice.</note> the moderns like
					rhetoricians.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.24" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Character is that which reveals choice<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><foreign lang="greek">PROAI/RESIS</foreign> is a technical term in
					Aristotle's ethics, corresponding to our use of the term "Will," the deliberate
					adoption of any course of conduct or line of action. It is a man's will or
					choice in the sense that determines the goodness or badness of his character. If
					character is to be revealed in drama, a man must be shown in the exercise of his
					will, choosing between one line of conduct and another, and he must be placed in
					circumstances in wbich the choice is not obvious, i.e., circumstances in which
					everybody's choice would not be the same. The choice of death rather than
					disbonourable wealth reveals character; the choice of a nectarine rather than a
					turnip does not.</note>, shows what sort of thing a man chooses or avoids in
				circumstances where the choice is not obvious, so those speeches convey no character
				in which there is nothing whatever which the speaker chooses or avoids.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.25" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> "Thought" you
				find in speeches which contain an argument that something is or is not, or a general
				expression of opinion.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.26" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The fourth of the literary elements is the language. By this
				I mean, as we said above, the expression of meaning in words,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This seems to be a mistaken reference to 6 above where "diction" is
					defined as "the metrical arrangement of the words." In poetry they come to the
					same thing.</note> and this is essentially the same in verse and in
					prose.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="6.27" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of the other elements which "enrich"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1449b">Aristot. Poet. 6.2</bibl>.</note> tragedy the most
				important is song-making. <milestone n="6.28" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Spectacle,
				while highly effective, is yet quite foreign to the art and has nothing to do with
				poetry. Indeed the effect of tragedy does not depend on its performance by actors,
				and, moreover,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>for achieving the
				spectacular effects the art of the costumier is more authoritative than that of the
					poet.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="7.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				After these definitions we must next discuss the proper arrangement of the incidents
				since this is the first and most important thing in tragedy. <milestone n="7.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We have laid it down that tragedy is a representation
				of an action that is whole and complete and of a certain magnitude, since a thing
				may be a whole and yet have no magnitude. <milestone n="7.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A whole is what has a beginning and middle and end. <milestone n="7.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A beginning is that which is not a necessary consequent of
				anything else but after which something else exists or happens as a natural result.
					<milestone n="7.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An end on the contrary is that
				which is inevitably or, as a rule, the natural result of something else but from
				which nothing else follows; <milestone n="7.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> a middle
				follows something else and something follows from it. <milestone n="7.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Well constructed plots must not therefore begin and end at
				random, but must embody the formulae we have stated.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="7.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Moreover, in everything that is
				beautiful, whether it be a living creature or any organism composed of parts, these
				parts must not only be orderly arranged but must also have a certain magnitude of
				their own; <milestone n="7.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> for beauty consists in
				magnitude and ordered arrangement. From which it follows that neither would a very
				small creature be beautiful&mdash;for our view of it is almost instantaneous and
				therefore confused<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">With a very small object the
					duration of our vision is, as it were, so rapid that the parts are invisible;
					we, therefore, cannot appreciate their proportion and arrangement, in which
					beauty consists.</note>&mdash;nor a very large one, <milestone n="1451a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>since being unable to
				view it all at once, we lose the effect of a single whole; for instance, suppose a
				creature a thousand miles long. <milestone n="7.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> As
				then creatures and other organic structures must have a certain magnitude and yet be
				easily taken in by the eye, so too with plots: they must have length but must be
				easily taken in by the memory.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="7.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The limit of length considered in relation to
				competitions and production<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><foreign lang="greek">AI)/SQHSIS</foreign> is the play's "perception" by an
					audience&mdash;how much an audience will stand.</note> before an audience
				does not concern this treatise. Had it been the rule to produce a hundred tragedies,
				the performance would have been regulated by the water clock, as it is said they did
				once in other days. <milestone n="7.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But as for the
				natural limit of the action, the longer the better as far as magnitude goes,
				provided it can all be grasped at once. To give a simple definition: the magnitude
				which admits of a change from bad fortune to good or from good fortune to bad, in a
				sequence of events which follow one another either inevitably or according to
				probability, that is the proper limit.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="8.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A plot does not have unity, as some people
				think, simply because it deals with a single hero. Many and indeed innumerable
				things happen to an individual, some of which do not go to make up any unity, and
				similarly an individual is concerned in many actions which do not combine into a
				single piece of action.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="8.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It seems therefore that all those poets are wrong who
				have written a <title>Heracleid</title> or <title>Theseid</title> or other such
					poems.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Aristotle condemns them all,
					assuming&mdash;or perhaps assured by experience&mdash;that their sole
					claim to unity lay in the fact that all the stories in the poem had a common
					hero.</note> They think that because Heracles was a single individual the plot
				must for that reason have unity. <milestone n="8.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But
				Homer, supreme also in all other respects, was apparently well aware of this truth
				either by instinct or from knowledge of his art. For in writing an
					<title>Odyssey</title> he did not put in all that ever happened to Odysseus, his
				being wounded on <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>, for instance,
				or his feigned madness when the host was gathered&lpar;these being events
				neither of which necessarily or probably led to the other&rpar;, but he
				constructed his <title>Odyssey</title> round a single action in our sense of the
				phrase. And the <title>Iliad</title> the same. <milestone n="8.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> As then in the other arts of representation a single
				representation means a representation of a single object, so too the plot being a
				representation of a piece of action must represent a single piece of action and the
				whole of it; and the component incidents must be so arranged that if one of them be
				transposed or removed, the unity of the whole is dislocated and destroyed. For if
				the presence or absence of a thing makes no visible difference, then it is not an
				integral part of the whole.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="9.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> What we have said already makes it further clear that a
				poet's object is not to tell what actually happened but what could and would happen
				either probably or inevitably. <milestone n="9.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The
				difference between a historian and a poet is not that one writes in prose and the
				other in verse&mdash; <milestone n="1451b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>indeed the writings of Herodotus could be put into
				verse and yet would still be a kind of history, whether written in metre or not. The
				real difference is this, that one tells what happened and the other what might
				happen. <milestone n="9.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For this reason poetry is
				something more scientific and serious than history, because poetry tends to give
				general truths while history gives particular facts.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="9.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> By a "general truth" I mean the
				sort of thing that a certain type of man will do or say either probably or
				necessarily. That is what poetry aims at in giving names to the characters.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The names indicate types. This is obvious, as he
					says, in Comedy and is also true of Greek Tragedy, which, although it deals with
					traditional heroes regarded as "real people," yet keeps to a few stories in
					which each character has become a type. In Chapter 17. the dramatist is
					recommended to sketch first his outline plot, making it clear and coherent,
					before he puts in the names.</note> A "particular fact" is what Alcibiades did
				or what was done to him. <milestone n="9.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In the case of
				comedy this has now become obvious, for comedians construct their plots out of
				probable incidents and then put in any names that occur to them. They do not, like
				the iambic satirists, write about individuals.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Aristophanes of course did write about individuals. But Aristotle is thinking
					of the New Comedy, where the names of the characters were invented by the author
					and there was no reference to real people.</note>
				<milestone n="9.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In tragedy, on the other hand, they
				keep to real names. The reason is that what is possible carries conviction. If a
				thing has not happened, we do not yet believe in its possibility, but what has
				happened is obviously possible. Had it been impossible, it would not have
					happened.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="9.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is true that in some tragedies one or two of the names are
				familiar and the rest invented; indeed in some they are all invented, as for
				instance in Agathon's <title>Antheus</title>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The
					name, apparently, of an imaginary hero. The word might be <foreign lang="greek">*)/ANQOS</foreign>, but "The Flower" is an unlikely title for a Greek
					tragedy.</note> where both the incidents and the names are invented and yet it
				is none the less a favourite. <milestone n="9.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> One need
				not therefore endeavor invariably to keep to the traditional stories with which our
				tragedies deal. Indeed it would be absurd to do that, seeing that the familiar
				themes are familiar only to a few and yet please all.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The reason why Greek tragedy dealt only with a few familiar themes
					is to be found of course in its religious origin. It was the function of tragedy
					to interpret and embroider myths. Aristotle never gives this reason, but offers
					instead tbe unconvincing explanation that tragedians adhered to certain "real"
					stories to gain verisimilitude&mdash;and yet he has to admit that, since to
					many of the auditors these stories were unfamiliar and none the less attractive,
					dramatists might just as well invent new themes.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="9.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is clear, then,
				from what we have said that the poet must be a "maker" not of verses but of stories,
				since he is a poet in virtue of his "representation," and what he represents is
				action. <milestone n="9.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Even supposing he represents
				what has actually happened, he is none the less a poet, for there is nothing to
				prevent some actual occurrences being the sort of thing that would probably or
				inevitably happen, and it is in virtue of that that he is their "maker."<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="9.11a" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of
					"simple"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This term is defined in the next
					chapter. It seems odd to use it before its meaning is explained. Perhaps we
					should read <foreign lang="greek">A)/LLWN</foreign>&lpar;Tyrwhitt&rpar;and translate "of all
					plots."</note> plots and actions the worst are those which are "episodic." By
				this I mean a plot in which the episodes do not follow each other probably or
				inevitably. <milestone n="9.11b" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Bad poets write such
				plays because they cannot help it, and good poets write them to please the actors.
				Writing as they do for competition, they often strain a plot beyond its capacity and
				are thus obliged to sacrifice continuity.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Or
					"logic." He means the chain of cause and effect, wherein each incident is the
					result of what has gone before. See the end of the next chapter.</note>
				<milestone n="9.11c" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But this is bad work, <milestone n="1452a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>since
				tragedy represents not only a complete action but also incidents that cause fear and
				pity, and this happens most of all when the incidents are unexpected and yet one is
				a consequence of the other.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The logic suffers from
					ellipse. Plays which fail to exhibit the sequence of cause and effect are
					condemned &lpar;1&rpar; because they lack the unity which befits
					tragedy, &lpar;2&rpar; because they miss that supreme effect of fear or
					pity produced by incidents which, though unexpected, are seen to be no mere
					accident but the inevitable result of what has gone before.</note>
				<milestone n="9.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For in that way the incidents will
				cause more amazement than if they happened mechanically and accidentally, since the
				most amazing accidental occurrences are those which seem to have been providential,
				for instance when the statue of Mitys at <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> killed the man who caused Mitys's death by falling on him at
				a festival. Such events do not seem to be mere accidents. <milestone n="9.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> So such plots as these must necessarily be the
					best.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="10.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Some plots are "simple" and some "complex," as indeed the actions represented by
				the plots are obviously such. <milestone n="10.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> By a
				simple action I mean one that is single and continuous in the sense of our
				definition above,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In chapters 7 and 8.</note>
				wherein the change of fortune occurs without "reversal" or "discovery"; <milestone n="10.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> by a complex action I mean one wherein the
				change coincides with a "discovery" or "reversal" or both. <milestone n="10.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These should result from the actual structure of the
				plot in such a way that what has already happened makes the result inevitable or
					probable;<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>for there is indeed a vast
				difference between what happens propter hoc and post hoc.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="11.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A "reversal" is a
				change of the situation into the opposite, as described above,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">At the end of chapter 7. Vahlen and many other exponents of the
						<title>Politics</title> confine the meaning of
					&ldquo;reversal&rdquo; to the situation in which the hero's action has
					consequences directly opposite to his intention and expectation. There is much
					to be said for this interpretation, which stresses the irony at the heart of all
					tragedy. But it is too narrow for Aristotle's theory. All tragedy involves a
					change of fortune &lpar; <foreign lang="greek">META/BASIS</foreign>&rpar;. In a &ldquo;simple&rdquo; plot this is
					gradual; in a &ldquo;complex&rdquo; plot it is catastrophic, a sudden
					revolution of fortune's wheel. In some of the greatest tragedies, but not in
					all, this is the result of action designed to produce the opposite
					effect.</note> this change being, moreover, as we are saying, probable or
					inevitable&mdash;<milestone n="11.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> like the man
				in the <title>Oedipus</title> who came to cheer Oedipus and rid him of his anxiety
				about his mother by revealing his parentage and changed the whole situation.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The messenger for <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> announces the death of Polybus and Oedipus's succession
					to the throne. Oedipus, feeling now safe from the prophecy that he would murder
					his father, still fears to return to <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, lest he should fulfil the other prophecy and marry his
					mother. The messenger seeks to reassure him by announcing that Polybus and
					Merope are not his parents. But the effect of this was to "change the whole
					situation" for Oedipus by revealing the truth that he a murdered his father,
					Laius, and married his mother, Jocasta. This "reversal" is the more effective
					because it is immediately coincident with the discovery of the truth.</note> In
				the <title>Lynceus</title>, too, there is the man led off to execution and
					<milestone n="11.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Danaus following to kill him, and
				the result of what had already happened was that the latter was killed and the
				former escaped.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Lynceus married Hypermnestra who
					disobeyed Danaus in not murdering him. Danaus trying by process of law to
					compass the death of their son Abas was killed himself. "The dog it was that
					died."</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="11.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A "discovery," as the term itself implies, is a change from
				ignorance to knowledge, producing either friendship or hatred in those who are
				destined for good fortune or ill. <milestone n="11.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A
				discovery is most effective when it coincides with reversals, such as that involved
				by the discovery in the <title>Oedipus</title>. <milestone n="11.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There are also other forms of discovery, for what we have
				described may in a sense occur in relation to inanimate and trivial objects, or one
				may discover whether some one has done something or not. <milestone n="11.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But the discovery which is most essentially part of the plot
				and part of the action is of the kind described above, for such a discovery and
				reversal of fortune will involve either pity or fear, <milestone n="1452b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>and it is actions such
				as these which, according to our hypothesis, tragedy represents; and, moreover,
				misfortune and good fortune are likely to turn upon such incidents.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="11.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now since the
				discovery is somebody's discovery, in some scenes one character only is discovered
				to another, the identity of the other being obvious; but sometimes each must
				discover the other. Thus Iphigeneia was discovered to Orestes through the sending of
				the letter, but a separate discovery was needed to make him known to
					Iphigeneia.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Euripides' <title>Iphigeneia in
					
					Tauris</title>&mdash;Orestes and Pylades arriving among the
					Tauri are by the custom of the country to be sacrificed to Artemis by her
					priestess, Iphigeneia. It is agreed that Pylades shall be spared to carry a
					letter from Iphigeneia to Orestes, whom she supposes to be in <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. In order that Pylades may deliver the
					message, even if he should lose the letter, she reads it aloud. Orestes thus
					discovers who she is. He then reveals himself to her by declaring who he is and
					proving his identity by his memories of their home.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="11.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We see then that two
				elements of the plot, reversal and discovery, turn upon these incidents. A third
				element is a calamity. Of these three elements we have already described reversal
				and discovery. <milestone n="11.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A calamity is a
				destructive or painful occurrence, such as a death on the stage, acute suffering and
				wounding and so on.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="12.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We have already<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In chapter
					6.</note> spoken of the constituent parts to be used as ingredients of tragedy.
				The separable members into which it is quantitatively divided are these: Prologue,
				Episode, Exode, Choral Song, <milestone n="12.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> the last
				being divided into Parode and Stasimon. <milestone n="12.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These are common to all tragedies; songs sung by actors on the stage and "commoi"
				are peculiar to certain plays.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="12.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A prologue is the whole of that part of a tragedy
				which precedes the entrance of the chorus.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="12.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An episode is the whole of that
				part of a tragedy which falls between whole choral songs. <milestone n="12.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An exode is the whole of that part of a tragedy which is not
				followed by a song of the chorus. <milestone n="12.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A
				parode is the whole of the first utterance of the chorus. <milestone n="12.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A stasimon is a choral song without anapaests or
					trochaics.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This does not apply to surviving
					Greek tragedies, but may be true of those of Aristotle's time. The word Stasimon
					is applied to all choruses in a tragedy other than those sung during entry or
					exit. It is usually explained as meaning a "stationary song," because it was
					sung after the chorus had taken up its "station" in the orchestra.</note>
				<milestone n="12.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A commos is a song of lament shared by
				the chorus and the actors on the stage.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="12.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The constituent parts to be used as
				ingredients of tragedy have been described above; these are the separable members
				into which it is quantitatively divided.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The whole
					of chapter 12. bears marks of belonging to the Poetics but seems out of place,
					since it interrupts the discussion of "plot."</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="13.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Following upon what
				has been said above we should next state what ought to be aimed at and what avoided
				in the construction of a plot, and the means by which the object of tragedy may be
				achieved. <milestone n="13.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Since then the structure of
				the best tragedy should be not simple but complex<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See chapter 10.</note> and one that represents incidents arousing fear and
				pity&mdash;for that is peculiar to this form of art&mdash;it is obvious to
				begin with that one should not show worthy men passing from good fortune to bad.
				That does not arouse fear or pity but shocks our feelings. <milestone n="13.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Nor again wicked people passing from bad fortune to
				good. That is the most untragic of all, having none of the requisite qualities,
				since it does not satisfy our feelings<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., our
					preference for "poetic justice."</note> or arouse pity or fear. <milestone n="1453a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="13.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Nor again the passing of a thoroughly bad man
				from good fortune to bad fortune. Such a structure might satisfy our feelings but it
				arouses neither pity nor fear, the one being for the man who does not deserve his
				misfortune and the other for the man who is like ourselves&mdash;pity for the
				undeserved misfortune, fear for the man like ourselves&mdash;so that the result
				will arouse neither pity nor fear.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="13.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There remains then the mean between these. This is the
				sort of man who is not pre-eminently virtous and just, and yet it is through no
				badness or villainy of his own that he falls into the fortune, but rather through
				some flaw in him,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Whether Aristotle regards the
					&ldquo;flaw&rdquo; as intellectual or moral has been hotly discussed. It
					may cover both senses. The hero must not deserve his misfortune, but he must
					cause it by making a fatal mistake, an error of judgement, which may well
					involve some imperfection of character but not such as to make us regard him as
					&ldquo;morally responsible&rdquo; for the disasters although they are
					nevertheless the consequences of the flaw in him, and his wrong decision at a
					crisis is the inevitable outcome of his character&lpar;cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1450b">Aristot. Poet. 6.24</bibl>.&rpar;.</note> he
				being one of those who are in high station and good fortune, like Oedipus and
				Thyestes and the famous men of such families as those. <milestone n="13.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The successful plot must then have a single<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><foreign lang="greek">A(PLOU=S</foreign> elsewhere in
					the <title>Poetics</title> means "simple" as opposed to <foreign lang="greek">PEPLEGME/NOS</foreign>, "complex"; here it is opposed to <foreign lang="greek">DIPLOU=S</foreign>, which describes a double denouement,
					involving happiness for some and disaster for others.</note> and not, as some
				say, a double issue; and the change must be not to good fortune from bad but, on the
				contrary, from good to bad fortune, and it must not be due to villainy but to some
				great flaw in such a man as we have described, or of one who is better rather than
				worse. <milestone n="13.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> This can be seen also in actual
				practice. For at first poets accepted any plots, but to-day the best tragedies are
				written about a few families&mdash;<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>Alcmaeon for instance and Oedipus and Orestes and Meleager and Thyestes and
				Telephus and all the others whom it befell to suffer or inflict terrible
					disasters.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="13.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Judged then by the theory of the art, the best<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This is modified by 19 in the following chapter,
					where he finds an even better formula for the tragic effect.</note> tragedy is
				of this construction. <milestone n="13.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Those critics
				are therefore wrong who charge Euripides with doing this in his tragedies, and say
				that many of his end in misfortune. <milestone n="13.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				That is, as we have shown, correct. And there is very good evidence of this, for on
				the stage and in competitions such plays appear the most tragic of all, if they are
				successful, and even if Euripides is in other respects a bad manager,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Against Euripides Aristotle makes the following
					criticisms: &lpar;1&rpar;his choruses are often irrelevant;
					&lpar;2&rpar;the character of the heroine in his <title>Iphigeneia in
							Tauris</title> is inconsistent;
					&lpar;3&rpar;in the <title>Medea</title> the deliberate killing of the
					children is ineffective and the play is inartistically ended by the machina;
					&lpar;4&rpar;the character of Menelaus in the <title>Orestes</title> is
					needlessly depraved; &lpar;5&rpar;Melanippe is too philosophical for a
					woman.</note> yet he is certainly the most tragic of the poets.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="13.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Next in order comes
				the structure which some put first, that which has a double issue, like the
					<title>Odyssey</title>, and ends in opposite ways for the good characters and
				the bad. <milestone n="13.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is the sentimentality of
				the audience which makes this seem the best form; for the poets follow the wish of
				the spectators. <milestone n="13.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But this is not the
				true tragic pleasure but rather characteristic of comedy, where those who are bitter
				enemies in the story, Orestes and Aegisthus, for instance, go off at the end, having
				made friends, and nobody kills anybody. <milestone n="1453b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="14.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Fear and pity sometimes result
				from the spectacle and are sometimes aroused by the actual arrangement of the
				incidents, which is preferable and the mark of a better poet. <milestone n="14.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The plot should be so constructed that even without
				seeing the play anyone hearing of the incidents happening thrills with fear and pity
				as a result of what occurs. So would anyone feel who heard the story of Oedipus.
					<milestone n="14.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> To produce this effect by means of
				an appeal to the eye is inartistic and needs adventitious aid, <milestone n="14.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> while those who by such means produce an effect which
				is not fearful but merely monstrous have nothing in common with tragedy.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">that here were plays which relied for their effect on
					the scenery and "make up" is clear from chapter 17:&mdash;"The Phorcides and
					Prometheus and Scenes laid in Hades." It was even possible to produce the
						<title>Eumenides</title> so badly as to bring it into this category. But
					Aristotle's criticism here includes the more important point that the poignancy
					of a Greek tragedy is due to what happens and not to our seeing it happen. That
					Medea murders her children is tragic: to display the murder coram populo would
					add either nothing or something merely "monstrous." And although Sophocles shows
					Oedipus with his eyes out, it is the fact and not the sight which is properly
					"tragic."</note> For one should not seek from tragedy all kinds of pleasure but
				that which is peculiar to tragedy, <milestone n="14.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and
				since the poet must by "representation" produce the pleasure which comes from
				feeling pity and fear, obviously this quality must be embodied in the
					incidents.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="14.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We must now decide what incidents seem dreadful or rather
				pitiable. Such must necessarily be the actions of friends to each other or of
				enemies or of people that are neither. <milestone n="14.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				Now if an enemy does it to an enemy, there is nothing pitiable either in the deed or
				the intention, <milestone n="14.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> except so far as the
				actual calamity goes. <milestone n="14.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Nor would there
				be if they were neither friends nor enemies. But when these calamities happen among
					friends,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>when for instance brother
				kills brother, or son father, or mother son, or son mother&mdash;either kills or
				intends to kill, or does something of the kind, that is what we must look
					for.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="14.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now it is not right to break up the traditional stories, I mean, for instance,
				Clytaemnestra being killed by Orestes and Eriphyle by Alcmaeon, <milestone n="14.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> but the poet must show invention and make a skilful
				use of the tradition.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But we must state more clearly
				what is meant by "skilful." <milestone n="14.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The
				action may happen in the way in which the old dramatists made their characters
				act&mdash;consciously and knowing the facts, as Euripides<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This does not necessarily imply that Aristotle reckons Euripides
					&ldquo;a modern,&rdquo; since the Greek can equally mean
					&ldquo;Euripides as well as other old dramatists.&rdquo;</note> also
				made his Medea kill her children. <milestone n="14.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Or
				they may do the deed but without realizing the horror of it and then discover the
				relationship afterwards, like Oedipus in Sophocles. That indeed lies outside the
					play,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., Oedipus kills his father Laius
					before the play opens.</note> but an example of this in the tragedy itself is
				the <title>Alcmaeon</title> of Astydamas<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A prolific
					tragedian of the fourth century.</note> or Telegonus in the <title>Wounded
					Odysseus</title>. <milestone n="14.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A third
				alternative is to intend to do some irremediable action in ignorance and to discover
				the truth before doing it. <milestone n="14.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Besides
				these there is no other way, for they must either do the deed or not, either knowing
				or unknowing. <milestone n="14.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The worst of these is
				to intend the action with full knowledge and not to perform it. That outrages the
				feelings and is not tragic, for there is no calamity. <milestone n="1454a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>So nobody does that,
				except occasionally, as, for instance, Haemon and Creon<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Haemon, discovered by his father Creon embracing the dead body of
					Antigone, drew his sword on him but missed his aim and Creon fled.</note> in the
					<title>Antigone</title>. <milestone n="14.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Next
				comes the doing of the deed. <milestone n="14.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is
				better to act in ignorance and discover afterwards. Our feelings are not outraged
				and the discovery is startling. <milestone n="14.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Best
				of all is the last; in the <title>Cresphontes</title>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">By Euripides. Polyphontes killed Cresphontes, king of <placeName key="tgn,7011369">Messenia</placeName>, and gained possession of his kingdom
					and his wife, Merope. She had concealed her son, Aepytus, in <placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, and when he returned, seeking
					vengeance, she nearly killed him in ignorance but discovered who he was. He then
					killed Polyphontes and reigned in his stead.</note> for instance, Merope intends
				to kill her son and does not kill him but discovers; and in the
					<title>Iphigeneia</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><title>In
						Tauris</title>. See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1452b">Aristot. Poet. 11.8</bibl>, note.</note> the case
				of the sister and brother; and in the <title>Helle</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Author and play unknown.</note> the son discovers just as he is on
				the point of giving up his mother.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="14.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> So this is the reason, as was said
					above,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1453a">Aristot. Poet. 13.7</bibl>.</note> why tragedies are about a few families.
				For in their experiments it was from no technical knowledge but purely by chance
				that they found out how to produce such an effect in their stories. So they are
				obliged to have recourse to those families in which such calamities befell.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1451b">Aristot. Poet.
						9.8</bibl>, note.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="14.21" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now concerning the structure of the incidents and the
				proper character of the plots enough has been said.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Concerning "character" there are
				four points to aim at. The first and most important is that the character should be
				good. <milestone n="15.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The play will show character if,
				as we said above,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1450b">Aristot. Poet. 6.24</bibl>.</note> either the dialogue or the actions
				reveal some choice; and the character will be good, if the choice is good.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="15.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				But this is relative to each class of people. Even a woman is "good" and so is a
				slave, although it may be said that a woman is an inferior thing and a slave beneath
					consideration.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The second point is that the characters should be
				appropriate. A character may be manly, but it is not appropriate for a woman to be
				manly or clever.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Thirdly, it should be "like."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The meaning probably is "like the traditional person," e.g. Achilles must not
					be soft nor Odysseus stupid. Cf. <bibl n="Hor. Ars 120">Horace Ars Poet.
						120</bibl> "famam sequere."</note> This is different from making the
				character good and from making it appropriate in the sense of the word as used
					above.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Fourthly, it should be consistent. Even if the original be inconsistent and
				offers such a character to the poet for representation, still he must be
				consistently inconsistent.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An example of unnecessary badness of character is Menelaos in
				the <title>Orestes</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Aristotle has a personal
					distaste for this character on the ground that Euripides made him a creature
					meaner than the plot demands.</note>; <milestone n="15.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> of character that is unfitting and inappropriate the lament
				of Odysseus in the <title>Scylla</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A dithyramb
					by Timotheus. Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1461b">Aristot. Poet.
					26.3</bibl>.</note> and Melanippe's speech<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A
					fragment survives &lpar;<bibl n="Eur. Fr. 484">Eur. Fr. 484
					(Nauck)</bibl>&rpar;. Euripides seems to have given her a knowledge of
					science and philosophy inappropriate to a woman.</note>; <milestone n="15.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> of inconsistent character Iphigeneia in <placeName key="perseus,Aulis">Aulis</placeName>, for the suppliant Iphigeneia is not at
				all like her later character.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.10a" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In character-drawing just as much as in the
				arrangement of the incidents one should always seek what is inevitable or probable,
				so as to make it inevitable or probable that such and such a person should say or do
				such and such; and inevitable or probable that one thing should follow
					another.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.10b" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Clearly therefore the "denouement"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Or "unravelling."</note> of each play should also be the result of
				the plot itself and not produced mechanically as in the <title>Medea</title> and the
				incident of the embarkation in the Iliad. <milestone n="1454b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.155">Hom. Il. 2.155-181</bibl>, where it is only the
					arbitrary (i.e., uncaused) intervention of Athene which stays the flight of the
					Greeks. In the <title>Medea</title> the heroine, having killed her rival and her
					children, is spirited away in the chariot ot the Sun, a result not "caused" by
					what has gone before.</note><milestone n="15.10c" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>The
				"god in the car"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The <foreign lang="greek">MHXANH/</foreign> or "car" was a sort of crane with a pulley attached,
					which was fixed at the top of the back-scene in the left corner of the stage. By
					it a god or hero could be lowered or raised or exhibited motionless in mid-air.
					Weak dramatists thus introduced a car to "cut the knot" by declaring the
					denouement instead of unravelling the plot by the logic of cause and effect. It
					was presumably on such a "car" that Medea was borne away.</note> should only be
				used to explain what lies outside the play, either what happened earlier and is
				therefore beyond human knowledge, or what happens later and needs to be foretold in
				a proclamation. For we ascribe to the gods the power of seeing everything.
					<milestone n="15.10d" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There must, however, be nothing
				inexplicable in the incidents, or, if there is, it must lie outside the tragedy.
				There is an example in Sophocles' <title>Oedipus</title>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., Oedipus had killed Laius in a wayside quarrel, not knowing who
					he was. When his subjects at <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
					crave his help to remove the curse which is blighting their crops, he pledges
					himself to discover the murderer of Laius. It may seem odd that he should not
					know enough about the details of the murder to connect it in his mind with his
					own murderous quarrel. But that was long ago, and neither an audience nor a
					novel-reader is critical about incidents which occur long before the point at
					which the story begins. See chapter <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1460a">Aristot.
						Poet. 24.20</bibl>.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Since tragedy is a representation of men
				better than ourselves we must copy the good portrait-painters who, while rendering
				the distinctive form and making a likeness, yet paint people better than they are.
				It is the same with the poet. When representing people who are hot-tempered or lazy,
				or have other such traits of character, he should make them such, yet men of worth
				&lsqb;an example of hardness&rsqb;<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Apparently a note on Achilles which has been copied by mistake into the
					text.</note>; take the way in which Agathon and Homer portray
					Achilles.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="15.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Keep, then, a careful eye on these rules and also on the
				appeal to the eye<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., stage-craft rather than
					staging.</note> which is necessarily bound up with the poet's business; for that
				offers many opportunities of going wrong. But this subject has been adequately
				discussed in the published treatises.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">As distinct
					from the body of "esoteric" doctrine circulated by oral teaching among
					Aristotle's pupils.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="16.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> What a "Discovery" is has been already stated.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In chapter 11.</note><milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>As for kinds of Discovery, first comes the least artistic kind,
				which is largely used owing to incompetence&mdash;discovery by tokens.
					<milestone n="16.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These may be congenital, like "the
				spear the Earth-born bear" or stars, like those which Carcinus<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A prolific tragedian of the early fourth century. The family are
					agreeably ridiculed in Aristophanes' <title>Wasps</title>.</note> uses in his
					<title>Thyestes</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">These were
					"birth-marks." The "spear-head" distinguished the descendants of the Spartoi at
						<placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>; the star or bright spot
					on the descendants of Pelops commemorated his ivory shoulder, and in Carcinus's
					play it seems to have survived cooking.</note>; <milestone n="16.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> or they may be acquired and these may be on the body, for
				instance, wounds, or external things like necklaces, and in the
					<title>Tyro</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A play by Sophocles. Tyro's
					twins by Poseidon, who appeared to her in the guise of the river Enipeus, were
					exposed in a little boat or ark, like Moses in the bulrushes, and this led to
					their identification.</note> the discovery by means of the boat. <milestone n="16.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There is a better and a worse way of using
				these tokens; for instance Odysseus, by means of his wound, was discovered in one
				way by the nurse and in another way by the swine-herds.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 19.386">Hom. Od. 19.386ff., 205ff.</bibl> The
					first came about automatically, the second was a deliberate demonstration "to
					prove the point." Aristotle here distinguishes between a discovery inevitably
					produced by the logic of events (e.g. it was inevitable or at least probable
					that Odysseus, arriving as a strange traveller, should be washed by Eurycleia,
					and that she should thus see the old scar on his thigh and discover his
					identity) and a discovery produced by a deliberate declaration (e.g. Odysseus's
					declaration of his identity to Eumaeus). The latter kind is "manufactured by the
					poet," not logically caused by what has gone before.</note>
				<milestone n="16.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Discovery scenes constructed to prove
				the point are inartistic and so are all such scenes, but those are better which
				arise out of a reversal scene, as, for instance, in "The Washing."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 19.392">Hom. Od. 19.392.</bibl> See
					preceding note.</note>
				<milestone n="16.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In the second place come those which
				are manufactured by the poet and are therefore inartistic. For instance, in the
					<title>Iphigeneia</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Euripides'
						<title>Iphigeneia in
					Tauris</title>. See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1452b">Aristot. Poet.
						11.8</bibl>, note.</note> Orestes revealed himself. She was revealed to him
				through the letter, <milestone n="16.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> but Orestes says
				himself what the poet wants and not what the plot requires. So this comes near to
				the fault already mentioned, for he might just as well have actually brought some
					tokens.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">To prove his identity Orestes mentions
					Pelops' lance and other "things from home," which is much the same as producing
					visible tokens.</note> And there is "the voice of the shuttle"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">When Philomela's tongue was cut out, she wove in
					embroidery the story of her rape by Tereus. Thus the facts were discovered to
					her sister, Procne, by deliberate demonstration.</note> In Sophocles'
					<title>Tereus</title>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="16.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The third kind is due to memory, to showing distress on
				seeing something. <milestone n="1455a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>An example of this is the scene in the <title>Cyprians</title> by
				Dicaeogenes; on seeing the picture he burst into tears<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Teucer, returning to <placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName> in disguise and seeing a portrait of his dead father
					Telamon, burst into tears and was thus discovered. So, too, in <title>The Two
						Gentlemen of <placeName key="perseus,Verona">Verona</placeName></title>
					Julia is discovered because she swoons on hearing Valentine offer Sylvia to his
					rival.</note>: and again in the "Tale of Alcinous,"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">
					<bibl n="Hom. Od. 8.521">Hom. Od. 8.521ff.</bibl>
				</note> hearing the minstrel he remembered and burst into tears; and thus they were
				recognized. <milestone n="16.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The fourth kind results
				from an inference; for instance, in the <title>Choephoroe</title> "Someone like me
				has come; but nobody is like me except Orestes; therefore he has come." And there is
					Polyidus's<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A Sophist who either wrote an
						<title>Iphigeneia</title> with this denouement or more probably suggested in
					a work of criticism (cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1455b">Aristot. Poet.
						17.6</bibl>) that Orestes on being led to his fate should speculate aloud
					upon the odd coincidence that both he and his sister should be sacrificed, thus
					revealing his identity to Iphigeneia. Like most critics, Polyidos would have
					been a poor dramatist. There is an example of this form of discovery in the
					French opera <title>Coeur de Lion</title>, where the old knight says "goddam"
					and is thus discovered to be an Englishman.</note> idea about Iphigeneia, for it
				is likely enough that Orestes should make an inference that, whereas his sister was
				sacrificed, here is the same thing happening to him. And in Theodectes'
					<title>Tydeus</title> that "having come to find a son, he is perishing himself."
				And the scene in the <title>Phineidae</title>, where on seeing the spot the women
				inferred their fate, that they were meant to die there for it was there that they
				had been exposed.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In these cases the inference was
					presumably uttered aloud and hence the identity of the speakers discovered.
					Nothing else is known of these plays.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="16.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There is also a kind of
				fictitious discovery which depends on a false inference on the part of the audience,
				for instance in <title>Odysseus the False Messenger</title>, he said he would
				recognize the bow, which as a matter of fact he had not seen, but to assume that he
				really would reveal himself by this means is a false inference.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The text is obscure, and our ignorance of the play or rhapsody adds
					to the darkness, but the reference may be to the ruse, common in detective
					stories, of misleading the audience by false clues in order to make the final
					revelation more effective.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="16.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Best of all is the discovery which is
				brought about directly by the incidents, the surprise being produced by means of
				what is likely&mdash;take the scene in Sophocles' <title>Oedipus</title> or in
				the <title>Iphigeneia</title>&mdash;for it is likely enough that she should want
				to send a letter. These are the only discovery scenes which dispense with artificial
				tokens, like necklaces.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The classical example of
					these tokens in English drama is "the strawberry mark on the left arm" in
						<title>Box and Cox</title>. But Aristotle seems here to use "tokens" in a
					wider sense than at the beginning of the chapter and to include not only
					birthmarks, necklaces, etc., but any statement or action which may be used as a
					sign in the scene of Discovery.</note><milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="16.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In the second place come those
				that are the result of inference.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="17.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In constructing plots and completing the effect by the
				help of dialogue the poet should, as far as possible, keep the scene before his
				eyes. Only thus by getting the picture as clear as if he were present at the actual
				event, will he find what is fitting and detect contradictions. <milestone n="17.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The censure upon Carcinos is evidence of this.
				Amphiaraos was was made to rise from a temple. The poet did not visualize the scene
				and therefore this escaped his notice, but on the stage it was a failure since the
				audience objected.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The example is obscure. Clearly
					Carcinus introduced an absurdity which escaped notice until the play was staged.
					Margoliouth suggests that if Amphiaraus were a god he should come down, and if a
					mere hero, he sould not have a temple. In <title>The Master of
					Ballantrae</title> Mrs. Henry cleans a
					sword by thrusting it up to the hilt in the ground&mdash;which is iron-bound
					by frost. The would be noticed on the stage: a reader may miss the
					incongruity.</note>
				<milestone n="17.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The poet should also, as far as
				possible, complete the effect by using the gestures. For, if their natural powers
				are equal, those who are actually in the emotions are the most convincing; he who is
				agitated blusters and the angry man rages with the maximum of conviction.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Sir Joshua Reynolds used thus to simulate emotion
					before a mirror. In his Preface to the <title>Lyrical Ballads</title> Wordsworth
					says that the Poet will wish "to bring his feelings near to those of the persons
					whose feelings he describes . . . and even confound and identify his own
					feelings with theirs." See also Burke, <title>On the Sublime and
						Beautiful</title>,4. 4. </note>
				<milestone n="17.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And that is why poetry needs either a
				sympathetic nature or a madman,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">"Genius to madness
					near allied" is the meaning of <foreign lang="greek">MANIKO/S</foreign> as used
					here. Plato held that the only excuse for a poet was that he couldn't help
					it.</note> the former being impressionable and the latter inspired.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="17.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The stories,
				whether they are traditional or whether you make them up yourself, <milestone n="1455b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>should first
				be sketched in outline and then expanded by putting in episodes. <milestone n="17.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> I mean that one might look at the general outline, say
				of the <title>Iphigeneia</title>, like this: A certain maiden has been sacrificed,
				and has disappeared beyond the ken of those who sacrificed her and has been
				established in another country, where it is a custom to sacrifice strangers to the
				goddess; and this priesthood she holds. Some time afterwards it happens that the
				brother of the priestess arrives there&mdash;the fact that the god told him to
				go there, and why, and the object of his journey, lie outside the outline-plot. He
				arrives, is seized, and is on the point of being sacrificed, when he reveals his
				identity either by Euripides' method or according to Polyidos, by making the very
				natural remark that after all it is not only his sister who was born to be
				sacrificed but himself too; and thus he is saved. <milestone n="17.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Not until this has been done should you put in names and
				insert the episodes; <milestone n="17.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and you must mind
				that the episodes are appropriate, as, for instance, in the case of Orestes the
				madness that led to his capture and his escape by means of the purification.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In the <title>Iphigeneia in
					Tauris</title> Orestes is captured because
					he is suffering from a fit of mania; and at the end Iphigeneia pretends that the
					image of Artemis has been infected by the blood-guiltiness of the Greek
					strangers, and that, before they can be sacrificed, she must cleanse both image
					and strangers secretly in the sea. Thus they all escape together by
					boat.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="17.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now in drama the episodes are short, but it is by them that
				the epic gains its length. <milestone n="17.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The story
				of the Odyssey is quite short. A man is for many years away from home and his
				footsteps are dogged by Poseidon and he is all alone. Moreover,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>affairs at home are in such a state that his estate is
				being wasted by suitors and a plot laid against his son, but after being
				storm-tossed he arrives himself, reveals who he is, and attacks them, with the
				result that he is saved and destroys his enemies. <milestone n="17.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> That is the essence, the rest is episodes.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="18.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In every tragedy
				there is a complication and a denouement.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The Greek
					says simply "tying" and "loosing." Complication and denouement seem clumsy
					equivalents, yet they are the words we use in dramatic criticism.</note> The
				incidents outside the plot and some of those in it usually form the complication,
				the rest is the denouement. <milestone n="18.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> I mean
				this, that the complication is the part from the beginning up to the point which
				immediately precedes the occurrence of a change from bad to good fortune or from
				good fortune to bad; the denouement is from the beginning of the change down to the
				end. <milestone n="18.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For instance, in the
					<title>Lynceus</title> of Theodectes the complication is the preceding events,
				and the seizure of the boy, and then their own seizure; and the denouement is from
				the capital charge to the end.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The boy must be Abas,
					and "they" are presumably Danaus and perhaps his other daughters. Aristotle
					seems to regard the arrest of Danaus not as part of the <foreign lang="greek">LU/SIS</foreign>, but as the end of the <foreign lang="greek">DE/SIS</foreign>.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="18.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Tragedies should properly be classed as the same or
				different mainly in virtue of the plot, that is to say those that have the same
				entanglement and denouement. Many who entangle well are bad at the denouement. Both
				should always be mastered.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>There are four varieties of
				tragedy&mdash;the same as the number given for the "elements"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Apparently the reference here is to the four elements
					into which in the course of chapters 10-15. Plot has been analysed, "Reversal,"
					"Discovery," "Calamity," and "Character." But the symmetry is spoilt by the fact
					that his first species, "the complex play," corresponds to the first two of
					these four elements, viz. to "Reversal" and "Discovery." Thus his fourth species
					is left in the air and he hurriedly introduces "Spectacle" as the fourth
					corresponding element. Other explanations seem even sillier than
					this.</note>&mdash;<milestone n="18.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> first the
				complex kind, which all turns on reversal and discovery; <milestone n="18.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> the "calamity play" like the stories of Ajax and Ixion;
					<milestone n="18.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> the "character play" like the
					<title>Phthian Women</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">By
					Sophocles.</note> and the <title>Peleus</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Both Sophocles and Euripides wrote a <title>Peleus</title>.</note>. <milestone n="1456a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="18.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The fourth element is spectacle, like the
					<title>Phorcides</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The text is obscure,
					and our ignorance of the play or rhapsody adds to the darkness, but the
					reference may be to the ruse, common in detective stories, of misleading the
					audience by false clues in order to make the final revelation more
					effective.</note> and <title>Prometheus</title>, and all scenes laid in Hades.
					<milestone n="18.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> One should ideally try to include
				all these elements or, failing that, the most important and as many as possible,
				especially since it is the modern fashion to carp at poets, and, because there have
				been good poets in each style, to demand that a single author should surpass the
				peculiar merits of each.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="18.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> One must remember, as we have often said, not to make a
				tragedy an epic structure: <milestone n="18.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> by epic I
				mean made up of many stories&mdash;suppose, for instance, one were to dramatize
				the <title>IIiad</title> as a whole. <milestone n="18.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				The length of the <title>IIiad</title> allows to the parts their proper size, but in
				plays the result is full of disappointment. <milestone n="18.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And the proof is that all who have dramatized the Sack of
					<placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> as a whole, and not, like
				Euripides, piecemeal, or the Niobe story as a whole and not like Aeschylus, either
				fail or fare badly in competition. Indeed even Agathon failed in this point alone.
					<milestone n="18.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In "reversals," however, and in
				"simple" stories<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., those that have no
					"Discovery" or "Reversal." See chapter 10.</note> too,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>they admirably achieve their end, which is a tragic
				effect that also satisfies your feelings. <milestone n="18.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> This is achieved when the wise man, who is, however,
				unscrupulous, is deceived&mdash;like Sisyphus&mdash;and the man who is brave
				but wicked is worsted. <milestone n="18.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And this, as
				Agathon says, is a likely result, since it is likely that many quite unlikely things
				should happen.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="18.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The chorus too must be regarded as one of the actors. It must
				be part of the whole and share in the action, not as in Euripides but as in
				Sophocles. <milestone n="18.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In the others the choral
				odes have no more to do with the plot than with any other tragedy. And so they sing
				interludes, a practice begun by Agathon. And yet to sing interludes is quite as bad
				as transferring a whole speech or scene from one play to another.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="19.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The other factors
				have been already discussed. It remains to speak of "Diction" and "Thought."
					<milestone n="19.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> All that concerns Thought may be
				left to the treatise on Rhetoric, for the subject is more proper to that
					inquiry.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">"Thought"&mdash;no English word
					exactly corresponds with <foreign lang="greek">DIA/NOIA</foreign>&mdash;is
					all that which is expressed or effected by the words (cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1450b">Aristot. Poet. 6.22, 23, and 25</bibl>). Thus the
					student is rightly referred to the <title>Art of Rhetoric</title>, where he
					learns "what to say in every case." Aristotle adds that the rules there given
					for the use of ideas will guide him also in the use of incidents, since the same
					effect may be produced either by talk or by "situation."</note>
				<milestone n="19.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Under the head of Thought come all the
				effects to be produced by the language. <milestone n="19.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Some of these are proof and refutation, <milestone n="1456b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>the arousing of feelings like pity,
				fear, anger, and so on, and then again exaggeration and depreciation.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">It is an important part of the orator's skill to
					depreciate what is important and to exaggerate trivial points.</note>
				<milestone n="19.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is clear that in the case of the
				incidents, too, one should work on the same principles, when effects of pity or
				terror or exaggeration or probability have to be produced. <milestone n="19.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> There is just this difference, that some effects must
				be clear without explanation,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Those produced by
					"situation."</note> whereas others are produced in the speeches by the speaker
				and are due to the speeches. For what would be the use of a speaker, if the required
				effect were likely to be felt without the aid of the speeches?<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="19.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Under the head of
				Diction one subject of inquiry is the various modes of speech, the knowledge of
				which is proper to elocution or to the man who knows the master art<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Rhetoric is a "master art" in relation to elocution,
					since it decides the effects to be produced, and elocution decides how to
					produce them. So the doctor's art is "master" to that of the dispenser, and the
					art of riding to that of the maker of bridles.</note>&mdash;I mean for
				instance, what is a command, a prayer, a statement, a threat, question, answer, and
				so on. <milestone n="19.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The knowledge or ignorance of
				such matters brings upon the poet no censure worth serious consideration. For who
				could suppose that there is any fault in the passage which Protagoras censures,
				because Homer, intending to utter a prayer, gives a command when he says, "Sing,
				goddess, the wrath"? To order something to be done or not is, he points out, a
					command.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="19.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> So we may leave this topic as one that belongs not to poetry
				but to another art.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="20.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Diction as a
					whole<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A translator is bound to render this
					chapter, since the balance of evidence is in favour of its inclusion. But the
					readaer is advised to skip it, since it is written from the point of view of
					grammar and philology, and does not, like the succeeding chapter, deal with the
					literary use of words. It is also very obscure. Students should refer to
					Bywater's edition.</note> is made up of these parts: letter, syllable,
				conjunction, joint,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A "joint," as defined below,
					appears to be a word which indicates the beginning or end of a clause.</note>
				noun, verb, case, phrase. <milestone n="20.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A letter is
				an indivisible sound, not every such sound but one of which an intelligible sound
				can be formed. Animals utter indivisible sounds but none that I should call a
				letter. <milestone n="20.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Such sounds may be subdivided
				into vowel, semi-vowel, and mute. A vowel is that which without any addition has an
				audible sound; a semivowel needs the addition of another letter to give it audible
				sound, for instance S and R; a mute is that which with addition has no sound of its
				own but becomes audible when combined with some of the letters which have a sound.
				Examples of mutes are G and D. <milestone n="20.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Letters
				differ according to the shape of the mouth and the place at which they are sounded;
				in being with or without aspiration; in being long and short; and lastly in having
				an acute, grave, or intermediate accent. But the detailed study of these matters
				properly concerns students of metre.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A syllable is a sound without meaning,
				composed of a mute and a letter that has a sound. GR, for example, without A is a
				syllable just as much as GRA with an A. But these distinctions also belong to the
				theory of metre. words. It is also very obscure. Students should refer to Bywater's
					edition.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A conjunction is a sound without meaning, <milestone n="1457a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>which
				neither hinders nor causes the formation of a single significant sound or phrase out
				of several sounds, and which, if the phrase stands by itself, cannot properly stand
				at the beginning of it, e.g. <foreign lang="greek">ME/N, DH/, TOI/, DE/</foreign>;
				or else it is a sound without meaning capable of forming one significant sound or
				phrase out of several sounds having each a meaning of their own, e.g. <foreign lang="greek">A)MFI/, PERI/</foreign>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A joint is a sound without meaning which
				marks the beginning or end of a phrase or a division in it, and naturally stands at
				either end or in the middle.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This paragraph remains
					a cause of despair. Bywater's notes suggest a restoration.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A noun is a
				composite sound with a meaning, not indicative of time, no part of which has a
				meaning by itself; for in compounds we do not use each part as having a meaning of
				its own, for instance, in "Theodorus," there is no meaning of <foreign lang="greek">DW=RON</foreign> &lpar;gift&rpar;.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A verb is a composite sound with
				a meaning, indicative of time, no part of which has a meaning by
				itself&mdash;just as in nouns. "Man" or "white" does not signify time, but
				"walks" and "has walked" connote present and past time respectively.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A
				case&lpar;or inflection&rpar;of a noun or verb is that which signifies
				either "of" or "to" a thing and the like;<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>or gives the sense of "one or many" e.g. men and man; or else it may depend on the
				delivery, for example question and command. "Walked?" and "Walk!" are verbal "cases"
				of this kind.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="20.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A phrase<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">There is no exact
					English equivalent of this meaning of <foreign lang="greek">LO/GOS</foreign>,
					which has been used already in 7 above without explanation. "Statement" and
					"proposition" also cover part of its meaning.</note> is a composite sound with a
				meaning, some parts of which mean something by themselves. <milestone n="20.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is not true to say that every "phrase" is made up
				of nouns and verbs, e.g. the definition of man<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Probably one of the two definitions given in the <title>Topics</title>, "a
					two-footed land animal" and "an animal amenable to reason."</note>; but although
				it is possible to have a "phrase" without verbs, yet some part of it will always
				have a meaning of its own, for example, Cleon in "Cleon walks." <milestone n="20.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A "phrase" may be a unit in two ways; either it
				signifies one thing or it is a combination of several "phrases." The unity of the
					<title>Iliad</title>, for instance, is due to such combination, but the
				definition of man is "one phrase" because it signifies one thing.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Nouns are of two
				kinds. There is the simple noun, by which I mean one made up of parts that have no
				meaning, like <foreign lang="greek">GH=</foreign>, and there is the compound noun.
					<milestone n="21.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These may be made up either of a
				part which has no meaning and a part which has a meaning&mdash;though it does
				not have its meaning in the compound&mdash;or of two parts both having a
				meaning. <milestone n="21.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A compound noun may be triple
				and quadruple and multiple, e.g. many of the bombastic names like
					Hermocaicoxanthus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A compound of the names of
					three rivers, Hermus, <placeName key="tgn,1121615">Caicus</placeName>, and
						<placeName key="perseus,Xanthos">Xanthus</placeName>.</note>
				<milestone n="1457b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/> . .
				. <milestone n="21.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Every noun is either "ordinary"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., one which has dined normal currency as
					contrasted with the "rare word," which is confined to a dialect or borrowed from
					a foreign language.</note> or "rare" or "metaphorical" or "ornamental" or
				"invented" or "lengthened" or "curtailed" or "altered." <milestone n="21.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An "ordinary" word is one used by everybody, a "rare" word
				one used by some; <milestone n="21.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> so that a word may
				obviously be both "ordinary" and "rare," but not in relation to the same people.
					<foreign lang="greek">SI/GUNON</foreign>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Meaning, "spear."</note> for instance, is to the Cypriots an "ordinary" word
				but to us a "rare" one.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Metaphor is the application of a strange term either
				transferred from the genus and applied to the species or from the species and
				applied to the genus, or from one species to another or else by analogy. <milestone n="21.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An example of a term transferred from genus
				to species is "Here stands my ship." Riding at anchor is a species of standing.
					<milestone n="21.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An example of transference from
				species to genus is "Indeed ten thousand noble things Odysseus did," for ten
				thousand, which is a species of many, is here used instead of the word "many."
					<milestone n="21.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An example of transference from
				one species to another is "Drawing off his life with the bronze" and "Severing with
				the tireless bronze," where "drawing off" is used for "severing" and "severing" for
				"drawing off," both being species of "removing."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Probably "the bronze" is in the first case a knife and in the second a
					cupping-bowl. This would make the metaphor intelligible.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Metaphor by analogy
				means this: when B is to A as D is to C, then instead of B the poet will say D and B
				instead of D. <milestone n="21.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And sometimes they add
				that to which the term supplanted by the metaphor is relative.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This may claim to be one of Aristotle's least lucid sentences. It
					means this: If Old Age: Life:: Evening: Day, then we may call old age " the
					Evening of Life." In that case "old age" is the "term supplanted by the
					metaphor," and it is relative to " Life"; therefore "Life" &lpar;i.e., "that
					to which the term supplanted by the metaphor is relative"&rpar;is added to
					the metaphorical &lpar;or "transferred"&rpar; term
					"Evening."</note><milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>For instance, a cup
				is to Dionysus what a shield is to Ares; <milestone n="21.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> so he will call the cup "Dionysus's shield" and the shield
				"Ares' cup." Or old age is to life as evening is to day; so he will call the evening
				"day's old-age" or use Empedocles' phrase<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Unknown to
					us.</note>; and old age he will call "the evening of life" or "life's setting
				sun." <milestone n="21.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Sometimes there is no word for
				some of the terms of the analogy but the metaphor can be used all the same. For
				instance, to scatter seed is to sow, but there is no word for the action of the sun
				in scattering its fire. Yet this has to the sunshine the same relation as sowing has
				to the seed, and so you have the phrase "sowing the god-created fire."<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Besides this
				another way of employing metaphor is to call a thing by the strange name and then to
				deny it some attribute of that name. For instance, suppose you call the shield not
				"Ares' cup" but a &ldquo;wineless cup.&rdquo; . . .<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Or you might call Love "Venus's bloodless War." At this point a few
					lines on "Ornament" have evidently been lost, since this is its place in the
					catalogue of nouns above. By "ornament" he seems to mean an embellishing epithet
					or synonym. In the <title>Rhetoric</title> he quotes "Our lady the fig-tree" as
					a misplaced "ornament." One might add the seventeenth-century use of "<placeName key="tgn,7011913">Thames</placeName>" for "water."</note> . . .<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An invented
				word is one not used at all by any people and coined by the poet. There seem to be
				such words, eg. "sprouters" for horns and "pray-er" for priest.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A word is
				"lengthened" or "curtailed," <milestone n="1458a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>the former when use is made of a longer vowel than
				usual or a syllable inserted, and the latter when part of the word is curtailed.
					<milestone n="21.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An example of a lengthened word
				is <foreign lang="greek">PO/LHOS</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">POLE/WS</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">*PHLHIA/DEW</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">*PHLEI/DOU</foreign>; and of a curtailed word <foreign lang="greek">KRI=</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">DW=</foreign>, and e.g. <foreign lang="greek">MI/A GI/NETAI A)MFOTE/RWN O)/Y</foreign>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><foreign lang="greek">KRI=</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">KRIQH/</foreign>, "barley"; <foreign lang="greek">DW=</foreign> for
						<foreign lang="greek">DW=MA</foreign> "house"; <foreign lang="greek">O)/Y</foreign> for <foreign lang="greek">O)/YIS</foreign> "face, eye, or
					appearance."</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A word is "altered" when the poet coins part of the word and
				leaves the rest unchanged, e.g. <foreign lang="greek">DECITERO\N KATA\
					MAZO/N</foreign> instead of <foreign lang="greek">DECIO/N</foreign>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="21.21" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of the nouns
				themselves, some are masculine, some feminine, and some neuter.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This paragraph the reader should either skip or study with Bywater's
					notes. Without them these generalizations on gender seem merely wrong.</note>
				<milestone n="21.22" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Masculine are all that end in N and P
				and <foreign lang="greek">*S</foreign> and in the two compounds of <foreign lang="greek">*S, *Y</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">*C</foreign>. <milestone n="21.23" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Feminine are all that end in those of the
				vowels that are always long, for instance <foreign lang="greek">*H</foreign> and
					<foreign lang="greek">*W</foreign>, and in <foreign lang="greek">*A</foreign>
				among vowels that can be lengthened. <milestone n="21.24" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				The result is that the number of masculine and feminine terminations is the same,
				for <foreign lang="greek">*Y</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">*C</foreign> are
				the same as <foreign lang="greek">*S</foreign>. <milestone n="21.25" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> No noun ends in a mute or in a short vowel. <milestone n="21.26" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Only three end in <foreign lang="greek">*I,
					ME/LI, KO/MMI</foreign>, and <foreign lang="greek">PE/PERI</foreign>. Five end
				in <foreign lang="greek">*U</foreign>. The neuters end in these letters and in
					<foreign lang="greek">*N</foreign> and <foreign lang="greek">*S</foreign>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The merit of diction is to be clear and not commonplace. The
				clearest diction is that made up of ordinary words, but it is commonplace.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="22.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> An
				example is the poetry of Cleophon and of Sthenelus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A tragedian whom Aristophanes ridicules for the insipidity of his
					diction.</note>
				<milestone n="22.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> That which employs unfamiliar words is
				dignified and outside the common usage. By "unfamiliar" I mean a rare word, a
				metaphor, a lengthening,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See preceding chapter
					19.</note> and anything beyond the ordinary use. <milestone n="22.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But if a poet writes entirely in such words, the result will
				be either a riddle or jargon; if made up of metaphors, a riddle and if of rare
				words, jargon. <milestone n="22.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The essence of a riddle
				consists in describing a fact by an impossible combination of words. By merely
				combining the ordinary names of things this cannot be done, but it is made possible
				by combining metaphors. For instance, "I saw a man weld bronze upon a man with
				fire," and so on.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The answer is a cupping-bowl. This
					was a bronze vessel which was applied to the body at the place at which a small
					incision had been made. Heated lint was placed in the bowl of it and the
					reduction of air-pressure thus caused a strong flow of blood. For this form of
					riddle cf. "Out of the strong came forth sweetness."</note>
				<milestone n="22.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> A medley of rare words is jargon.
					<milestone n="22.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We need then a sort of mixture of
				the two. For the one kind will save the diction from being prosaic and commonplace,
				the rare word, for example, and the metaphor and the "ornament," whereas the
				ordinary words give clarity. <milestone n="1458b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="22.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A considerable aid to clarity and distinction are the
				lengthening and abbreviation and alteration of words. Being otherwise than in the
				ordinary form and thus unusual, these will produce the effect of distinction, and
				clarity will be preserved by retaining part of the usual form. <milestone n="22.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Those critics are therefore wrong who censure this
				manner of idiom and poke fun at the poet, as did the elder Eucleides<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A critic of this name wrote on the drama, but his
					date is uncertain.</note> who said it was easy to write poetry, granted the
				right to lengthen syllables at will. He had made a burlesque in this very style:
					<foreign lang="greek">*)EPIXA/RHN EI)=DON *MARAQW=NA/DE BADI/ZONTA</foreign> and
					<foreign lang="greek">OU)K A)/N G' E)RA/MENOS TO\N E)KEI/NOU
					E)LLE/BORON</foreign>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In Homer we find short
					vowels lengthened "by position," but, whereas Homer uses the licence sparingly,
					Eucleides raised a laugh by overdoing it and writing in parody such hexameters
					as those here quoted. A modern parallel may illustrate this. The poet Stephen
					Phillips employed to excess the licence whihc allows a clash between the natural
					accent and the metrical ictus, and Mr. Owen Seaman, "for the express purpose of
					raising a laugh," parodied the trick by carrying it to further excess and wrote
					in blank verse, "She a milliner was and her brothers
					Dynamiters."</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now to make an obtrusive use of this licence is ridiculous;
					<milestone n="22.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> but moderation is a requisite
				common to all kinds of writing. The same effect could be got by using metaphors and
				rare words and the rest unsuitably for the express purpose of raising a
					laugh.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> What a difference is made by the proper use of such licence
				may be seen in epic poetry, if you substitute in the verse the ordinary forms.
					<milestone n="22.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Take a rare word or metaphor or
				any of the others and substitute the ordinary word; the truth of our contention will
				then be obvious.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>For instance, Aeschylus
				and Euripides wrote the same iambic line with the change of one word only, a rare
				word in place of one made ordinary by custom, yet the one line seems beautiful and
				the other trivial. Aeschylus in the <title>Philoctetes</title> wrote, "The ulcer
				eats the flesh of this my foot," and Euripides instead of "eats" put "feasts upon."
				Or take "I that am small, of no account nor goodly;" suppose one were to read the
				line substituting the ordinary words, "I that am little and weak and ugly." Or
				compare "He set a stool unseemly and a table small." with "He set a shabby stool and
				a little table," or "the sea-shore is roaring" with "the sea-shore is
					shrieking."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Similarly we might use "ordinary"
					words instead of those which Keats chose so carefully and speak of "wonderful
					windows abutting on to a dangerous sea-shore in a dreary, mysterious
					country."</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Ariphrades<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Unknown.</note>
				again made fun of the tragedians because they employ phrases which no one would use
				in conversation, like " <foreign lang="greek">DWMA/TWN A)/PO</foreign>" instead of
					<foreign lang="greek">A)PO\ DWMA/TWN</foreign> and their " <foreign lang="greek">SE/QEN</foreign>"and " <foreign lang="greek">E)GW\ DE/ NIN</foreign>"and "
					<foreign lang="greek">*)AXILLE/WS PE/RI</foreign>" for <foreign lang="greek">PERI\ *)AXILLE/WS</foreign>, and so on. <milestone n="1459a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="22.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> All that sort of thing, not being in the ordinary form, gives
				distinction to the diction, which was what he failed to understand.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is a great thing
				to make a proper use of each of the elements mentioned, and of double words and rare
				words too, but by far the greatest thing is the use of metaphor. <milestone n="22.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> That alone cannot be learnt; it is the token
				of genius. For the right use of metaphor means an eye for resemblances.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., the power of detecting "identity in difference"
					which distinguishes also both the philosopher and the
					scientist.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Of the various kinds of words the double forms are most
				suited for dithyrambs, rare words for heroic verse and metaphors for iambics.
					<milestone n="22.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And indeed in heroic verse they
				are all useful; but since iambic verse is largely an imitation of speech, only those
				nouns are suitable which might be used in talking. These are the ordinary word,
				metaphor, and "ornament."<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="22.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now concerning tragedy and the art of representing life in
				action, what we have said already must suffice.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="23.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> We come now to the art of
				representation which is narrative and in metre.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., epic.</note> Clearly the story must be constructed as in tragedy,
				dramatically, round a single piece of action, whole and complete in
					itself,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>with a beginning, middle and
				end, so that like a single living organism it may produce its own peculiar form of
				pleasure. <milestone n="23.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It must not be such as we
				normally find in history, where what is required is an exposition not of a single
				piece of action but of a single period of time, showing all that within the period
				befell one or more persons, events that have a merely casual relation to each other.
					<milestone n="23.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For just as the battle of
					<placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName> occurred at the same time as
				the Carthaginian battle in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, but they
				do not converge to the same result<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Gelo's defeat of
					the Carthaginians in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> in <date value="-480">480</date> B.C. took place, according to Herodotus, on the same
					day as the battle of <placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName>.</note>;
				so, too, in any sequence of time one event may follow another and yet they may not
				issue in any one result. <milestone n="23.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Yet most of
				the poets do this. <milestone n="23.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> So in this respect,
				too, compared with all other poets Homer may seem, as we have already said, divinely
				inspired, in that even with the Trojan war, which has a beginning and an end, he did
				not endeavor to dramatize it as a whole, since it would have been either too long to
				be taken in all at once or, if he had moderated the length, he would have
				complicated it by the variety of incident. As it is, he takes one part of the story
				only and uses many incidents from other parts, such as the Catalogue of Ships and
				other incidents with which he diversifies his poetry. <milestone n="23.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The others, on the contrary, all write about a single hero or
				about a single period or about a single action with a great many parts, the authors,
					<milestone n="1459b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>for example, of the <title>Cypria</title> and the <title>Little
					Iliad</title>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">As we have seen already in chapter 8, a poem or a play must be one story and
					not several stories about one hero. Thus, since the <title>Iliad</title> and
						<title>Odyssey</title> have this essential unity (i.e., one thread runs
					through the narrative of each), few plays can be made out of them but many out
					of the <title>Cypria</title> or the <title>Little Iliad</title>, which are
					merely collections of lays on similar themes.</note>
				<milestone n="23.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The result is that out of an
					<title>Iliad</title> or an <title>Odyssey</title> only one tragedy can be made,
				or two at most, whereas several have been made out of the <title>Cypria</title>, and
				out of the <title>Little Iliad</title> more than eight, e.g. <title>The Award of
					Arms</title>, <title>Philoctetes</title>, <title>Neoptolemus</title>,
					<title>Eurypylus</title>, <title>The Begging</title>, <title>The Laconian
					Women</title>, <title>The Sack of <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName></title>, and <title>Sailing of the Fleet</title>, and
					<title>Sinon</title>, too, and <title>The Trojan Women.</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The next point is
				that there must be the same varieties of epic as of tragedy<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1455b">Aristot. Poet.
					18.4</bibl>.</note>: an epic must be "simple or complex,"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See chapter 10.</note> or else turn on "character" or on "calamity."
					<milestone n="24.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The constituent parts, too, are
				the same with the exception of song and spectacle. Epic needs reversals and
				discoveries and calamities, and the thought and diction too must be good. <milestone n="24.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> All these were used by Homer for the first
				time, and used well. Of his poems he made the one, the <title>
					Iliad
				</title>, a "simple" story turning on "calamity," and the <title>Odyssey</title> a
				"complex" story&mdash;it is full of "discoveries"&mdash;turning on
				character. Besides this they surpass all other poems in diction and
					thought.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Epic differs from tragedy in the length of the composition
				and in metre. <milestone n="24.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The limit of length
				already given<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1451a">Aristot. Poet. 7.12</bibl>.</note> will suffice&mdash;it must be
				possible to embrace the beginning and the end in one view,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>which would be the case if the compositions were
				shorter than the ancient epics but reached to the length of the tragedies presented
				at a single entertainment.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A Satyr play by
					Aeschylus. The Phorcides were sisters of the Dragon who kept the garden of the
					Hesperides, and they lived &ldquo;under <placeName key="tgn,6005315">Scythia</placeName>.&rdquo; The <title>Prometheus</title> is not the
						<title>Prometheus Bound</title> but another Satyr play, probably by
					Aeschylus.</note>
				<milestone n="24.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Epic has a special advantage which
				enables the length to be increased, because in tragedy it is not possible to
				represent several parts of the story as going on simultaneously, but only to show
				what is on the stage, that part of the story which the actors are performing;
				whereas, in the epic, because it is narrative, several parts can be portrayed as
				being enacted at the same time. <milestone n="24.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If
				these incidents are relevant, they increase the bulk of the poem, and this increase
				gives the epic a great advantage in richness as well as the variety due to the
				diverse incidents; for it is monotony which, soon satiating the audience, makes
				tragedies fail.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Experience has shown that the heroic hexameter is the right
				metre. Were anyone to write a narrative poem in any other metre or in several
				metres, the effect would be wrong. <milestone n="24.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The
				hexameter is the most sedate and stately of all metres and therefore admits of rare
				words and metaphors more than others, and narrative poetry is itself elaborate above
				all others. <milestone n="24.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The iambic and the
				trochaic tetrameter are lively, the latter suits dancing and the former suits real
				life. <milestone n="1460a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="24.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Still more unsuitable is it to
				use several metres as Chaeremon did. <milestone n="24.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				So no one has composed a long poem in any metre other than the heroic hexameter. As
				we said above, Nature shows that this is the right metre to choose.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Homer deserves
				praise for many things and especially for this, that alone of all poets he does not
				fail to understand what he ought to do himself. The poet should speak as seldom as
				possible in his own character, since he is not "representing" the story in that
					sense.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This takes us back to the beginning of
					chapter 3, where the various "manners" of representation are distinguished.
					Homer represents life partly by narration, partly by assuming a character other
					than his own. Both these "manners" come under the head of "Imitation." When
					Aristotle says "the poet speaks himself" and "plays a part himself" he refers
					not to narrative, of which there is a great deal in Homer, but to the "preludes"
					&lpar;cf. <foreign lang="greek">FROIMIASA/MENOS</foreign> below&rpar; in
					which the poet, invoking the Muse, speaks in his own person.
						Ridgeway points out that in the whole of the <title>
						Iliad
					</title> and <title>Odyssey</title> Homer thus "speaks himself" only 24
					lines.</note>
				<milestone n="24.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now the other poets play a part
				themselves throughout the poem and only occasionally "represent" a few things
				dramatically, but Homer after a brief prelude at once brings in a man or a woman or
				some other character, never without character, but all having character of their
					own.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Now the marvellous should certainly be portrayed in tragedy, but epic affords
				greater scope for the inexplicable&lpar;which is the chief element in what is
				marvellous&rpar;, because we do not actually see the persons of the story.
					<milestone n="24.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The incident of
					Hector's pursuit<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">&ldquo;Entertainment&rdquo; must mean a festival. At the City Dionysia
					three poets competed, each with three tragedies. By the end of the fifth century
					only one Satyr play was performed at each festival. But the tragedies were
					longer than those we possess. It is therefore likely that the nine tragedies
					together with one Satyr play amounted to about 15,000 lines. The <title>
						Iliad
					</title> contains between 16,000 and 17,000 lines.</note> would look ridiculous
				on the stage, the people standing still and not pursuing and Achilles waving them
				back, but in epic that is not noticed. <milestone n="24.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But that the marvellous causes pleasure is shown by the fact that people always
				tell a piece of news with additions by way of being agreeable.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Above all, Homer has
				taught the others the proper way of telling lies,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>that is, by using a fallacy. When B is true if A is true, or B
				happens if A happens, people think that if B is true A must be true or happen. But
				that is false. Consequently if A be untrue but there be something else, B, which is
				necessarily true or happens if A is true, the proper thing to do is to posit B, for,
				knowing B to be true, our mind falsely infers that A is true also. This is an
				example from the Washing.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><title>Odyssey</title> 19.
					Odysseus tells Penelope that he is a Cretan from Gnossus, who once entertained
					O. on his voyage to <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. As evidence,
					he describes O.'s dress and his companions (<bibl n="Hom. Od. 19.164">Hom. Od.
						19.164-260</bibl>). P. commits the fallacy of inferring the truth of the
					antecedent from the truth of the consequent: &ldquo;If his story were true,
					he would know these details; But he does know them; Therefore his story is
					true.&rdquo; The artist in fiction uses the same fallacy, e.g.:
					&ldquo;If chessmen could come to life the white knight would be a duffer;
					But he is a most awful duffer &lpar;look at him!&rpar;; Therefore
					chessmen can come to life.&rdquo; He makes his deductions so convincing that
					we falsely infer the truth of his hypothesis.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> What is convincing
				though impossible should always be preferred to what is possible and unconvincing.
					<milestone n="24.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Stories should not be made up of
				inexplicable details; so far as possible there should be nothing inexplicable, or,
				if there is, it should lie outside the story&mdash;as, for instance, Oedipus not
				knowing how Laius died&mdash;and not in the play; for example, in the
					<title>Electra</title> the news of the Pythian games,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">In Sophocles'<title>Electra</title>the plot hinges on a false story
					of Orestes' death by an accident at the Pythian games. Presumably the
					anachronism shocked Aristotle.</note> or in the Mysians the man who came from
					<placeName key="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName> without speaking.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Telephus.</note> To say that the plot would otherwise have been ruined is
				ridiculous. <milestone n="24.21" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> One should not in the
				first instance construct such a plot, and if a poet does write thus, and there seems
				to be a more reasonable way of treating the incident, then it is positively absurd.
					<milestone n="24.22" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Even in the
					<title>Odyssey</title> the inexplicable elements in the story of his
					landing<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 13.116">Hom. Od.
						13.116ff.</bibl> It seemed to the critics inexplicable that Odysseus should
					not awake when his ship ran aground at the harbour of Phorcys in <placeName key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName> and the Phaeacian sailors carried him
					ashore.</note> would obviously have been intolerable, had they been written by
				an inferior poet. <milestone n="1460b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>As it is, Homer conceals the absurdity by the charm of all his
				other merits.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="24.23" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The diction should be elaborated only in the "idle" parts
				which do not reveal character or thought.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The
					Messengers' speeches, a regular feature o Greek tragedy, may serve to illustrate
					what is here called the "idle part" of a play, i.e., passages which, but for
					brilliant writing, might be dull, since no character is there elucidated and no
					important "sentiments" expressed.</note> Too brilliant diction frustrates its
				own object by diverting attention from the portrayal of character and
					thought.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> With regard to problems,<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">A
					"problem" in this sense is a difficult passage or expression which explanation
					and may easily be censured by an unsympathetic critic. Aristotle here classifies
					the various grounds of censure and the various lines of defence. Most of his
					illustrations are drawn from the critical objections lodged against the
						<title>Iliad</title> by Zoilus and other "hammerers of Homer." As the reader
					will see, many of them are abysmally foolish.</note> and the various solutions
				of them, how many kinds there are, and the nature of each kind, all will be clear if
				we look at them like this. <milestone n="25.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Since the
				poet represents life, as a painter does or any other maker of likenesses, he must
				always represent one of three things&mdash;either things as they were or are; or
				things as they are said and seem to be; or things as they should be. <milestone n="25.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These are expressed in diction with or
				without rare words and metaphors, there being many modifications of diction, all of
				which we allow the poet to use. <milestone n="25.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/>
				Moreover, the standard of what is correct is not the same in the art of poetry as it
				is in the art of social conduct or any other art. <milestone n="25.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In the actual art of poetry there are two kinds of errors,
				essential and accidental. <milestone n="25.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If a man
				meant to represent something and failed through incapacity, that is an essential
				error. But if his error is due to his original conception being wrong and his
				portraying, for example, a horse advancing both its right legs, that is then a
				technical error in some special branch of knowledge,<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>in medicine, say, or whatever it may be; or else some sort of
				impossibility has been portrayed, but that is not an essential error. <milestone n="25.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> These considerations must, then, be kept in
				view in meeting the charges contained in these objections.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let us first take the charges against the art of poetry itself. If
				an impossibility has been portrayed, an error has been made. <milestone n="25.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> But it is justifiable if the poet thus achieves the
				object of poetry&mdash;what that is has been already stated&mdash;and makes
				that part or some other part of the poem more striking. The pursuit of
					Hector is an example of this.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1460a">Aristot. Poet. 24.16</bibl> and
					note.</note>
				<milestone n="25.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If, however, the object could have
				been achieved better or just as well without sacrifice of technical accuracy, then
				it is not justifiable, for, if possible, there should be no error at all in any part
				of the poem. <milestone n="25.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Again one must ask of
				which kind is the error, is it an error in poetic art or a chance error in some
				other field? It is less of an error not to know that a female stag has no horns than
				to make a picture that is unrecognizable.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Next, supposing the charge is "That is not
				true," one can meet it by saying "But perhaps it ought to be," just as Sophocles
				said that he portrayed people as they ought to be and Euripides portrayed them as
				they are. <milestone n="25.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If neither of these will
				do, then say, "Such is the tale"; for instance, tales about gods. <milestone n="25.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Very likely there is no advantage in telling
				them, and they are not true either, but may well be what Xenophanes declared<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., immoral and therefore untrue. He opened the
					assault on Homeric theology at the end of the sixth or the beginning of the
					fifth century B.C.</note>&mdash;all the same such is the tale. <milestone n="1461a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="25.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In another case, perhaps, there is no
				advantage but "such was the fact," e.g. the case of the arms, "Their spears erect on
				butt-spikes stood,"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 10.152">Hom.
						Il. 10.152</bibl>. Problem: "Surely a bad stance: they might so easily fall
					and cause alarm." Solution: "Homer does not defend it. He merely states a fact."
					It is thus that we excuse "unpleasant" fiction.</note> for that was then the
				custom, as it still is in <placeName key="tgn,7016683">Illyria</placeName>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> As to the question whether anything that has been said or
				done is morally good or bad, this must be answered not merely by seeing whether what
				has actually been done or said is noble or base, but by taking into consideration
				also the man who did or said it, and seeing to whom he did or said it, and when and
				for whom and for what reason; for example, to secure a greater good or to avoid a
				greater evil.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Some objections may be met by reference to the diction, for
				example, by pleading "rare word," e.g. <foreign lang="greek">OU)RH=AS ME\N
					PRW=TON</foreign>, for perhaps he means not mules but sentinels.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 1.50">Hom. Il. 1.50</bibl>: "The
					mules and swift-footed hounds he first beset with his arrows." Apollo is sending
					plague upon the Greek army. Problem: "Why should he first attack the mules?"
					Solution: "The word may here mean 'sentiels.'"</note> And Dolon, "One that was
				verily evil of form," it may be not his deformed body but his ugly face, for the
				Cretans use "fair-formed" for "fair-featured."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 10.316">Hom. Il. 10.316</bibl>: "One that was verily evil inform
					but swift in his running." Problem: "If Dolon were deformed, how could he run
					fast?" Solution: "'Form' may here mean 'feature.'"</note> And again "Livelier
				mix it" may mean not undiluted as for drunkards but quicker.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 9.202">Hom. Il. 9.202</bibl>: "Set me, Menoetius'
					son, a larger bowl for the mingling, Livelier mix it withal and make ready for
					each one a beaker." Problem: "'Livelier' suggests intemperance." Solution:
					"Perhaps the word means 'quicker.'" Similar scruples emended the lines in "Young
					Lochinvar" to read: "And now am I come with this pretty maid To dance but one
					measure, drink one lemonade."</note>
				<milestone n="25.17" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Other expressions are metaphorical,
				for example: Then all the other immortals and men lay all night in slumber," while
				yet he says: "Yea, when indeed he gazed at the Trojan plain Agamemnon Marvelled at
				voices of flutes . . ." <milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>"All" is used
				instead of "many" metaphorically, "all" being a species of "many."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.2">Hom. Il. 2.2</bibl> (quoted by
					mistake for <bibl n="Hom. Il. 10.1">Hom. Il. 10.1</bibl>) and <bibl n="Hom. Il. 10.13">Hom. Il. 10.13, 14</bibl>: "Then all the other immortals
					and all the horse-crested heroes Night-long slumbered, but Zeus the sweet sleep
					held not. . . (<bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.1">Hom. Il. 2.1, 2</bibl>) Yea, when indeed
					he gazed at the Trojan plain, Agamemnon Marvelled at voices of flutes and of
					pipes and the din of the soldiers." (<bibl n="Hom. Il. 10.13">Hom. Il. 10.13,
						14</bibl>) Problem: "If all were asleep, who was playing the flute?"
					Solution: "This may be a metaphor; as explained in chapter 21, 'all' is one kind
					or species of 'many,' and thus by transference 'all' is used for 'many,' the
					species for the genus."</note> And again, "Alone unsharing "<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 18.489">Hom. Il. 18.489</bibl>: "She alone of all
					others shares not in the baths of the Ocean." The reference is to the Great
					Bear. Problem: "Why does Homer say 'she alone' when the other Northern
					Constellations also do not set?" Solution: "As in the last instance, the may be
					'metaphorical,' i.e., the genus, 'sole,' may be here used by transference for
					one of its species, 'best known.'"</note> is metaphorical; the best known is
				called the only one.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.18" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> By intonation also; for example, the solutions of Hippias of
					<placeName key="perseus,Thasos City">Thasos</placeName>, his " <foreign lang="greek">DI/DOMEN DE/ OI(</foreign>"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.15">Hom. Il. 2.15</bibl>. Our text is different. Aristotle,
					who quotes the line agains elsewhere, read thus: "No longer the gods in the
					halls of Olympus Strive in their plans, for Hera has bent them all to her
					purpose Thus by her prayers; and we grant him to win the boast of great glory."
					Zeus is instructing the Dream, whom he is sending to lure Agamemnon to disaster.
					Problem: "The last statement is a lie." Solution: "Change the accent and the
					statement <foreign lang="greek">DI/DOMEN DE/ OI(</foreign> becomes a command
					&lpar;the infinitive <foreign lang="greek">DIDO/MENAI</foreign> written in a
					shortened form and used as an imperative&rpar;. The lie will then be told by
					the Dream and not by Zeus, who may thus save his reputation for
					veracity."</note> and <foreign lang="greek">TO\ ME\N OU(= KATAPU/QETAI
					O)/MBRW|</foreign><note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 23.327">Hom. Il. 23.327</bibl>: "A fathom high from the earth there rises a stump
					all withered, A stump of an oak or a pine, that rots not at all in the rain."
					Problem: "The last statement is incredible." Solution: "Alter the breathing and
						<foreign lang="greek">TO\ ME\N OU)</foreign> becomes <foreign lang="greek">TO\ ME\N OU(=</foreign> and means part of it rots in the rain.'"</note>;
					<milestone n="25.19" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and by punctuation; for example,
				the lines of Empedocles: Soon mortal grow they that aforetime learnt Immortal ways,
				and pure erstwhile commingled.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">The Problem is
					"erstwhile" goes with "pure" or with "commingled." The former interpretation
					seems to give the best solution. Empedocles is speaking of the elements or
					atoms.</note>
				<milestone n="25.20" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Or again by ambiguity, e.g. <foreign lang="greek">PARW/|XHKEN DE\ PLE/W NU/C</foreign>, where <foreign lang="greek">PLEI/W</foreign> is ambiguous.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 10.252">Hom. Il. 10.252</bibl>: "Come now, the night is far
					spent and at hand is the dawning, Far across are the stars and more than two
					parts of the night-time Are gone, but a third is still left us." Problem: If
					"more than two parts" are gone, a third cannot be left. Solution: <foreign lang="greek">PLE/W</foreign> here means "full," i.e., " the full night of
					two-thirds"&equals;"full two-thirds of the night is gone," and so Homer's
					arithmetic is saved.</note><milestone n="25.21" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Others
				according to the habitual use of the phrase, e.g. wine and water is called "wine" so
				you get the phrase "greaves of new-wrought tin";<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Problem: "Greaves are made not of tin but of an alloy of tin and copper."
					Solution: "Compounds are called by the name of the more important partner. Just
					as a mixture of wine and water is called 'wine,' so here an alloy of tin and
					copper is called 'tin.'" So, too, is whisky and water called "whisky."</note> or
				workers in iron are called "braziers," and so Ganymede is said to pour wine for
				Zeus, though they do not drink wine. This last might however be metaphorical.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Nectar:gods::wine: men. Therefore, according to the
					rules of metaphor in chapter 21, nectar may be called "wine" or "the wine of the
					gods."</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.22" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Whenever a word seems to involve a contradiction, one should
				consider how many different meanings it might bear in the passage, e.g. in "There
				the bronzen shaft was stayed,"<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 20.272">Hom. Il. 20.272</bibl>: "Nay but the weighty shaft of
					the warlike hero Aeneas Brake not the shield; for the gold, the gift of a god,
					did withstand it. Through two folds it drave, yet three were beneath, for
					Hephaestus, Crook-footed god, five folds had hammered; two were of bronze-work,
					Two underneath were of tin and one was of gold; there the bronzen Shaft of the
					hero was stayed in the gold." Problem: "Since the gold was presumably outside
					for the sake of ornament, how could the spear he stayed in the gold and yet
					penetrate two folds?" Bywater suggests as a solution that "the plate of gold
					sufficed to stop the course of the spear, though the spear-point actually
					pierced it and indented the underlying plates of brass."</note> we should ask in
				how many ways "being stayed" might be taken, <milestone n="25.23" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> interpreting the passage in this sense or in that, and
				keeping as far as possible from the attitude which Glaucon<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">This may well be the Glaucon mentioned in
					Plato's <title>Ion</title> as an authority on
					Homer.</note> describes <milestone n="1461b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="25.24" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> when he
				says that people make some unwarrantable presupposition and having themselves given
				an adverse verdict proceed to argue from it, and if what they think the poet has
				said does not agree with their own preconceived ideas, they censure him, as if that
				was what he had said. <milestone n="25.25" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> This is what
				has happened in the case of Icarius.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Penelope's
					father.</note> They assume that he was a Spartan and therefore find it odd that
				when Telemachus went to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> he did not
				meet him. But the truth may be, as the Cephallenians say, that Odysseus married a
				wife from their country and that the name was not Icarius but Icadius. So the
				objection is probably due to a mistake.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.26" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> In general any "impossibility" may be
				defended by reference to the poetic effect or to the ideal or to current opinion.
					<milestone n="25.27" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> For poetic effect a convincing
				impossibility is preferable to that which is unconvincing though possible.
					<milestone n="25.28" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It may be impossible that there
				should be such people as Zeuxis<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">See <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1450a">Aristot. Poet. 6.15</bibl>.</note> used to paint,
				but it would be better if there were; for the type should improve on the
					actual.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.29" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Popular tradition may be used to defend what seems
				irrational, and you can also say that sometimes it is not irrational, for it is
				likely that unlikely things should happen. <milestone n="25.30" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Contradictions in terms must be examined in the same way as
				an opponent's refutations in argument, to see whether the poet refers to the same
				thing in the same relation and in the same sense, and has contradicted either what
				he expressly says himself or what an intelligent person would take to be his
				meaning. <milestone n="25.31" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> It is right, however, to
				censure both improbability and depravity where there is no necessity and no use is
				made of the improbability.<milestone n="20" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/>An example is
				Euripides' intro duction of Aegeus<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe"><bibl n="Eur. Med. 663">Eur. Medea 663</bibl>. In Aristotle's opinion there is no
					good reason for Aegeus's appearance and no good use is made of it.</note>
				or&lpar;of depravity&rpar;the character of Menelans in the
					<title>Orestes</title>.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="25.32" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The censures they bring are of five kinds; that things
				are either impossible or irrational or harmful or inconsistent or contrary to
				artistic correctness. The solutions must be studied under the heads specified above,
				twelve in number.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., any expression that is
					criticized should be considered with reference to (1) things as they were; (2)
					things as thy are; (3) things as they are said to be; (4) things as they seem to
					be; (5) things as they ought to be. Further, we should consider whether (6) a
					rare word or (7) a metaphor is used; what is the right (8) accent and (9)
					punctuation; also where there may be (10) ambiguity and what is (11) the
					habitual use of the phrase; also we may refer to (12) the proper standard of
					correctness in poetry as distinct from other arts.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="26.1" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The question may be
				raised whether the epic or the tragic form of representation is the better.
					<milestone n="26.2" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If the better is the less vulgar
				and the less vulgar is always that which appeals to the better audience, then
				obviously the art which makes its appeal to everybody is eminently vulgar.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Aristotle first states the popular condemnation of
					tragedy on the ground that it can be and often is spoilt by the stupid vulgarity
					of actors. So might spectators of certain productions of
					Shakespeare in their haste condemn the poet.
					The refutation of this view begins at 6.</note><milestone n="26.3" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> And indeed actors think the audience do not understand unless
				they put in something of their own, and so they strike all sorts of attitudes, as
				you see bad flute-players whirling about if they have to do "the
					Discus," or mauling the leader of the chorus when
				they are playing the "Scylla."<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1454a">Aristot. Poet. 15.8</bibl></note><milestone n="26.4" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> So tragedy is something like what the older
				school of actors thought of their successors, for Mynniscus used to call Callippides
				"the monkey," because he overacted, and the same was said of Pindarus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Mynniscus acted for Aeschylus: Callippides belonged
					to the next generation, end of fifth century. Pindarus is unknown.</note>
				<milestone n="1462a" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="26.5" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The whole tragic art, then, is
				to epic poetry what these later actors were compared to their predecessors, since
				according to this view epic appeals to a cultivated audience which has no need of
				actor's poses, while tragedy appeals to a lower class. If then it is vulgar, it must
				obviously be inferior.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="26.6" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> First of all, this is not a criticism of poetry but of
				acting: even in reciting a minstrel can overdo his gestures, as Sosistratus did, or
				in a singing competition, like Mnasitheus of Opus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Both unknown.</note><milestone n="26.7" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Besides it is
				not all attitudinizing that ought to be barred any more than all dancing, but only
				the attitudes of inferior people. That was the objection to Callippides; and modern
				actors are similarly criticized for representing women who are not ladies.
					<milestone n="26.8" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Moreover, tragedy fulfils its
				function even without acting, just as much as epic, and its quality can be gauged by
				reading aloud. So, if it is in other respects superior, this disadvantage is not
				necessarily inherent.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="26.9" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Secondly, tragedy has all the elements of the
				epic&mdash;it can even use the hexameter&mdash;<milestone n="26.10" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and in addition a considerable element of its own in the
				spectacle and the music, which make the pleasure all the more vivid; <milestone n="26.11" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> and this vividness can be felt whether it is
				read or acted. <milestone n="1462b" unit="section"/><milestone n="1" ed="Bekker" unit="line"/><milestone n="26.12" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Another point is
				that it attains its end with greater economy of length. What is concentrated is
				always more effective than what is spread over a long period; suppose, for example,
					Sophocles'<title>Oedipus</title>were to be turned into as many lines as there
				are in the<title>
					Iliad
				</title>. <milestone n="26.13" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> Again, the art of the epic
				has less unity, as is shown by the fact that any one epic makes several tragedies.
				The result is that, if the epic poet takes a single plot, either it is set forth so
				briefly as to seem curtailed, or if it conforms to the limit of length<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">Literally "the length of the (proper) limit."</note>
				it seems thin and diluted.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In saying that epic has
				less unity I mean an epic made up of several separate actions. <milestone n="26.14" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> The <title>Iliad</title> has many such parts and so
				has the <title>Odyssey</title>, and each by itself has a certain magnitude. And yet
				the composition of these poems is as perfect as can be and each of them
				is&mdash;as far as an epic may be&mdash;a representation of a single action.
					<milestone n="26.15" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> If then tragedy is superior in
				these respects and also in fulfilling its artistic function&mdash;for tragedies
				and epics should produce not any form of pleasure but the pleasure we have
					described<note anchored="yes" resp="Fyfe">i.e., the pleasure felt when by the
					representation of life in art &ldquo;relief is given&rdquo; to pity,
					fear, and other such emotions, or, to use a term now prevalent, when such
					emotions are &ldquo;released.&rdquo;Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1453b">Aristot. Poet. 14.3</bibl>.</note>&mdash;then obviously, since it
				attains its object better than the epic, the better of the two is tragedy.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone n="26.16" ed="P" unit="Loeb chap"/> This must
				suffice for our treatment of tragedy and epic, their characteristics, their species,
				their constituent parts, and their number and attributes; for the causes of success
				and failure; and for critical problems and their solutions. . . .</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
