<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="work" n="Cic. S. Rosc.">
<bibl><author n="Cic.">Cicero</author>
<title type="work" n="S. Rosc.">Pro Roscio Amerino</title>,
<edition n="Latin">Edited, after Karl Halm.</edition></bibl></title>

<author n="Donk.">E. H. Donkin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Follows the 1915 2nd edition of this commentary.</p>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>Scanned printed text</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="chapter"/>
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English&gt;</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="de">German</language>
<language id="fr">French</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text lang="en">
<body>

<div1 type="introduction"><head>INTRODUCTION</head>
<div2 type="section" n="A.-THE HISTORY OF THE CASE.">
<div3 type="subsect" n="1"><head>1.</head>

<p>The trial of Sextus Roscius for parricide was the first <foreign lang="la">causa publica</foreign> <note anchored="yes" n="1"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 59">59</bibl>. A <foreign lang="la">causa publica</foreign> was one which concerned the State (<foreign lang="la">populus</foreign>), and dealt with an offence not against an individual (<foreign lang="la">privatus</foreign>), but against the whole citizen-body. Willful murder was such an offence, as it threatened the public safety.</note>
or criminal case in which Cicero was engaged. It took place in his
twenty-seventh year, B.C. 80. The circumstances were as follows.</p><p>Sextus Roscius, the father of the accused, was a wealthy <note anchored="yes" n="2"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 20">20</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">nam fundos decem et tres reliquit, qui Tiberim fere omnes tangunt</foreign>.</note>
 and respected <note anchored="yes" n="3">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl>.</note>

citizen of the <foreign lang="la">municipium</foreign> of Ameria (the modern Amelia) in Umbria,
situated about 50 miles north of Rome. He was intimate with several noble
families,<note anchored="yes" n="4">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl> <foreign lang="la">: cum Metellis, Serviliis, Scipionibus erat ei non modo hospitium, verum etiam domesticus usus et consuetudo</foreign>. Cp. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 148">148</bibl> sq.</note>
 and usually lived <note anchored="yes" n="5">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>.</note>
 in Rome, leaving his thirteen estates under the
management of his son Sextus.<note anchored="yes" n="6">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 18">18</bibl>,<bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 42">42sqq.</bibl></note>
 In the summer or autumn
 of B.C. 81 the elder Roscius, while returning at night from a supper-party in
Rome, was attacked near the Pallacinian baths <note anchored="yes" n="7">  These were situated close to the circus Flaminius.</note>
 and murdered. The son was not
in Rome; but a relative and fellow-townsman of the deceased, T. Roscius Magnus,
who was in Rome,<note anchored="yes" n="8">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 18">18</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 92">92</bibl>.	</note>
 sent news of the murder to Ameria, immediately <note anchored="yes" n="9">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 97">97</bibl>.</note>
 after it was
committed, by a courier, one Mallius Glaucia; not however to the house of the
son, but to that of another relative, T. Roscius Capito.<note anchored="yes" n="10">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 19">19</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 96">96</bibl> sqq.</note>
 Both these
relatives, Magnus and Capito, had been on bad terms with their late kinsman,
owing to a dispute about property.<note anchored="yes" n="11"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">inimicitias tibi fuisse cum Sex. Roscio et magnas res
familiaris controversias concedas necesse est.</foreign> Cp. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl> , <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 19">19</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 86">86</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 88">88</bibl>.</note>
 Within the next four days, news of the
murder was brought--probably by Magnus and Capito <note anchored="yes" n="12">12. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 107">107</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">ipsos certo scio non negare ad haec bona Chrysogonum
accessisse impulsu suo</foreign>.</note>
--to L. Cornelius <note anchored="yes" n="13">13. He received this name because he owed his freedom to L. Cornelius
Sulla.  See Verr. 2. 4. 25, and cp. App. Bell. Civ. n 100: 'Sulla set free and
distributed among the people the youngest and strongest of the slaves of the
proscribed, in number more than 10,000, and declared them Roman citizens, and
called them Cornelii after himself, in order that he might have 10,000 men
among the citizens ready to carry out his orders.'  The name Chrysogonus often
occurs in inscriptions as that of freedmen, and was also borne by a slave of
Verres; see Verr. 2. 1.92.</note>
Chrysogonus, a freedman and favourite
of the dictator Sulla, who was with Sulla in his camp at Volaterrae.<note anchored="yes" n="14">  Volaterra was one of the last towns which (after a two years' siege, B.C.  80) surrendered to Sulla. Cp. Strabo, 5.2.6:
"There some of the Etruscans and those who were proscribed by Sulla assembled;
they formed four cohorts of an army, were besieged for two years, and then
surrendered the place under a truce."</note></p><p></p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="2"><head>2.</head>
<p>It was now but a few months after the Sullan reign of terror and the
Proscription. Sulla had doomed to death all who had publicly taken part against
him in Italy, and all such persons were proscribed; i.e. a formal list of their
names was made out and published. Now, since the property of the proscribed was
confiscated by Sulla to reward his agents, those who coveted the possessions of
others had but to contrive to have their names placed on the proscription list:
thus many innocent persons fell victims merely to avarice or to private enmity.
'The slaughter did not cease,' says Sallust, 'until Sulla had enriched all his
followers.' <note anchored="yes" n="15"> Sall. Cat. 51. 32: <foreign lang="la">nostra memoria victor Sulla cum Damasippum et alios
eius modi, qui malo rei publicae creverant, iugulari iussit, quis non factum
eius laudabat? homines scelestos et factiosos, qui seditionibus rem publicam
exagitaverant, merito necatos aiebant. Sed ea res magnae initium cladis fuit:
nam uti quisque domum aut villam, postremo vas aut vestimentum alicuius
concupiverat, dabat operam ut is in proscriptorum numero esset . . . neque
prius finis iugulandi fuit, quam Sulla omnes suos divitiis explevit</foreign>.</note>
 In this way Chrysogonus had already acquired immense
wealth <note anchored="yes" n="16">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 133">133</bibl> sqq.</note>
 and power.<note anchored="yes" n="17"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">adulescens vel potentissimus hoc tempore nostrae
civitatis</foreign>.</note>
 On hearing of the murder of Sex. Roscius and of the
large property which he had left, and learning further that the only heir, his
son, a rustic person of unsuspicious nature and not known in Rome, could easily
be set aside,<note anchored="yes" n="18">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 20">20</bibl>.</note>
 Chrysogonus united with his two informants, Magnus and Capito,
in a plot for getting that property into his possession.</p><p></p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="3"><head>3.</head>
<p>The scheme was carried out as follows. Chrysogonus contrived, though the
deceased had been a partisan of Sulla and the aristocracy,<note anchored="yes" n="19">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 126">126</bibl>.</note>
 and though the
proscription list had been closed some months,<note anchored="yes" n="20"> The day of closing was June 1, B.C. 81. Cp. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">aliquot post
menses et homo occisus est et bona venisse dicuntur;</foreign> and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>.</note> to get his name placed on the
list; <note anchored="yes" n="21"> <foreign lang="la">Tabula proscriptionis.</foreign> The publication of the list was supported by a
<foreign lang="la">'lex de proscriptione'</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 125">125</bibl>).  Cicero, referring there to
this <foreign lang="la">lex,</foreign> says: <foreign lang="la">'sive Valeria est sive Cornelia, non enim novi</foreign>. .
. 'and in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl> he disclaims exact knowledge of it: '<foreign lang="la">opinor esse
in lege</foreign> . . .' Why this vagueness? It is certain that a <foreign lang="la">lex Valeria</foreign>
existed, having been duly passed in the Comitia Centuriata on the motion of L.
Valerius Flaccus as <foreign lang="la">interrex,</foreign> conferring the dictatorship on Sulla and
ratifying Sulla's acts (Cic. de Leg. Agr. 3. 5). Was there, as Cicero implies,
a <foreign lang="la">lex Cornelia</foreign> on the same lines, so that the one might be confused with
the other? Two views have been held: (1) Sulla may have issued an autocratic
enactment,  together with the proscription-list, regulating its operation;
afterwards the phrase <foreign lang="la">'lex Cornelia</foreign>' may have been applied to this
enactment when it had been legalised by the <foreign lang="la">lex Valeria;</foreign> (2) Sulla may
have supplemented the <foreign lang="la">lex Valeria</foreign> by a subsequent <foreign lang="la">lex Cornelia</foreign>
announcing further regulations as to the proscribed persons, e.g. the
regulations (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 126">126</bibl>) as to men slain within the outposts of Sulla's
opponents, and (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>) as to the day up to which the list held good:
together with other provisious (Verr. 2.1.123; Livy, Epit. 89). Whichever view
is correct, the two titles would refer to closely allied ordinances, both
virtually due to Sulla; Cicero refers to them as not needing to be
distinguished, for he is as it were speaking thus: 'My duty does not require me
to be acquainted with the exact basis of legality on which my opponents justify
their treatment of my client. I only say that nothing in their
<foreign lang="la">lex</foreign>--whatever its title--that has reached my ears, justifies them at
all.' Possibly, as editors have suggested, he is speaking of this <foreign lang="la">lex</foreign>
with veiled sarcasm as a piece of autocracy, a parody of law.</note>
so that his entire property fell in to the State.<note anchored="yes" n="22"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 126">126</bibl>. Because proscribed persons were looked on as public
enemies.</note> It was then sold by public auction <note anchored="yes" n="23"> The property of a proscribed person was sold as public property <foreign lang="la">sub hasta</foreign>
(originally the symbol of booty won in battle), i.e. by public auction, and
was always sold as an undivided whole.  Such a sale was called <foreign lang="la">sectio</foreign>;
the purchaser, <foreign lang="la">sector</foreign>: cp. Gaius, Inst. 4. 146, <foreign lang="la">sectores vocantur qui
publica bona mercantu</foreign>r. The meaning of the word <foreign lang="la">sector</foreign> is very
obscure, and was so even to the ancient grammarians, who derived it froni
<foreign lang="la">sequi</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">sectari</foreign>, and explained <foreign lang="la">sectores</foreign> as  <foreign lang="la">sectatores
bonorum.</foreign> The derivation from <foreign lang="la">secare</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 80">80</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">sectores
bonorum et collorum</foreign>) seems more correct; but the theory that the purchasers
were called <foreign lang="la">sectores</foreign> because they used to 'cut up' the entire property
which they had bought into small divisions so as to sell it again, is surely a
false one. (It is expressly contradicted by &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 103">103</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">testimonium
dicturus est is, qui et sector est et sicarius, hoc est, qui et illorum ipsorum
bonorum, de quibus agitur, emptor atque possessor est, et eum hominem
occidendum curavit de cuius morte quaeritur</foreign>.) Since the purchaser of a
property had to undertake the debts with which it was encumbered, Mommsen
explains the word, with great probability, in reference to the percentage which
was deducted from the price of a property, in consideration of its being
saddled with debts. Thus purchasers who, instead of the full price, offered 50
per cent. of the price, would justly be called 'cutters off' <foreign lang="la">(sectores)</foreign>.
The property of Milo, for instance, on account of its indebtedness, was
sold <foreign lang="la">semuncia</foreign>, i.e. for 1/24th of its value.</note>
and as no one dared to bid against the dreaded favourite, Chrysogonus bought it
at the nominal price of 2,000 sesterces <note anchored="yes" n="24">  Plutarch, Cic. 3, says <foreign lang="greek">disxili/wn draxmw=n</foreign>, misunderstanding the phrase <foreign lang="la">nummum</foreign> (i.e. <foreign lang="la">sestertium</foreign>) in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>, since the drachma was worth more than four times the sesterce.</note>
, though the real value is said to
have been six million sesterces <note anchored="yes" n="25">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>.</note>. Three of the best estates were given <note anchored="yes" n="26"> In &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl> Cicero only says <foreign lang="la">possidere audio</foreign>: but later on
(&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 99">99</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 108">108</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 115">115</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 117">117</bibl>) he asserts it as a fact. We
must, however, suppose that Capito did not come into possession of the three
<foreign lang="la">praedia</foreign> immediately after the sale; for, if so, he could hardly have
appeared amongst the <foreign lang="la">decem primi</foreign> of Ameria in Sulla's camp.</note> to
Capito as his share of the spoil; <note anchored="yes" n="27">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 107">107</bibl> sub fin</note> the ten remaining estates and
the personal effects were taken possession of by Chrysogonus  through  Magnus,
whom  he  had appointed steward.<note anchored="yes" n="28"> &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 108">108</bibl>.</note>  The latter came to Ameria, hunted the
rightful heir Sextus out of house and home, and began to give away, sell,<note anchored="yes" n="29">  Sc. by auction; see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 23">23</bibl>. <foreign lang="la">Auctio</foreign>, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">sectio</foreign>, meant the sale of individual articles of property.</note> and
appropriate the movable property.</p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="4"><head>4.</head>
<p>This caused the greatest indignation in Ameria.<note anchored="yes" n="30">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 24">24</bibl>.</note> The decuriones <note anchored="yes" n="31"> In <foreign lang="la">municipia</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">colonias</foreign> the Senate (variously named
<foreign lang="la">senatus</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">ordo</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">curia</foreign>) usually consisted of 100 members,
divided into decuries (<foreign lang="la">decuriones</foreign>), whence the whole body was called
<foreign lang="la">ordo decurionum</foreign>. The <foreign lang="la">decem primi</foreign> who stood at the head of the
decuries formed a special committee, and used to represent the community on
embassies.</note> of the
town resolved to send the <foreign lang="la">decem primi</foreign>, of whom Capito was one,<note anchored="yes" n="32">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 109">109</bibl>.</note> to the
camp of Sulla, to give evidence of the aristocratic tendencies of the
deceased,<note anchored="yes" n="33">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 25">25</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">doceantque eum (Sullam), qui vir Sex. Roscius fuerit</foreign>.</note> and to get his name taken off the list and the sale of his property
annulled.</p><p>But Capito baffled their efforts.<note anchored="yes" n="34">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 109">109</bibl> sqq., <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 116">116</bibl> sqq. The account in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 25">25</bibl> is different, where Capito's share in the affair is only touched on in passing.</note> He let Chrysogonus know the object of the
mission, and showed him how great a loss he would suffer if the sale were annulled; he prevented the embassy coming before Sulla, and contrived to put
them off with the promises of Chrysogonus that their wishes should be carried
out. Finally they departed without addressing their request to Sulla at
all.<note anchored="yes" n="35"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 26">26</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">re inorata</foreign>, which phrase is distinguishable from
<foreign lang="la">re infecta</foreign>; see note.</note></p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="5"><head>5.</head>
<p>Thus the conspirators remained in possession of their spoil. But they could
not feel secure of it. The Amerini might make new efforts for their unfortunate
fellow-townsman; or, as time went on, he might be reinstated through some
political movement.<note anchored="yes" n="36"> Sulla's own enactment provided against this; cp. Vell. Pat. 2. 28. 4,
<foreign lang="la">adiectum etiam, ut bona proscriptorum venirent exclusique paternis opibus
liberi etiam petendorum honorum iure prohiberentur</foreign>. But Cicero himself
suggests that his opponents anticipated such an occurrence;
&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl> sub fin., <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 146">146</bibl>.</note> Unless he were entirely got rid of, they could not feel at ease.<note anchored="yes" n="37">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">quoniam ei pecuniae vita Sex. Roscii obstare atque officere videatur</foreign>.</note> Accordingly they began to make plots against his life. Sextus, by
the advice of his friends, fled to Rome,<note anchored="yes" n="38">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>.</note> where he found shelter and
protection with Caecilia,<note anchored="yes" n="39">  See &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 147">147</bibl>, notes.</note> a noble lady and a friend of his father: <note anchored="yes" n="40">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">qua pater usus erat plurimum</foreign>.</note> thus he
was safe from assassination. Magnus and Capito now formed the atrocious design
of taking advantage of the crime through which the father had been got rid
of, for the removal of the son.  They resolved to accuse the son himself of the
murder.<note anchored="yes" n="41"> It is remarkable that Cicero has not noticed the inconsistency involved in
this plan of his opponents. If the elder Roscius had really been proscribed,
his murder could not legally be punished, for the <foreign lang="la">lex Cornelia</foreign> promised
even <foreign lang="la">rewards</foreign> to those who killed the proscribed, 'even if it be the
slave who slays his master, or the son who slays his father,' Plut. Sull. 31 ;
while if he had <foreign lang="la">not</foreign> been proscribed, the sale of his property must have
been illegal.  (Richter.)</note></p><p></p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="6"><head>6.</head>
<p>This plan for several reasons offered hopes of success. The father and son
seem not to have been on the best of terms with one another; <note anchored="yes" n="42">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 40">40</bibl> sqq., <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 52">52</bibl> sqq.</note> the trouble
taken by Cicero to contradict any such idea goes to show that it had some
foundation, and we may infer from the assertions of the accuser that the
somewhat boorish manners of the son may have offended the father's aristocratic
tastes.<note anchored="yes" n="43">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 74">74</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">hunc hominem ferum atque agrestem fuisse</foreign>.</note> Again, the witnesses who could throw most light on the murder were
two slaves, who had been with the elder Roscius in Rome; they had now passed
with the rest of the property into the hands of Chrysogonus, and could not be
examined without his consent.<note anchored="yes" n="44">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 119">119</bibl>-123.</note> The time, too, was favourable:<note anchored="yes" n="45">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">ut quoniam crimine non poterant, tempore ipso pugnarent</foreign>.</note> as the trial
would be the first held for murder after a long interruption of all judicial
business, so that
the strictest procedure could be expected from the jury, the voice of justice
having been silent so long. <note anchored="yes" n="46"> &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>.</note> But the accusers built still greater hopes on
the powerful influence of Chrysogonus. Through fear of the dictator, as they
calculated, the accused would find no one to defend him; at any rate, no
advocate would dare to say a word about the shameful sale of the property, nor
to reveal the criminal plot of which the accused was to be the victim.<note anchored="yes" n="47">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 58">58</bibl>.</note></p><p></p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="7"><head>7.</head>
<p>To open the prosecution one Erucius, a professed accuser,<note anchored="yes" n="48">  <foreign lang="la">Accusator vetus</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>: cp. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, note.</note> was suborned; <note anchored="yes" n="49"> That Erucius was assisted by additional accusers (<foreign lang="la">subscriptores</foreign>)
cannot be inferred from &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">sedere in accusatorum
subselliis</foreign>, and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">qui cum accusatoribus sederes</foreign>, where
the plural refers generally to his opponents (cp. 6.30): see on the contrary,
&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">sederes cum accusatore</foreign>; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 110">110</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">si accusator
voluerit testimonium iis denuntiare</foreign>.  Nor does the singular prove that
Erucius acted alone.</note>
a man of some education, but of low descent and bad character.<note anchored="yes" n="50">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 46">46</bibl>.</note> Bribed
witnesses <note anchored="yes" n="51"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 30">30</bibl>; <foreign lang="la">testes in hunc et accusatores hujusce pecunia
comparant</foreign>.</note> were to support the charge, among others perhaps Roscius Magnus
himself,<note anchored="yes" n="52">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 84">84</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 85">85</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 104">104</bibl>.  We learn also that Capito intended to appear as witness; &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 84">84</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 100">100</bibl> sqq.</note> who had been present in Rome at the time of the murder.
</p>
<p>Sex. Roscius was not left in the lurch by his father's friends.<note anchored="yes" n="53">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 1">1</bibl> sqq., <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl> sub fin.,<bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>.</note> The party of the nobles though closely attached to Sulla's interests, could not but
feel in the highest degree aggrieved at the overpowering influence and the
revolting pride of an upstart favourite, and were glad to support the Cause of
Sextus.<note anchored="yes" n="54">  Cp. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 136">136</bibl>-142.</note> From fear of offending Sulla, no prominent man dared conduct the
defence himself; but young Cicero consented to undertake it,<note anchored="yes" n="55">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 4">4</bibl>.</note>
 at the request
of the noble friends of Sex. Roscius, especially the youthful M. Messalla.<note anchored="yes" n="56"> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 149">149</bibl>. It is generally supposed that the consul of B.C. 61 is
meant, who attained to this office only two years later than Cicero; but
Drumann (Rom. Hist. v.237, note 84), with greater probability, thinks that the
consul of B.C. 53 is meant, "who was now sixteen years of age, reckoning from
the age at which the consulship was usually obtained, and had only lately
assumed the toga virilis."</note></p><p></p>
<p></p></div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="B.-THE SPEECH.">

<div3 type="subsect" n="8"><head>8.</head>
<p>Cicero's defence divides into three parts.<note anchored="yes" n="57">  &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 35">35</bibl>.</note>
 In the first
(&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 37">37</bibl>-42) he examines the accusation, and shows its entire
groundlessness and the want of any corroborative evidence.  An English counsel
for the defence who had done this, would have done all that was necessary.<note anchored="yes" n="58">  Cp. Forsyth's Life of Cicero, p.29, ed. 3.</note>

But Cicero goes further: in the second part of the speech (&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>-123) he
turns from defence to attack, and shows, from the life and character of Magnus,
and the incidents preceding the murder, how clearly facts pointed to Magnus and
Capito themselves as the authors of the crime.  In the third part
(&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 124">124</bibl>-150) he even attacks Chrysogonus directly, and
depicts with deep indignation the flagrant misuse which he had made of his
power, both on other occasions and especially in the purchase of the property
and in his heartless behaviour towards the accused.</p><p>Cicero's boldness and courage were rewarded by the acquittal<note anchored="yes" n="59">  Plut. Cic. 3: "He was admired for having undertaken the defence, and for having brought it to a successful issue."</note> of his client;
a result which we may conjecture that Sulla himself saw without displeasure,<note anchored="yes" n="60">  It has been well conjectured that the intercession of the Metelli, with whom Sulla was connected through his fourth wife Caecilia, mother of Faustus Sulla, had a favourable effect.</note>
since if such horrors had been palliated, the stability of his own institutions
might have been threatened.<note anchored="yes" n="61">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 137">137</bibl> sqq.</note> We do not know whether a <foreign lang="la">restitutio
bonorum</foreign> ensued, nor whether after the acquittal of Sextus an accusation was
brought against Magnus and Capito. But neither is probable. With the fear of
the dictator's wrath before him, Cicero must have been well contented to have
effected his client's acquittal on a dangerous charge, without wishing to
attempt more.</p></div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="9"><head>9.</head>
<p>Though the speech is one of Cicero's youthful performances it has been
justly held in the highest estimation both among the ancients and in later
times, and has won the young orator well-earned fame<note anchored="yes" n="62">  Cic. Brut. 312: <foreign lang="la">itaque prima causa publica pro Sex. Roscio dicta tantum commendationis habuit, ut non ulla esset, quae non digna nostro patrocinio videretur</foreign>.</note> for the courage and tact
with which he conducted a just cause under the greatest difficulties. It is
true that in several places the style is youthfully overladen and strained : <note anchored="yes" n="63">  Cic. Orat. 107: <foreign lang="la">quantis illa clamoribus</foreign> (applause) <foreign lang="la">adulescentuli diximus de supplicio parricidarum! quae nequaquam satis deferbuisse post aliquanto sentire coepimus</foreign> : "<foreign lang="la">quid enim tam commune quam spiritus vivis . . . ut ne ad saxa quidem mortui conquiescant</foreign>" (c. xxvi. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 72">72</bibl>)-<foreign lang="la">et quae sequuntur; sunt enim omnia sicut adulescentis non tam re et maturitate quam spe et exspectatione laudati</foreign>.</note>

the periods are not so rounded and full, nor the transitions so natural and
unaffected, as in his later works; there are many peculiarities in the diction
which are not to be found in the later speeches, though some of them are
certainly due to incorrect transmission. But these individual defects are amply
compensated for by the good impression which the speech makes as a whole. The
deep conviction of the justice of his cause animates and exalts the young
orator. None of his statements represent him as serving the interests of one
party, or merely playing the advocate. He faces his abandoned opponents with
manly boldness; and though he has indeed the prudence to avoid
anything that might offend the all-powerful dictator, his consciousness of
right makes him utterly regardless of the power of the faction to which his
opponents belong, and contemptuous of their scoffs and threats. The moral
indignation which speaks from every line of the speech must have made all the
deeper impression on his hearers in the forum because of the length of time
during which the voice of justice and truth had been silenced under the
pressure of brute force.</p><p></p></div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="C.-THE PUNISHMENT OF PARRICIDE.">

<div3 type="subsect" n="10"><head>10.</head>
<p>From two passages <note anchored="yes" n="64">  De Inv. 2. 50,149; ad Her. 1.13.23. A case of the <foreign lang="la">poena cullei</foreign> is mentioned in the Epitome of Liv. Lxviii., dating about B.C. 101. Probably the book may have contained a detailed account of the punishment.</note> in Cicero's rhetorical treatises, we learn what was
apparently the original form of the punishment of parricide.  Immediately after
sentence was passed, the criminal's face was covered with a wolf's skin, and
wooden sandals<note anchored="yes" n="65">  <foreign lang="la">Soleae ligneae</foreign>, otherwise explained as <gloss>fetters</gloss>. </note>
 bound on his feet, as though the air might no longer be
defiled by his breath nor the ground with his tread. He was then taken back to
prison, but only to remain there until a sack was prepared in which he was cast
into the nearest river or sea. We hear of further provisions in the Pandects<note anchored="yes" n="66">  XLVIII. 9.9.</note> <foreign lang="la">poena parricidii more maiorum haec instituta est, ut parricida virgis sanguineis</foreign> (with scarlet rods) <foreign lang="la">verberatus, deinde
culleo</foreign> (made of leather) <foreign lang="la">insuatur cum cane</foreign> (an animal despised by
Greeks and Romans), <foreign lang="la">gallo gallinaceo</foreign> (which, like the parricide, was
devoid of all filial affection), <foreign lang="la">et vipera</foreign> (a creature universally
hated, and whose birth was supposed to necessitate its mother's death <note anchored="yes" n="67">  Aristot. Hist. Anim. 2. 8. Plin. N.H. 8. 54; 11. 44.</note>
),
<foreign lang="la">et simia</foreign> (probably as a degraded imitation of man), <foreign lang="la">deinde in mare
profundum</foreign> (or into a river) <foreign lang="la">culleus iactetur</foreign><note anchored="yes" n="68">  The symbolism of the animals has been otherwise explained.  "From the house whose peace has been broken are taken the animals who might to have guarded and aroused it (sc. <foreign lang="la">canis et gallus</foreign>); from the wilderness are taken the constant foe (<foreign lang="la">vipera</foreign>) and the base imitation (<foreign lang="la">simia</foreign>) of man, as an offering to the offended gods."  (Richter.)</note> The sack with its
contents was thrown into the sea, in order that the criminal might be withdrawn
from all the elements:  "<foreign lang="la">ut omni elementorum usu vivus carere incipiat et ei
coelum superstiti, terra mortuo auferatur</foreign>"(Justinian, Inst. iv. 18.6). From
the fact that Cicero does not mention the animals, while two writers under the
Empire refer to them (Seneca, de Clem. 1. 15, to the serpents; and Juvenal,
8.212, 13.154, to the apes), it has been inferred that they were not added till
after the establishment of the Empire; but Cicero's not mentioning them can
hardly be taken as a proof of this, since according to his later opinion<note anchored="yes" n="69">  See above, note 63.</note> even
what he does say here about the <foreign lang="la">poena cullei</foreign> is too full and copious.</p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="11"><head>11.</head>
<p>Though Cicero and the Digest (l.c.) speak as if the <foreign lang="la">poena cullei</foreign>
regularly occurred in practice, it is a question whether this was the case
under the later republic. Zumpt <note anchored="yes" n="70">  <foreign lang="de">Criminalrecht</foreign>, vol. ii. part 2, pp.53 sqq.</note> believes that it was inflicted only in cases
where there was no need of a trial, viz. when the criminal was caught in the
very act, or when he confessed his guilt. Zumpt's arguments are:</p><p>(1)	No <foreign lang="la">quaestio</foreign> could or ever did inflict the punishment of death.</p><p>(2)	Suetonius, in order to show the leniency of Augustus, describes him as
dealing in the following way with a man caught in the act of parricide. The
Emperor wished to get him off the punishment of the sack, and therefore put to
him the leading question, 'You surely did not kill your father?'
<emph>because only those who confessed their guilt received this
punishment.</emph><note anchored="yes" n="71">  Suet. Aug.33.</note> In such a case the criminal might answer 'No,' and
then be tried and punished in the ordinary way, viz. by exile and
confiscation.</p><p>We may also notice that Cicero's passage about the <foreign lang="la">culleus</foreign> in this
speech <note anchored="yes" n="72">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 70">70</bibl>-73.</note> is evidently meant to enhance the greatness of the <foreign lang="la">crimen</foreign> <note anchored="yes" n="73">  <foreign lang="la">&sect;</foreign> 72: <foreign lang="la">tanti maleficii crimen, cui maleficio tam insigne supplicium est constitutum</foreign>, &amp;c.</note>
of which his adversaries had dared to accuse Sex. Roscius, not to rouse the
pity of the jury as if he were really in danger of so horrible a punishment.
</p></div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="D.-THE COURT OF JUSTICE.">

<div3 type="subsect" n="12"><head>12.</head>
<p>The court of justice before which an accusation for parricide was brought,
was the <foreign lang="la">quaestio inter sicarios</foreign>.  This phrase needs a short
explanation.</p><p>In early times criminal cases in Rome used to come before the whole people,
assembled in the <foreign lang="la">Comitia centuriata</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">tributa</foreign>. But, owing to
the inconvenience of this mode of trial, the <foreign lang="la">Comitia</foreign> frequently used to
delegate their power to special commissions, <foreign lang="la">quaestiones</foreign>, of one or more
persons, appointed to try individual cases.  The next step was to establish,
instead of these temporary commissions, <emph>permanent</emph>
commissions or courts (<foreign lang="la">quaestiones perpetuae</foreign>), which sat to try the
commoner crimes: the first instance of this was the standing commission to try
cases of extortion (<foreign lang="la">de pecuniis repetundis</foreign>), established in 149 B.C., on
the proposal of L. Calpurnius Piso.  The system grew, and was finally brought
into general operation by Sulla, who much increased the number of the permanent
courts. Each <foreign lang="la">quaestio</foreign> dealt with one class of offences only:  thus there
was a <foreign lang="la">quaestio de repetundis</foreign>, another <foreign lang="la">de peculatu,</foreign> another <foreign lang="la">de
ambitu</foreign>, another <foreign lang="la">inter sicarios</foreign>,
<note anchored="yes" n="74">  The expression <foreign lang="la">quaestio</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">iudicium inter sicarios</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl>), as well as <foreign lang="la">inter sicarios deferre, accusare</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 90">90</bibl>), <foreign lang="la">defendere</foreign>, was used, because there was no substantive to express the action of murder, answering to <foreign lang="la">peculatus, veneficium</foreign>, &amp;c.; it was impossible to say <foreign lang="la">sicae deferre</foreign>, on the analogy of <foreign lang="la">veneficii deferre</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">de sica deferre</foreign>, on that of <foreign lang="la">de vi deferre</foreign>.  It was therefore said, <foreign lang="la">ita deferre ut nomen alicuius inter sicarios referatur;</foreign> instead of which the short phrase <foreign lang="la">inter sicarios deferre</foreign> and the other analogous forms came into use.</note>
and so forth; the last-named being the one which dealt with murder, before which Sex. Roscius came to be tried.
The law by which this <foreign lang="la">quaestio</foreign> was established (for every <foreign lang="la">quaestio</foreign>
was established by a separate law) was the <foreign lang="la">lex Cornelia de sicariis et
veneficis</foreign>; but this law comprehended more than the name implies, as it was
directed not only against stabbing and poisoning, but against every form of
murder, including even judicial murder; and it seems to have contained special
regulations as to parricide, for the <foreign lang="la">poena cullei</foreign> was expressly
mentioned.<note anchored="yes" n="75">  See Smith's Dict. Ant. Lex Cornelia.</note> Apparently it was also provided that the trial of such a rare and
unnatural crime should be taken <foreign lang="la">extra ordinem</foreign>, i.e. out of regular
succession, before other crimes of the same class ; <note anchored="yes" n="76">  Cp. Cic. de Inv. 2. &sect; 58.</note> which perhaps explains
the fact that the present trial was the <foreign lang="la">first</foreign> after a long cessation of
judicial business.</p><p></p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsect" n="13"><head>13.</head>
<p>The judge presiding in the <foreign lang="la">quaestio inter sicarios</foreign> in the present
year (B.C. 80) was M. Fannius,<note anchored="yes" n="77">  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 12">12</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 85">85</bibl>.</note> who had already acted as <foreign lang="la">iudex
quaestionis</foreign> in a similar case.<note anchored="yes" n="78">  Before the <foreign lang="la">lex Cornelia de sicariis</foreign> was passed, there can hardly have been a <emph>permanent</emph> court <foreign lang="la">inter sicarios</foreign> (see, however, Mommsen, Rom. Hist. in. pp.112, 372); therefore the words <foreign lang="la">cum huic eidem quaestioni iudex praeesses</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl>, can scarcely refer to a continuous presidency, but rather to a commission which he had received as <foreign lang="la">vir aedilicius</foreign> to preside in some single trial for murder; the words <foreign lang="la">qualem te iam antea populo Romano praebuisti</foreign> point to the same thing. In the words quoted above from &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl> the reading is doubtful, as <foreign lang="la">iudex</foreign> is wanting in one of the best MSS. and may be spurious. If genuine, <foreign lang="la">iudex</foreign>=<foreign lang="la">index quaestionis</foreign> (The Latter Word Being Supplied From <foreign lang="la">quaestioni</foreign>), which phrase signified presiding judges who were appointed to supplement the number of the praetors when the latter were not sufficient for all the <foreign lang="la">quaestiones</foreign>; cp. Ramsay, Rom. Ant. pp.335-6.</note> The jury was composed, according
to the reform introduced by Sulla, of senators.<note anchored="yes" n="79">  Vell. Pat. 2. 32. 3: <foreign lang="la">per idem tempus Cotta iudicandi munus, quod C. Gracchus ereptum senatui ad equites, Sulla ab illis ad senatum transtulerant, aequaliter inter utrumque ordinem partitus est</foreign>.</note> As to their number or how
they were selected, nothing precise is known: nor can any certain explanation
be given of the words <foreign lang="la">qui ex senatu in hoc consilium delecti estis propter
severitatem</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>.  We may conjecture that the presidents of the
different <foreign lang="la">quaestiones</foreign> selected their <foreign lang="la">consilia</foreign> or juries in turn,
and that the president of the <foreign lang="la">quaestio inter sicarios</foreign> had first choice,
or chose among the first, so that he could secure those jurors who were most
distinguished for strict rectitude ; or at any rate that his jurors counted as
such.</p>
</div3></div2></div1>

<div1 type="commentary">
<head>Pro.Rosc.donk</head>
<pb n="1"/> 
<div2 type="section" n="1">
<milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>

<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Credo ego vos mirari</lemma> = <foreign lang="greek">qauma/zoite</foreign>. <foreign lang="la">iudices</foreign>, <ref n="intro.,13" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 13</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid sit quod</lemma>, <gloss>what is (the reason) why . . .</gloss> : cf. <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 99">99</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quid erat quod</foreign>, and <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 138">138</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nobilissimi</lemma>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc.149">149</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aetate</lemma>, <ref n="1" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 1</ref>, <foreign lang="la">ingenio</foreign> (<gloss>ability</gloss>) =<foreign lang="la">facultate dicendi</foreign>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 9">9</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 62">62</bibl>; <foreign lang="la">auctoritate</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 3">3</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quod nondum ad rem publicam accessi</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">omnes hi</lemma>, the friends of Sex. Roscius : see <ref n="7" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 7</ref>. Up to <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">defendere ipsi</lemma> the sentence is concessive : <gloss> <emph>It is true that</emph> all . . . think, etc.; <emph>but</emph> they do not dare</gloss>, etc.  For the omission of the adversative particle Richter compares &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 2">2</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">si qui istorum dixisset . . . ego si omnia dixero</foreign>.  &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 42">42</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 57">57</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 58">58</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">adesse</lemma>, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 2">2</bibl>.  Others join <foreign lang="la">adesse in hac causa</foreign>, but the addition has no force in an allusion to the <foreign lang="la">advocati</foreign>, i.e. the friends who supported the accused merely by their presence in court.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">novo</lemma>, <gloss>unheard of</gloss>, <gloss>strange</gloss>; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 30">30</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">crimen incredibile</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">scelere</lemma>, abstract, <gloss>wickedness</gloss>, <gloss>villainy</gloss>, as in &sect;&sect;  <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 7">7</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 12">12</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 25">25</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">defendi</lemma>: notice two special meanings of this verb in the present speech; here, <gloss>to ward off, repel</gloss> ; in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 136">136</bibl> <gloss>to support or strive for (an undertaking)</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">officium</lemma>, as <foreign lang="la">hospites</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl>.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2">

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quid ergo?</lemma> introduces a question which the speaker only suggests in order to negative it at once : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 122">122</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quid igitur?</foreign> and see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 36">36</bibl>, first note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praeter ceteros</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quia</lemma>: <foreign lang="la">quod</foreign> would better answer the question <foreign lang="la">quae rea impulit?</foreign> Before <foreign lang="la">quia</foreign> supply <foreign lang="la">causam recepi</foreign>.

<pb n="2"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">amplitudo</lemma>, the especial attribute of the <foreign lang="la">ordo senatorius</foreign>; cf. <bibl>de Dome sua, &sect; 55</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ordo amplissimus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si verbum de re publica fecisset</lemma>, <gloss>if he had in a single word touched on politics.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fieri necesse est</lemma>. In narrating the sale of the property of Sex. Roscius, allusion must be made to the proscriptions and Sulla's regime.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">multo plura</lemma>, etc.; i.e. a mere hint, from a prominent man, of his political opinions, would be caught up and exaggerated by the audience.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">exire atque . . . emanare</lemma>, i.e. will not be reported so far by word of mouth, and so be liable to be exaggerated and misrepresented. Note the slightness of antithesis between this and <foreign lang="la">multo plura . . . dixisse putaretur</foreign>, which words would rather lead on to the thought, <gloss>but <emph>my</emph> words will not be taken for more than they are worth.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">concedi . . . ignosci</lemma>, synonymous terms used for variety; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 10">10</bibl> sub fin., <foreign lang="la">praebeas . . . impertias</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vel occultum esse</lemma> differs only verbally from <foreign lang="la">exire atque emanare</foreign> above; but here there is a distinct antithesis with <foreign lang="la">neque obscurum potest esse</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad rem publicam accessi</lemma>. Cicero did not enter on the quaestorship until five years later.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ignoscendi ratio</lemma>, <gloss>pardoning</gloss>; a periphrasis for the nonexistent verbal subst. of <foreign lang="la">ignoscere</foreign>.  N&auml;gelsbach, Lat. Stil. &sect; 27, quotes ad Q. Fr. 1
.1.18, <foreign lang="la">praecipiendi rationem</foreign> =<gloss> teaching</gloss>, <gloss>theorising</gloss>, with other instances.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cognoscendi</lemma>.  <foreign lang="la">Cognoscere</foreign> is the technical term for inquiry into a crime; a process which had been abandoned for the summary procedure of the proscriptions. For the <foreign lang="la">paronomasia</foreign>, cf. Ter. Heaut. 2.1.5, <foreign lang="la">Mihi si umquam filius erit, ne ille facili me utetur patre : Nam et cognoscendi et ignoscendi dabitur peccati locus</foreign>: and in this speech, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 18">18</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">suspiciosum . . . perspicuum; </foreign> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 42">42</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">confirmaret . . . infirmem; </foreign> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 89">89</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">derogo . . . adrogo; </foreign> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 135">135</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">videtis . . . invidetis; </foreign> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 117">117</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">praediis . . . praemiis;</foreign> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 112">112</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">offers . . . officio . . . officis . . . obstas.</foreign> Landgraf quotes these among many instances of the <foreign lang="la">Asianum genus dicendi</foreign>, i.e. the artificial florid style, followed at first by Cicero before he studied under Melon in Rhodes.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dicerent</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">causam</foreign>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ita petitum sit . . .</lemma>; the request was made to others <foreign lang="la">ita</foreign>, <emph>only</emph> in such a manner, i.e. backed by <emph>only</emph> such moderate claims, that they felt they could equally comply or not, without violating friendship. For <foreign lang="la">ita</foreign> in this limiting sense see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">utrumvis</lemma>, to undertake the defence or decline it; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ii contenderunt</lemma>, <ref n="7" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect;  7</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5">
<milestone n="II" unit="chapter"/>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causis . . . causae</lemma>,  <gloss>reasons . . . case.</gloss> This figure of speech, <foreign lang="la">cum continenter unum verbum non eadem sententia ponitur</foreign> (Cic. Orat. 135), was named <foreign lang="greek">plokh/</foreign>  or <foreign lang="greek">a)ntimeta/qesis</foreign> by the rhetoricians. Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ut ad eam rem aliquem accusatorem veterem compararent, qui de ea re posset dicere aliquid, in qua re</foreign>, etc. ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 149">149</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">causam mihi tradidit, quem sua causa cupere intellegebat ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 7">7</bibl>, peto . . . vitam ne petat.</foreign> Auct. ad Herenn. IV. 21, <foreign lang="la">"Cur eam rem tam studiose curas, quae multas tibi dabit curas?" "Nam amari iucundum est, si curetur, ne quid insit amari." "Veniam ad vos, si mihi senatus det veniam."</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">unus</lemma>, <gloss>rather than anyone else </gloss>= <foreign lang="la">unus praeter ceteros</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui . . . possem</lemma>, in a generic sense  <gloss>as the one man left, such as could . . .</gloss>  (Sonnenschein, New Grammar 335).
</p>
<p> <pb n="3"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">et fortunis</lemma> : frequently joined with <foreign lang="la">capite</foreign>, as here ; since capital trials involved, as a rule, partial or entire loss of property. The phrase here seems used only formally, to avoid mentioning the <foreign lang="la">poena cullei</foreign> (<ref n="10" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 10</ref>); and &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 143">143</bibl>, show that Cicero did not mean to enter on a <foreign lang="la">dimicatio de fortunis</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causam dicere</lemma>: said alike of the <foreign lang="la">reus</foreign> (&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 13">13</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 56">56</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 82">82</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 85">85</bibl>) and of the <foreign lang="la">patronus causae</foreign> (here and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 12">12</bibl>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eius rei</lemma>; sc. the fact that they held in their possession the property of the murdered man.  On <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ab accusatoribus</lemma>, see <ref n="n.,49" targOrder="U">Introd. note 49</ref>.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quae sunt</lemma>, <gloss>which are worth.</gloss> Supply the abl. <foreign lang="la">centenis milibus sestertium</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de viro</lemma>, as representative of the State. In historical language Cicero would not have said <foreign lang="la">de L. Sulla bona emit</foreign>; but the words, which he puts with bitter irony into the mouth of Chrysogonus, point to Sulla as the authorizer of the purchase, and to the sale <foreign lang="la">sub hasta</foreign>, as of State property, <ref n="n.,23" targOrder="U">Introd. note 23</ref>. Cf. Verr. 2.3.81 : <foreign lang="la">Unus adhuc fuit post Romam conditam, cui respublica se totam traderet, L. Sulla  Hic tantum potuit, ut nemo illo invito nec bona nec patriam nec vitam retinere posset; tantum animi habuit ad audaciam, ut dicere in contione non dubitaret, bona civium Romanorum cum venderet, se praedam suam vendere</foreign>. The phrase <foreign lang="la">emere de aliquo</foreign> is as frequent as <foreign lang="la">ab aliquo</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">honoris causa nomino</lemma> (the opposite to <foreign lang="la">contumeliae causa nominare</foreign>, Verr. 1.18) was a formula used in mentioning a living person of distinction, indirectly connected with the matter in hand, in order to preclude any idea that the speaker would allow himself to make a derogatory allusion to him. Cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, de Imp. Pomp. 58, and esp. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 47">47</bibl> below, <foreign lang="la">homines notos sumere odiosum est, cum et illud incertum sit, velintne ii sese nominari</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nummum</lemma>, <ref n="3" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 3</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vel</lemma>, <gloss>perhaps.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">L. Cornelius</lemma>, <ref n="n.,13" targOrder="U">Introd. note 13</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pecuniam</lemma>, <gloss>the entire property</gloss> = <foreign lang="la">patrimonium</foreign>. "<foreign lang="la">Pecuniam dicit universitatem rei familiaris</foreign>," Schol. Cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 7">7</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 23">23</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 26">26</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 86">86</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 110">110</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">invaserit</lemma>, ironically for <foreign lang="la">invasit</foreign>, implying that Chrysogonus himself gave that reason for the request.  <gloss>Since, <emph>as he says</emph>, he has seized upon</gloss>, etc. Cf. <foreign lang="la">quod adeptus est</foreign>, below, indicative.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">obstare atque officere</lemma>, i.e. bars his way to it, hinders his enjoyment of it. The same words are in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 112">112</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl>. Cf., on the other hand, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl> sub fin., <foreign lang="la">adiutores ad hanc praedam</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">damnato et eiecto</lemma>, condemned, and hence thrust out (of his property). Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 23">23</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">eicit domo atque focis</foreign>, and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>. Loss of property would be, not the regular penalty of a condemnation for parricide, but a sure consequence of it. Others supply <foreign lang="la">de civitate</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">eiecto</foreign>, since Sex. Roscius, if he foresaw his condemnation, could go into exile before sentence was passed.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per scelus</lemma>, i.e. by having the late owner's name placed on the proscription list : <ref n="3" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 3</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id per luxuriam effundere</lemma>, sarcastically for <foreign lang="la">id tuto habere</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui se pungit</lemma>, instead of the regular forms <foreign lang="la">eum pungit</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">se pungat</foreign>. The relative clause <foreign lang="la">qui se . . . pungit</foreign> seems to form a part of and coalesce with the main sentence, = <foreign lang="la">se pungentem</foreign>. Examples, which are rare in Cicero, occur chiefly in his later writings : cf. de Inv. 1.55, <foreign lang="la">Epaminondas ei qui sibi ex lege praetor successerat</foreign> (= <foreign lang="la">successori suo</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">exercitum non tradidit</foreign>. Verr. 2. 5, 128, <foreign lang="la">Dexo hic non quae privatim sibi eripuisti . . . flagitat</foreign>. Hor. Sat. 1.1. 1, <foreign lang="la">Qui fit, Maecenas, ut nemo, quam sibi sortem seu ratio dederit seu fors obiecerit, illa contenti vivat?</foreign> Madvig, &sect; 490, Obs. 3.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut evellatis postulat, ut</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">ut . . . ut</foreign> are in different senses; <gloss>asks you to pluck out . . . in order that you may profess yourselves . . . </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praedam</lemma>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 86">86</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 107">107</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <pb n="4"/> <milestone n=" 7" unit="section"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si . . . videtur</lemma>, ironical: the sense is, 'If you consider <emph>that</emph> to be a fair and honourable demand, I will in my turn bring a demand before you, and a much fairer one. 
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nostris</lemma>. Cicero frequently identifies himself with his clicnt : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 32">32</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">patrem meum</foreign>, etc. ; see note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">petat</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>, note; and cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">impetum facit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sceleri</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 1">1</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">et in causa</lemma>.  <foreign lang="la">Et</foreign> is very rare with the third member in a series : here the first two, being in antithesis with each other, may be regarded as forming one.  Or<gloss> the third is the resultant of the first two </gloss> (Richter). </p>
</div2>
<milestone n="III" unit="chapter"/>

<div2 type="section" n="8">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causa criminis</lemma>, <gloss>grounds for an accusation.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">illi</lemma> : <foreign lang="la">ille</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">iste</foreign> in judicial speeches mean <gloss>my opponent</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">hic</foreign>, <gloss>my client</gloss>, the man near me. <foreign lang="la">Ille</foreign> implies that the orator is speaking to the audience <emph>of</emph> his adversary ; <foreign lang="la">iste</foreign>, that he is speaking <emph>at</emph> his adversary.  <foreign lang="la">Ille</foreign> is said here (and <foreign lang="la">illorum</foreign> below), not <foreign lang="la">isti</foreign>, because Cicero is addressing the jurors direct. Cf. pro Sulla, 34.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non nihil tamen ... secuti</lemma>, <gloss>to have been guided by some sort of evidence.</gloss>  In &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 34">34</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quid vos sequi conveniat</foreign> =<gloss> what you ought to keep in view, keep your attention on.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">non nihil tamen</foreign> ; here, as also in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 33">33</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 104">104</bibl>, the <gloss>although</gloss> idea wanted before <foreign lang="la">tamen</foreign> is left entirely to the reader's sense ; <gloss>little though it be, <emph>yet</emph> not nothing.</gloss>  Caesar has a somewhat similar use of the word, in B.G. 1. 32, <foreign lang="la">quod reliquis tamen fugae facultas daretur, Sequanis vera</foreign>, etc. = <gloss>at least</gloss>. Cf. Thuc. III. 49, where <foreign lang="greek">o(/mws</foreign>, refers back to c. 36.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in deferendo nomine</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">in accusando</foreign>. The <foreign lang="la">delatio nominis</foreign>, or giving notice of an accusation to the presiding magistrate in the appropriate <foreign lang="la">quaestio</foreign> (<ref n="12" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 12</ref>), was followed by the <foreign lang="la">nominis receptio</foreign>, or entry of the accused's name by the Praetor on the list of <foreign lang="la">rei</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">recusamus</lemma>, <gloss>protest against.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">libidini</lemma>, ' will and pleasure.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si hoc pugnatur</lemma>, <gloss>if this be the object of the contest </gloss> ; differing little from <foreign lang="la">si aliud agitur nihil</foreign>  Cf. Phil. 10. 22, <foreign lang="la">qui id pugnant id agunt</foreign>; VIII. 8, <foreign lang="la">M. Antonius id molitur, id pugnat</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vos idoneos habitos</lemma>. The infin. is the regular construction after <foreign lang="la">dignum est</foreign> (= <foreign lang="la">decet</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">aequum est</foreign>, Cic. Tusc. II. 14) and <foreign lang="la">indignum est</foreign>. Madvig, &sect; 398a.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per sententias iusque iurandum</lemma>, <gloss>through your verdict, which you give on oath </gloss> (&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 101">101</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 140">140</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 152">152</bibl>): cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 9">9</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">natura pudorque</foreign>, <gloss>natural modesty </gloss> ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 123">123</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">vestris ingeniis coniecturaeque committo</foreign> ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 149">149</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">aetas et pudor</foreign>. These passages show that in <emph>hendiadys</emph> (the socalled <foreign lang="greek">e(/n dia\ duoi=n</foreign>) the first member has a complete sense in itself, but is followed by a second, equally able to stand alone, which specifies the sense more clearly. But whether the first or second gives the leading idea is not always clear. De Or. I. 33, <foreign lang="la">clamores et admirationes</foreign> may mean <gloss>admiring shouts</gloss>, or <gloss>boisterous admiration.</gloss> Dr&auml;ger, Lat. Synt. II. p.17.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui ex civitate</lemma> : the antecedent to <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign> is <foreign lang="la">his</foreign> two lines below. in senatum. Sulla had filled up the number of the Senate by the addition of 300 equites, whom he allowed the assembly of the Tribes to nominate.  Mommsen, Rom. Hist. III. p. 359.) The remaining senators, too, had been chosen indirectly by the people, for they had entered the Senate as curule magistrates.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">propter severitatem</lemma>, <ref n="13" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 13</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">postulare</lemma> is not an infin. of indignant exclamation, but depends on <foreign lang="la">indignissimum est</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">homines sicarios</lemma>. The addition of <foreign lang="la">homines</foreign> expresses contempt : <gloss>a set of cut-throat fellows.</gloss> Cf. Ter. Adelph. I. 2. 31, <foreign lang="la">Tu homo adigis me ad insaniam.</foreign>
<pb n="5"/></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="9">
<milestone n="IV" unit="chapter"/>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commode</lemma>, <gloss>in a manner appropriate to, worthy of, my subject</gloss>, so that the speech may correspond to the <foreign lang="la">atrocitas rerum.</foreign> Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 33">33</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">laudare satis commode ;</foreign> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 61">61</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">causam si non commode, at</foreign> <foreign lang="la">libere dici</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">graviter</lemma>, <gloss>impressively.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">natura pudorque</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, note.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="10">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fide</lemma>, fidelity to their oath as jurors.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non spero</lemma>, <gloss>I will not hope</gloss>, <gloss>I do not expect.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">Spero</foreign>, of unwelcome expectation, is only found with a negative in Cicero; without a negative only in poets and later writers.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">perferam</lemma>, <gloss>carry through.</gloss> For <foreign lang="la">et</foreign> (where we should say <gloss>but</gloss>) after <foreign lang="la">non deficiam</foreign>, see Madvig, &sect; 433, Obs. 2.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum fide</lemma>, <gloss>trustfully.</gloss> &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 30">30</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">cum fide defendat</foreign>, is different = in an honest, conscientious way.'
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iudex</lemma> : see <ref n="13" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 13</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rei publicae</lemma> : cf. esp. c. LII. and c. LIII.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">impertias</lemma>, a variety for <foreign lang="la">praebeas</foreign> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 3">3</bibl>.
<pb n="6"/>
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="11">
 <milestone n="v" unit="chapter"/> 
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mortales</lemma> in Cicero = <foreign lang="la">homines</foreign> only in connection with <foreign lang="la">omnes</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">multi</foreign> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">omnibus mortalibus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inter sicarios</lemma>, <ref n="12" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 12</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">committitur</lemma>, <gloss>is held, set on foot</gloss> : cf. <foreign lang="la">committere ludos, spectaculum, pugnam, agona musicum</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum interea . . . factae sunt</lemma>, <gloss>while in the meantime . . </gloss> This phrase is regularly followed by the indicative ; cf. Verr. 2. 5. 162, <foreign lang="la">caedebatur virgis . . . cum interea nullus gemitus audiebatur</foreign>. It may be classified with the <gloss>inverted </gloss> <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> and indicative, as in Caes. B.G. 7.26, <foreign lang="la">jamque hoc facere apparabant, cum matres procurrerunt</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sanguine</lemma>, <gloss>bloodshed </gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">dignissimum</foreign>, <gloss>fully worthy</gloss>, corresponding to the greatness of the crimes : cf. just below, <foreign lang="la">ut quam acerrime maleficia vindicetis</foreign>, and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 9">9</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">satis commode dicere</foreign>, note. The reading of the MSS. is corrupt and meaningless. Halm calls the reading in the text <gloss>only a makeshift.</gloss></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="12">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vociferatione</lemma>, i.e. an appeal for due severity.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causam dicimus</lemma>, <gloss>who are answering to a charge.</gloss> The phrase here suits Cicero both as <foreign lang="la">patronus</foreign> and as identified with his client : cf. &sect;5.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui vester animus sit</lemma>, <gloss>your real disposition</gloss>, the free manifestation of which would put a check on deeds of violence.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">prorumpere</lemma> (for which <foreign lang="la">proruptura esse</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">prorumpere posse</foreign> would be expected) =<gloss> is on the way to break forth.</gloss> The construction is irregular, and so rare as to render the reading doubtful. The pres. may be rhetorical : is even now breaking all bounds ' Richter ; who compares Cic. Ep. XII. 6.2, <foreign lang="la">si Brutus conservatus erit, vicimus</foreign>, where the perf. instead of the fut. is forcible.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hic in foro</lemma>.  "The Praetor had his seat (<foreign lang="la">sella curulis</foreign>) on a raised platform (<foreign lang="la">tribunal</foreign>), under the open air, in the forum ; the jurors and clerks sat around him on low benches (<foreign lang="la">subsellia</foreign>) ; lower down (<foreign lang="la">ante pedes vestros</foreign>), perhaps on the ground itself, stood <foreign lang="la">subsellia</foreign> for the two contending parties, separated from one another ; in a circle around stood the public (<foreign lang="la">corona</foreign>) who were interested in the case." (Richter.)</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="13">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">accusant ei</lemma>, etc. Note the fine succession of antitheses.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quibus bono fuit</lemma> : cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 84">84</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 86">86</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">cui bono</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum praesidio</lemma>. So Cicero calls the friends (<foreign lang="la">advocati</foreign>) who had appeared with him in court.


<pb n="7"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">poscit</lemma> (sc. <foreign lang="la">in judicium</foreign>), demands for trial and punishment ; cf. pro Sest. 46, <foreign lang="la">cum ob hasce causas me unum deposcerent</foreign>. Liv. 9. 26. 17, <foreign lang="la">poscere reum</foreign> = to demand a man for accusation. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="14">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Atque</lemma>, etc., marks the transition to the <foreign lang="la">narratio</foreign> (account of the facts of the case).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">res quem ad modum gesta sit</lemma>, <gloss>the particulars of the affair.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="15">
<milestone n="VI" unit="chapter"/>

<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">municeps</lemma>, a citizen of a <foreign lang="la">municipium</foreign>, which term at this date meant a town governed by its own magistrates, and possessing the full rights of Roman citizenship ; the latter having been granted to all Italian towns during the Social War by the <foreign lang="la">lex Iulia</foreign>, B.C. 90, and the lex <foreign lang="la">Plautia Papiria</foreign>, B.C. 89.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hospitiis florens . . . nobilissimorum</lemma>.  Note the emphasis falling on the last word ; it enhances the shamefulness of inscribing a friend of Sulla's own party on the proscription list. Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">nobilitatis</foreign>. On <foreign lang="la">hospitium</foreign>, see Ramsay, Rom. Ant. pp.115-6.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Metellis</lemma> : &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl> ; <ref n="1" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 1</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">gratia</lemma>, <gloss>in acknowledgment of</gloss>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">honoris causa</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">itaque</lemma> . . . reliquit : the force of <foreign lang="la">itaque</foreign> can be shown by a paraphrase ; <gloss><emph>thus it was</emph> that he could leave to his son what is now the only advantage the son retains</gloss>, Viz. friendship with people of good position.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">domestici praedones</lemma>, i.e. who were members of his own family (<foreign lang="la">domus</foreign>) : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="16">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">is</lemma>, the elder Roscius. 
</p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum fuisset</lemma>, <gloss>since he had been</gloss>, or <gloss>having been . </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tumultu</lemma>, in the civil war between Marius and Sulla ; properly, <gloss>alarm of war.</gloss> The word was used of any sudden outbreak of hostilities that caused confusion and alarm in Rome : cf. Phil. VIII. 3.
</p>
<p> <pb n="8"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pro eorum honestate</lemma>, <gloss>in defence of their distinguished position.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">propter quos</lemma>, <gloss>to whom he owed it that </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 63">63</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">numerabatur</lemma> : indicative, being Cicero's own statement rather than part of Roscius' thought.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">proscriberentur</lemma>, <ref n="2" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 2</ref>. Join <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">homines . . . ei qui,</lemma> as subject to <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">proscriberentur</lemma> and <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">caperentur</lemma>.  <foreign lang="la">Caperentur</foreign> implies the capture of enemies while in flight after a battle. Yet not <foreign lang="la">hostes</foreign>, nor even <foreign lang="la">inimici</foreign>, but <foreign lang="la">adversarii</foreign> (<gloss>men of the opposite party</gloss>) follows. This brings out the severity of Sulla's measures ; otherwise <foreign lang="la">raperentur</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">conquirerentur</foreign> would be expected rather than <foreign lang="la">caperentur</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">frequens</lemma>. For the adj. in apposition, instead of the adverb, see Madvig, &sect; 300 c, and cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 18">18</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">assiduus in praediis esset</foreign> ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 92">92</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">Romae assiduus fuerit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut</lemma>, <gloss>so that.</gloss>
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="17">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">veteres inimicitiae</lemma>, <ref n="1" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 1</ref>. For the plural, see Madvig, &sect; 51 d.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quorum alterum</lemma>, T. Roscius Magnus.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sedere in accusatorum subselliis</lemma>. Cicero repeatedly calls attention to this (&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 84">84</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 104">104</bibl>), perhaps in order to attach to Magnus, in case he should wish to give evidence afterwards, the imputation of being prejudiced against the accused. The examination of witnesses followed next after the speeches for the prosecution and defence.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possidere audio</lemma>, <ref n="n.,26" targOrder="U">Introd. note 26</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nobilis</lemma>, the standing epithet for famous artists or performers : cf. Curtius, IX. 29. 16, <foreign lang="la">pugil nobilis. Gladiator</foreign>, figurat. for <foreign lang="la">sicarius</foreign>. This explains what kind of victories are denoted by <foreign lang="la">palmae</foreign> (the general term for tokens of victory in every kind of contest), viz. <gloss>successful deeds of violence </gloss> : cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 84">84</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 100">100</bibl> ; Auct. ad Her. IV. &sect; 51, <foreign lang="la">sanguinolenta palma, crudelissima victoria potiti</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hic</lemma>, not <foreign lang="la">iste</foreign>, although said of Cicero's adversary (cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl> sub init.), because Magnus, who was present, is meant, as opposed to the absent Capito. So &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 113">113</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">hic discipulus</foreign> : cf. in Verr. II. 4, &sect; 7. 
</p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad eum lanistam</lemma>, <gloss>to the other (Capito) as trainer. </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hanc pugnam</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">caedem Roscii</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quique . . . esset</lemma>, <gloss>and though he was . . . </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod sciam</lemma>, added ironically, <gloss>so far as I know </gloss>, : i.e. <gloss>I <emph>know of</emph> no other murder committed by him, and must therefore conclude that previously he was only a <foreign lang="la">tiro gladiatorius </foreign></gloss>; hinting that Magnus may have committed many other crimes which Cicero had not heard of. For the subj. <foreign lang="la">sciam</foreign>, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>,
</p>
<p> <foreign lang="la">quod possim</foreign> ; and Madvig, &sect; 364, Obs. 2. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="18">
<milestone n="VII" unit="chapter"/>

<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum hic Sex. Roscius . . . cum hic filius</lemma>: both phrases refer to the son. The second <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> is not co-ordinate with but subordinate to the first : <gloss>while Sextus the son was at Ameria . . . through being constantly present on the estates </gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ipse autem</lemma>, <gloss>whereas the father (<foreign lang="la">ipse</foreign>) was often in Rome.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">Ipse</foreign> is a good emendation for MSS. <foreign lang="la">iste</foreign>, which would mean Magnus ; we have just been told that he was in Rome.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rei familiari</lemma>, <gloss>management of the property </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 43">43</bibl>.


<pb n="9"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad balneas Pallacinas</lemma>, <ref n="n.7" targOrder="U">Introd. note 7</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad quem suspicio pertineat</lemma>, <gloss>on whom the suspicion of the deed falls.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">culpae</lemma> may be genit. or dat. : cf. pro Sulla, &sect; 70, <foreign lang="la">huic adfines sceleri</foreign> ; and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. Sul. 17">17</bibl> of the same speech, <foreign lang="la">huius adfines suspicionis</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iudicatote</lemma> : <foreign lang="la">imperativus permissivus</foreign>, <gloss>Declare him, for all I care </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 57">57</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">si voletis . . . latratote</foreign> ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 109">109</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">iudicatote</foreign> The <gloss>permissive </gloss> sense seems due to the more formal commanding tone of the imperat. forms in <foreign lang="la">-to</foreign> : cf. pro Balb. &sect; 36, <foreign lang="la">verbi genus hoc <emph>conservanto</emph> . . . imperantis est, non precantis</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <milestone n=" 19" unit="section"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nuntiat</lemma>, <gloss>brings the news</gloss>, intrans., sc. <foreign lang="la">occisum esse Roscium</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tenuis</lemma>, <gloss>poor</gloss>, and so accessible to bribes.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Titi Roscii</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">Magni</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">et nuntiat</lemma>, a rhetorical repetition, = <gloss>and that, too </gloss> : cf. de Imp. Pomp. &sect; 7, <foreign lang="la">regnat et ita regnat</foreign> ; de Imp. Pomp. &sect; 10, <foreign lang="la">dicam et ita dicam</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inimici</lemma>, i.e. the enemy of the murdered man.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">post horam primam noctis</lemma>. The Romans, both in summer and winter, divided both day and night into twelve <foreign lang="la">horae</foreign> : thus in summer the twelve <foreign lang="la">horae nocturnae</foreign> must be shorter than the twelve <foreign lang="la">horae diurnae</foreign>, and in winter <foreign lang="la">vice versa</foreign>. The season when the murder was committed is shown by the word <foreign lang="la">nocturnis</foreign>, which is added to enhance the speed of the journey, and must therefore mean <foreign lang="la">short</foreign> hours, i.e. hours of a summer night.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sex et quinquaginta milia passuum</lemma>, 56 Roman miles =51 1/4 English.
</p>
<p> <pb n="82"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cisiis</lemma>: <foreign lang="la"><gloss>cisium genus vehiculi Gallici</gloss>,</foreign> Schol. The plural (cf. Phil. 2. 77, <foreign lang="la">cisio ad urbem advectus</foreign>) shows that the messenger took fresh carriages at the different stations. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="20">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quadriduo quo</lemma>, <gloss>within four days after that</gloss>, etc., abbrev. for <foreign lang="la">quadriduo a die quo</foreign>; so Halm; but Madvig, &sect; 276, Obs. 4, says, <gloss>in the course of the same four days during which these things took place</gloss> : cf. Ter. And. 1.1.77, <foreign lang="la">In paucis diebus, quibus haec acta sunt, Chrysis moritur</foreign>. Cf. below, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 105">105</bibl>. Suet. Iul. &sect; 35, <foreign lang="la">quem . . . quatuor quibus in conspecturn venit horis . . . profligavit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Volaterras</lemma>, <ref n="n.,14" targOrder="U">Introd. note 14</ref>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 105">105</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ad Volaterras</foreign>, which is more accurate, as denoting the <foreign lang="la">vicinity</foreign> of the town. Madvig  232.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fundos</lemma>. Digest. lib. L. 16.211, <foreign lang="la">ager cum aedificio fundus dicitur</foreign>; i.e. <foreign lang="la">fundus</foreign> = an estate on which there is a building, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">ager</foreign>, on which there is none.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Tiberim tangunt</lemma>: an advantage. Pliny (Ep. 5.6.12) says of his villa, <foreign lang="la">medios ille (Tiberis) agros secat, navium patiens, omnesque fruges devehit in urbem</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inopia</lemma>, <gloss>helplessness.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">splendidus</lemma>, the honorary epithet of the equestrian order, to which the murdered Roscius from the amount of his property belonged. Cf. Fin. 2. 18.58, <foreign lang="la">C. Plotius, eques Romanus splendidus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">incautum</lemma>, <gloss>unsuspicious</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ne diutius teneam</lemma>. Without <foreign lang="la">vos</foreign>, as in Verr. 1.1.34: cf. ib. Iv. 104, <foreign lang="la">ne multis morer</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">societas coitur</lemma>, between Chrysog., Magnus, and Capito; cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 28">28</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 58">58</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 60">60</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>.  The last two passages imply that there were other associates as well. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="21">
<milestone n="VIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mentio</lemma>: &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>; <ref n="n.,20" targOrder="U">Introd. note 20</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nomen refertur</lemma>: as Catiline had the name of his brother, whom he had murdered, subsequently placed on the proscription list (<foreign lang="la">tabulas</foreign>, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 26">26</bibl>), in order to avoid a prosecution for murder. The whole property of a proscribed person necessarily fell in to the State.
</p>
<p> <pb n="10"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">manceps</lemma>: in its original sense. Festus, p. 151, <foreign lang="la">manceps dicitur qui quid a populo</foreign> (i.e. from the State) <foreign lang="la">emit conducitve</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hodie</lemma>, <gloss>even now</gloss>, = <foreign lang="la">hodie quoque</foreign>, or the later phrase <foreign lang="la">hodieque</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nomine Chrysogoni</lemma>, as his <foreign lang="la">procurator</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 23">23</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">impetum facit</lemma>, <gloss>falls upon,  seizes on</gloss>, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 137">137</bibl> ; a stronger term for <foreign lang="la">occupet</foreign>, marking the act of violence which it was in the orator's view : cf. <foreign lang="la">invadere</foreign>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 13">13</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 23">23</bibl>. The following words <foreign lang="la">Haec bona</foreign>, etc., which would be expected above after <foreign lang="la">manceps fit Chrysog</foreign>., seem interpolated from &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">imprudente L. Sulla</lemma>.  With this and the following passage, cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 127">127</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 131">131</bibl>. Cicero takes care to say nothing against the dictator.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="22">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quae praeterita sunt</lemma> sc. the wounds inflicted on the State in the civil war.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sanet</lemma>: a better reading is Prof. Clark's <foreign lang="la">reparet</foreign>, in much the same sense.  <foreign lang="la">Reparet</foreign>, rhyming with <foreign lang="la">praeparet</foreign>, would have pleased Cicero at this period (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 3">3</bibl>, note), and is thus confirmed.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praeparet</lemma>: according to usage this verb should here mean <gloss>prepare what is coming</gloss> rather than <gloss>prepare <emph>for</emph> what is coming.</gloss>  But Cic. probably meant no more than the latter.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pacis constituendae</lemma>.  There is a reference here to Sulla's great constitutional changes, which had accompanied the conclusion of peace after the civil war.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rationem</lemma>, properly <gloss>making calculations for</gloss>, translate, has the control over the arrangements for peace, and the power for waging war.'
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si non animadvertat</lemma> follows from <foreign lang="la">neque enim mirum</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aliquid</lemma>. After <foreign lang="la">si, nisi, ne, num</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">quis</foreign> is more usual than <foreign lang="la">aliquis</foreign>; but the latter is found after <foreign lang="la">si</foreign>, especially if an emphasis rests on the pronoun, i.e. <gloss>something</gloss>, as opposed to <gloss>much</gloss>, <gloss>little</gloss>, <gloss>all</gloss>, and the like.  (Madvig &sect; 493, Obs. 1.) The emphasized <foreign lang="la">aliquid</foreign>, and the subj. <foreign lang="la">animadvertat</foreign>, put the case in the mildest way; <gloss>what wonder if there were <emph>something</emph> which he failed to notice?</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">occupationem</lemma>, <gloss>his being engrossed</gloss>, i.e. the time when he was engrossed. Many verbals in <foreign lang="la">-io</foreign> take a passive sense: Verr. 1.1. &sect; 83, <foreign lang="la">circumsessionis tuae</foreign> = <gloss> the fact of your being surrounded</gloss> ; pro Sest. &sect; 47, <foreign lang="la">spolatio</foreign> =<gloss> the fact or condition of having been spoiled</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">infractio</foreign>, <gloss>the state of being broken.</gloss> N&auml;gelsbach, Lat. Stil. &sect; 59 a 2.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">observent</lemma>, <gloss>look out for.</gloss> Virg. Georg. 4. 513, <foreign lang="la">Quos durus arator observans . . . detraxit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">despexerit</lemma>, <gloss>glance aside</gloss> <foreign lang="la">= oculos dejecerit</foreign>:  cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 131">131</bibl>. Similarly <foreign lang="la">deversor</foreign> = to turn aside off the road into an inn.

</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">felix</lemma>. It was known that Sulla had taken the surname of <foreign lang="la">Felix</foreign>, though it had not yet come into general use.  Vell. Pat. 2.27.5, <foreign lang="la">occiso enim eo</foreign> (sc. <foreign lang="la">C. Mario adulescente</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">Felicis nomen</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">Sulla</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">adsumpsit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">neminem . . . neque . . . neque</lemma>.  For the double negative, the first, a general one, not destroying the subordinate ones, see Roby 2246, and cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 73">73</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 96">96</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 139">139</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 146">146</bibl>. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="23">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">interea</lemma> brings the events graphically before the hearers' eyes: <gloss>Meantime (while I am digressing), T. Roscius comes to Ameria</gloss>, etc. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vir optimus</lemma>: ironical, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 104">104</bibl>. procurator.  "<foreign lang="la">Procurator est qui aliena negotia mandatu domini administrat</foreign>," Ulpianus. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nondum etiam</lemma>: cf. Cat. 1.10, <foreign lang="la">vixdum etiam</foreign>; Verr. Iv. 9, <foreign lang="la">nihildum etiam</foreign>. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">omnia iusta solvisset</lemma>.  Funeral ceremonies lasted nine days after the interment , and ended with a repast (<foreign lang="la">novemdialia</foreign>) placed beside the tomb, as an offering to the <foreign lang="la">Manes</foreign>. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">disque</lemma>: without a preposition, as the persons stood for the place.  On the other hand, pro Quinct. &sect; 83, <foreign lang="la">iam de fundo expulsus, iam a suis dis penatibus praeceps eiectus</foreign>.


<pb n="11"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui fuisset egentissimus</lemma>, not <gloss>he who would have been very miserly. . .</gloss> but <gloss>since he had been. . .</gloss> or, <gloss>having been . . .</gloss> He accorded with the usual rule ; first miserly with what was his own; then lavish with what was another's.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">insolens</lemma>, <gloss>arrogant</gloss>  i.e. lavish, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">egentissimus.</foreign> Phil. 9. &sect; 13, <foreign lang="la">mirifice Servius maiorum continentiam diligebat, huius saeculi insolentiam vituperabat</foreign>. De Orat. 2.84. &sect; 342, <foreign lang="la">insolentem in pecunia</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">auctione</lemma>, <ref n="n.,29" targOrder="U">Introd. note 29</ref>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="24">
<milestone n="IX" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iter ad sepulcrum</lemma>. 'The Romans frequently built tombs for themselves and their families on their estates, and, if they sold such estates, used to stipulate for the right of free access to the <foreign lang="la">sepulcra.</foreign> Unless such a stipulation were made in the deed of sale, the seller lost all right of access. So material an encroachment as this on the right of property was named <foreign lang="la">servitus</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">fundus servit</foreign>) ; by <foreign lang="la">servitus itineris</foreign> or simply <foreign lang="la">iter</foreign>, as here, was meant that the owner conceded to the former owner or to any interested person the right of walking, riding, or being carried over the land to the <foreign lang="la">sepulcrum; viae servitus</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">via</foreign> was the right of driving thither, and included the <foreign lang="la">iter</foreign>. The younger Roscius could not retain even the relic of his <foreign lang="la">patrimonium</foreign> usually preserved, the <foreign lang="la">iter ad sepulcrum patrium in fundo</foreign>
</p>
<p> <pb n="85"/> <foreign lang="la">alieno.'</foreign> Osenbr&uuml;ggel).  It was also customary among the Greeks, when land changed owners, to keep the grave as a family possession, and allow free access to relatives.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">reliquisset</lemma>: subjunctive, being what they were thinking; virtually orat. obl.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">flagitiosa</lemma>. It was so, because it depended on the murdered man's name being added to the list of proscribed after the right time.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possessio</lemma>, <gloss>seizure</gloss>, implying violence, in the sense of <foreign lang="la">possidere</foreign>, <gloss>to take possession of</gloss>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 23">23</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iactantem</lemma>, <gloss>pluming himself</gloss>; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dominantem</lemma>, <gloss>playing the proprietor.</gloss> 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="25">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">decurionum . . . decem primi</lemma>, <ref n="n.,31" targOrder="U">Introd. note 31</ref>. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fit ut proficiscantur</lemma>, etc.  Note the pres. tense, carried graphically into the subordinate clauses : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 110">110</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">monet ut provideat, ne . . . agatur</foreign>; but below, <foreign lang="la">allegat, qui peterent</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">scelere</lemma>: &sect;7, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">decretum decurionum</lemma>. Omitted by Cicero in the published edition of the speech.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">intellegitur</lemma>, <gloss>it <emph>can</emph> be understood</gloss>, in English ; sc. from what happened to the embassy.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">allegat qui peterent</lemma>: here the historic present is strictly treated and has a historic tense after it. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="26">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">autem</lemma>, <gloss>but</gloss> (though he professed such readiness to serve them).  <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">antiqui</lemma>, <gloss>men of the old stamp.</gloss> Pl. Ep. 11.9, <foreign lang="la">vir sanctus, anitiquus</foreign>.


<pb n="12"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fingerent</lemma>, <gloss>formed their ideas of.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vacua</lemma>, <gloss>unoccupied</gloss>; as they would be, if the forcible appropriation were made null and void.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">adpromitteret</lemma>, <gloss>added his promise</gloss> to that of Chrysogonus: a <foreign lang="greek">a(/pac lego/menon</foreign>. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">re inorata</lemma>, <gloss>without getting their case heard</gloss>; from the old meaning of <foreign lang="la">orare</foreign> = <foreign lang="la">agere</foreign>, to plead, whence <foreign lang="la">orator</foreign> in early Latin = <foreign lang="la">legatus</foreign>, one who pleaded or transacted an affair for the State. 
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aliquanto lentius nihil agere</lemma>: some critics formerly omitted <foreign lang="la">nihil</foreign>, not appreciating the vigour of the phrase <gloss>did nothing, trifled, still more indolently.</gloss> It should be retained. Without <foreign lang="la">nihil</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">agere</foreign>= <gloss>behaved</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <pb n="86"/>	 <milestone n=" 27" unit="section"/> </p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de amicorum cogn. sententia</lemma>. Important family affairs were laid before a <foreign lang="la">consilium cognatorum et amicorum</foreign>, for their consideration and decision.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Caeciliam</lemma>: see below, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 147">147</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">honoris causa</lemma>: &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 6">6</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">usus erat plurimum</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">familiariter</foreign>: cf. ad Att. xvi. 5.3, <foreign lang="la">Cn. Lucceius, qui multum utitur Bruto</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">etiam nunc</lemma>, i.e. in these degenerate days, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">antiqui</foreign>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 26">26</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">exempli causa</lemma>, <gloss>to serve as a pattern</gloss>; not <gloss>for instance</gloss>, which is in Latin <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">velut</foreign>, or "<foreign lang="la">exempli causa</foreign> with some such verb as <foreign lang="la">nominare, ponere, afferre.</foreign>"  (Richter.)
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">officii</lemma>, <gloss>sense of duty</gloss>, i.e. conscientiousness, obedience to duty; (sc. duty towards Sex. Roscius, in consideration of her friendship with his father).  For the meaning of <foreign lang="la">officii</foreign>, cf. Tusc. IV. 28.61, <foreign lang="la">Si quis aegre ferat, nihil in se esse officii</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hospiti</lemma>, because <foreign lang="la">pater ea usus erat plurimum</foreign>. The <foreign lang="la">hospitium</foreign> of the father had been transmitted to the son: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 106">106</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">diligentia</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">cura</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">vigilantia</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in reos</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">in reorum album</foreign> (list); <foreign lang="la">in proscriptos</foreign> = <foreign lang="la">in proscriptorum tabulas</foreign>. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="28">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut . . . deferrent</lemma>: <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> epexegetic, <gloss>namely that they should</gloss>, etc.; as in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 136">136</bibl>.  Cf. Madvig, &sect; 417, Obs. 2 ad fin.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad eam rem</lemma>, <gloss>for that purpose</gloss>  <foreign lang="la">de ea re</foreign>, as Mr. Stock shows =<gloss>about <emph>a</emph> matter</gloss>, <foreign lang="la">in qua re</foreign> <gloss>in which . . .</gloss>; omit the second <foreign lang="la">re</foreign> in English.  See &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>, first note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">veterem</lemma>, <gloss>trained</gloss> (cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">vetus gladiator</foreign>; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 39">39</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">vetus sicarius</foreign>); i.e. who had often acted as accuser, had had enough practice, and would not scruple as to the evidence he employed.


<pb n="13"/>
 </p><p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">crimine</lemma>. <gloss>by an accusation</gloss>, i.e. since they had no (<emph>real</emph>) charge to bring against him.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tempore ipso pugnarent</lemma>, <gloss>to use the very circumstances as their weapons</gloss>: cf. <ref n="6" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 6</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ita loqui homines</lemma>, <gloss>the fellows talked thus</gloss>; the next seven lines tell us how they talked. <foreign lang="la">homines</foreign> are Magnus, Capito, and Chrysogonus: <foreign lang="la">loqui</foreign> is historic infin.  I follow Prof. Clark in thus interpreting.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">patronos</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 30">30</bibl> sub fin.  societate: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 20">20</bibl> sub fin.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="29">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">atque adeo</lemma> =<foreign lang="la">ac potius</foreign>, as in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 100">100</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 113">113</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">jugulandum</lemma>.  Cicero chooses a word implying judicial murder : cf. Verr. 2.2.26, <foreign lang="la">decretis iugulare</foreign>; pro Mil. &sect; 31, <foreign lang="la">iugulari a vobis</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">iudicibus</foreign>).  Compare the metaphor for an accused man, <foreign lang="la">laqueis legum constrictus</foreign>. 

<milestone n="XI" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">deorumne . . . populine . . . vestramne</lemma>; strictly should be <foreign lang="la">deorumne . . . an . . . an</foreign>.  This is the rhetorical figure called anaphora, repetition, which adds much animation. Cf. Cic. Fin. 1.20, <foreign lang="la">si loca,si fana, si campum, si canes, si equos adamare solemus</foreign>. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="30">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid. . . videtur</lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 118">118</bibl> init.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">infesta</lemma>, <gloss>endangered.</gloss>  Gellius, N.A. 9. 12.2, <foreign lang="la">Infestus et is appellatur, qui malum infert cuipiam, et contra, cui aliunde impendet malum.</foreign> (Richter.)
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut optet</lemma>, <gloss>choose</gloss> : cf. the subst. <foreign lang="la">aptio</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cervices dare</lemma>: cf. pro Mil. &sect; 31, <foreign lang="la">optabilius Miloni fuit dare iugulum P. Clodio</foreign>. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">T. Roscio</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">Magno</foreign>, who was present who had already made his reputation as a <foreign lang="la">sicarius</foreign> (&sect;17); unless <foreign lang="la">Roscius</foreign> should be read, as the <foreign lang="la">praenomen</foreign> is wanting in the MSS.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">insutus in culleum</lemma>, <ref n="10" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 10</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">desunt</lemma>. Cicero had already (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>) said that he is <foreign lang="la">patronus causae</foreign>, <gloss>counsel for the defence </gloss> ; but he could rhetorically disclaim the title, as not being able to protect the accused by personal weight and influence; or, as Halm says, though Cicero was <foreign lang="la">patronus causae</foreign>, he will not reckon himself among the <foreign lang="la">patroni rei</foreign> (of the accused), because he was not in a position to defend him by personal weight.  It is implied in the exaggerated statement <foreign lang="la">desunt</foreign> that many friends of the accused had not ventured to appear with him in court: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 148">148</bibl>.


<pb n="14"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="31">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quoniam quidem</lemma>.  The latter word is adversative, <gloss>however</gloss> ; cf. in Caecil. &sect; 48, <foreign lang="la">quid in dicendo posset, nunquam satis attendi, in clamando quidem video eum esse bene robustum</foreign>. Cf. N&auml;gelsbach, Lat. Stil. &sect; 195 c.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">licet hercules</lemma>. More commonly <foreign lang="la">hercule</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">hercle</foreign>: cf. <foreign lang="la">mehercules, &sect;&sect;</foreign> 58, 151, but Verr. 11.3.145, <foreign lang="la">licet hercules omnes omnia dicant</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">certum est</lemma>, <gloss>it is my resolve</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">libenter</lemma>: in the rare sense of <gloss>according to my inclination</gloss>, <gloss>without constraint.</gloss> The usual sense is <gloss>cheerfully</gloss>, <gloss>gladly.</gloss> Cf. Cic. Parad. 5.34, <foreign lang="la">qui nihil dicit, nihil facit, nihil cogitat denique nisi libenter ac libere</foreign>. <foreign lang="la">Licenter dicere</foreign>, which has been conjectured, is different, being said only of an extravagant and impudent style of speech.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">exsistet</lemma>, <gloss>will occur.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vim adhibere</lemma>, <gloss>have more power over me</gloss>; more freq. in the sense of <foreign lang="la">vim adferre</foreign>. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="32">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dissoluto</lemma>, <gloss>insensate</gloss>, <gloss>heedless</gloss>, implies a higher degree of <foreign lang="la">neglegentia</foreign> : cf. pro Quinct. 38, <foreign lang="la">quis tam dissolutus in re familiari fuisset, quis tam neglegens?</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">patrem meum</lemma>, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl>, the so-called rhetor. figure <foreign lang="greek">proswpopoi/a</foreign>: cf. Cat. 1, &sect; 18, Halm's note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Ut aut iuguletis aut condemnetis</lemma>, to effect either a direct murder or an indirect one (i.e. judicial, through the <foreign lang="la">iudices</foreign>). <foreign lang="la">Condemnare</foreign>, as often, <gloss>to effect a condemnation.</gloss> The verbs have no object, but describe in general terms the aim of Cicero's opponents. Kayser well compares Auct. ad Her. 4. &sect; 19, <foreign lang="la">nam cum istos ut absolvant rogas, ut periurent rogas</foreign>; ib. 4. &sect; 48. Cf. below, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 56">56</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ut significent</foreign>. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="33">
<milestone n="XII" unit="chapter"/>

 

<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">C. Flavius Fimbria</lemma> (<foreign lang="la">ultimae audaciae homo</foreign>, Liv. Epit. 82), a furious partisan of Marius, who had played a prominent part in the massacres carried on by Marius and Cinna in 87 B.C.  In 86 B.C. he was <foreign lang="la">legatus</foreign> to the consul L. Valerius Flaccus, whom the Marian party had sent to Asia to carry on the war against Mithridates and wrest the command from Sulla. Fimbria murdered Valerius and succeeded him in the command. Cf. Liv. Epit. 82.83; Mommsen, Rom. Hist. III. pp.306-311.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nisi</lemma> =<gloss> but</gloss>, <gloss>except</gloss>, is rare except in negative sentences: here <foreign lang="la">quod inter omnes constat</foreign> = <foreign lang="la">quod nemo negat nisi</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Q. Mucius Scaevola</lemma>, distinguished from the Augur by the title <foreign lang="la">Pontifex Maximus</foreign>: famous for his legal learning, and noted as a teacher of law, as an advocate, and as a man of the strictest integrity.  He was murdered in 82 B.C. as a partisan of the aristocracy: cf. Liv. Ep. 86; Mommsen, Rom. Hist. III. p.336. The orator Crassus says of him (ap. Cic. de Orat. I. 180), <foreign lang="la">Q. Scaevola, homo omnium et disciplina iuris civilis eruditissimus et ingenio prudentiaque acutissimus et oratione maxime limatus atque subtilis</foreign>, etc. He was one of Cicero's teachers.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">locus est ut</lemma>, as in Tusc. 4. &sect; 1. So <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> freq. after <foreign lang="la">tempus est</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tamen</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">etiam locus esset</foreign>; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">tamen</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possunt</lemma>, <gloss><emph>could</emph> be said.</gloss> The subjunctive would suit our idiom, the indic. the Latin. Cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 94">94</bibl>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">diem dixit</lemma>; i.e. gave him formal notice that on a certain day he would impeach him before the <foreign lang="la">comitia</foreign>: cf. Halm's note on pro Mu. 36. It is unlikely that the accusation was actually brought.  <foreign lang="la">Accusaturus esset</foreign>, <gloss>why he <emph>intended</emph> to accuse him.</gloss>


<pb n="15"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vivere</lemma>, <gloss>escape with his life.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid . . . accusaturus</lemma>, <gloss>what accusation he was about to bring . . .</gloss>; <foreign lang="la">quid</foreign> is accusative showing <gloss>the extent of action of the verb</gloss>, Roby 1094. Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quid tibi obsto?</foreign> Livy 1.54, <foreign lang="la">omnia poterat</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commode</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 9">9</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut erat furiosus</lemma>, <gloss>like a madman as he was.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">recepisset</lemma>, a term belonging to gladiatorial fights. If the people cried <foreign lang="la">recipe ferrum</foreign>, a conquered gladiator was obliged patiently to receive the death-blow. Fimbria meant that Scaevola ought to have presented his breast like a gladiator to meet the stroke.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quo</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">dicto</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quae tantum potuit</lemma>, literally, <gloss>which had such power, that he, being assassinated, ruined and crushed all men</gloss>, i.e. his assasination had that effect. Cicero means that Scaevola's death virtually brought upon the citizens the coming horrors of the civil war, because he, if anyone, was the man to reconcile the hostile parties, and he wished to do so.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quos . . . iis</lemma> do not denote the same individuals; <foreign lang="la">quos</foreign> = the citizen body generally; <foreign lang="la">ab iis</foreign> = certain persons in that body. "Because he wished to save the citizen-body, he fell a victim to citizens' fury."
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per compositionem</lemma>: cf. 136, <foreign lang="la">componeretur</foreign>. It is not otherwise known that Scaevola wished to mediate between the Marians and Sulla.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="34">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">estne</lemma>=<gloss>is not?</gloss> <foreign lang="la">Ne</foreign>=<foreign lang="la">nonne</foreign>; as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 66">66</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">videtisne</foreign>, and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 113">113</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">itane est?</foreign>  =<gloss> Is it not so?</gloss> These are abbreviated forms, the other clause of the question being understood: <foreign lang="la">estne</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">an non est?</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">videtisne</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">an non videtis?</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in Scaevola</lemma>, <gloss>in the case of Scaevola</gloss>; cf. de Orat. 3.36, <foreign lang="la">se calcaribus in Ephoro, . . . in Theopompo frenis uti solere</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Nam, per deos immortales, quid</lemma>: cf. ad Q. Fr. 1.1.10, <foreign lang="la">Nam quid ego de Gratidio dicam?</foreign> Verr. 2. 2. 160, <foreign lang="la">Nam quid ego de Syracusis loquar</foreign>, etc.  In such places <foreign lang="la">nam</foreign> introduces an additional remark which the speaker wishes to represent as almost too obvious to be mentioned; and it indicates, not the reason of what precedes (as usually), but the reason why what precedes did not iuclude what is now added. <gloss>Is this to be <emph>endured</emph>? (I do not say, to be treated as a justifiable charge, requiring a defence); for</gloss> (<foreign lang="la">nam</foreign>) <gloss>what is there in the case that needs a defence?</gloss> Cf. Long's note on Cic. Lael. &sect; 104.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quae . . . contineat</lemma>, <gloss>on what the whole case rests.</gloss> This is described in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">sin aliud agitur nihil</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid sequi</lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">secuti</foreign>, note.  De Invent. 1.22, <foreign lang="la">certum quiddam destinatur auditori, in quo animum debeat habere occupatum</foreign>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="35">
<milestone n="XIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p>This sec. contains the <foreign lang="la">partitio</foreign> (enumeration of topics to be discussed; see de Invent. 1.22).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">crimen adversariorum</lemma>, etc. It is a striking illustration of Cicero's times, that he speaks of the boldness and power of his opponents in the same breath with the charge itself.


<pb n="16"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="36">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid igitur est</lemma>; as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quid ergo est?</foreign> a phrase limiting what has just been said; in sense =<foreign lang="la">sed</foreign>. (Richter.) <foreign lang="la">non eodem modo</foreign>, i.e. (<foreign lang="la">dicam equidem de his rebus sed</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">non eodem modo</foreign>, not at the same length, <foreign lang="la">de omnibus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">primo quoque tempore</lemma>, <gloss>at the very first opportunity</gloss>, <gloss>the sooner the better.</gloss> 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="37">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">occidisse. - - arguitur</lemma>; the <foreign lang="la">propositio</foreign>, <gloss>allegation</gloss>, of the accusers.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">complexa</lemma>, in a passive sense.  We may retain this reading because Priscian (8.16, and 11.29) quotes the passage thus, as an example of the passive use of deponent verbs.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vultu saepe laeditur pietas</lemma>.  Mr. Stock translates, <gloss>Filial respect is often violated by a look.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cogebant</lemma>. The indicative is used, as if the phrase were <foreign lang="la">debebat mori</foreign>; cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 94">94</bibl>, etc. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="38">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">exstitit</lemma>, <gloss>has appeared.</gloss> Halm suggests the pres. <foreign lang="la">exsistit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">immanemque</lemma>, as opp. to <foreign lang="la">humana natura</foreign>, <gloss>brutish.</gloss> Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 63">63</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">qui tantum immanitate bestias vicerit</foreign>; &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 71">71</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 146">146</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 150">150</bibl>.


<pb n="17"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad perniciem profligata</lemma>, <gloss>sunk down into ruin.</gloss> Gellius, N.A. 15. 5, notices a change in the use of <foreign lang="la">profligare</foreign>, from <gloss>destroy</gloss>, to <gloss>finish off</gloss>, <gloss>get done</gloss>: <foreign lang="la">aedificia, templa esse profligata</foreign>. So Liv. 21. 40, <foreign lang="la">profligare bellum</foreign>. But here we have the earlier sense.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">obiciendi ... causa</lemma>, <gloss>by way of a slanderous reproach</gloss>, as it was the custom for accusers to do.  Cf. pro Murena, &sect; 11, <foreign lang="la">trium partium (accusationis) prima ita fuit infirma et levis, ut illos lex magis quaedam accusatoria quam vera maledicendi facultas . . . dicere coegerit</foreign>. Pro Cluent. &sect; 23, <foreign lang="la">doce quid non modo in criminis, sed in maledicti loco sit obiectum</foreign>. 

<milestone n="xiv" unit="chapter"/> 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="39">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui</lemma> (=<foreign lang="la">qualis</foreign>) <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">homo</lemma>? Cicero proceeds to show that the former life of Sex. Roscius afforded no ground for believing him guilty; a line of argument termed <foreign lang="la">probabile ex vita</foreign> by the rhetoricians.  It continues through &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 39">39</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">annos natus maior quadraginta</lemma>. As <foreign lang="la">natus</foreign> itself has no comparative, <foreign lang="la">natus maior</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">minor</foreign>) was said, and the number of years subjoined either in the abl. (Verr. 2.2.122, <foreign lang="la">ne qui minor triginta annis natus</foreign>) or in the accus., <foreign lang="la">quam</foreign> being omitted as after <foreign lang="la">plus</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">amplius</foreign>) and <foreign lang="la">minus</foreign>. For a third form without <foreign lang="la">natus</foreign>, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 100">100</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">minorem annis sexaginta</foreign>. Madvig, &sect; 306, Obs. 1.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">luxuries. . . luxuria</lemma>, here and in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 75">75</bibl> the word fluctuates from one declension to the other.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ne in convivio . . . interfuisse</lemma>.  Erucius' own statement was less sweeping: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 52">52</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cupiditate</lemma>, <gloss>avarice</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">officio</foreign>, <gloss>observance of duty</gloss>, i.e. of moral duty : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">officii</foreign>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="40">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">obiecit</lemma>; used of feelings which mislead or confound: <foreign lang="la">obicere errorem, rabiem, metum</foreign>, etc. This section begins the <foreign lang="la">probabile ex causa, i.e</foreign>. the inquiry whcther the accused had any motive for committing the crime laid to his charge.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">lustam</lemma>, <gloss>adequate.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">Eam quoque</foreign>, that secondary cause, no less than the primary one.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">necessariis</lemma>, <gloss>cogent.</gloss> 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="41">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eodem</lemma>, to the same point (the so-called <foreign lang="la">probabile ex vita</foreign>), to look for proofs for the statement <foreign lang="la">patri non placebat</foreign>.


<pb n="18"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">unico filio</lemma>: cf. Verr. 2.1.104, <foreign lang="la">is cum haberet unicam filiam</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">is</lemma> with an emphasis : <gloss>he especially.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">constantissimus</lemma> as opposed to <foreign lang="la">amens</foreign>. <foreign lang="la">Constantia</foreign>, steadiness of character, was the effect of <foreign lang="la">sanitas animi</foreign>, the opposite of which is <foreign lang="la">insania</foreign>: Tusc. 3.9, <foreign lang="la">sanitatem animorum positam in tranquillitate quadam constantiaque censebant</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">philosophi</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <milestone n="xv" unit="chapter"/> 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="42">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praedia rustica</lemma>, estates in the country, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">praedia urbana</foreign>, which lay in the precincts of the city.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">relegarat</lemma>. Roman history gives various instances of this kind of penalty: the best known is that of L. Manlius Imperiosus, dictator B.C. 363: Cic. de Off. 3.112, <foreign lang="la">criminabatur etiam</foreign> (M. Pomponius trib. pl.) <foreign lang="la">quod Titum filium, qui postea est Torquatus appellatus</foreign>, ab <foreign lang="la">hominibus relegasset et ruri habitare jussisset</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod... idem</lemma>; i.e. the same difficulty which met Erucius, etc., occurs to me, etc. The next sentence describes it. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="43">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fructuosa</lemma>; cf. Tuac. 11.13, <foreign lang="la">ager quamvis fertilis sine cultura fructuosus esse non potest</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tuenda</lemma>; usually the duty of the <foreign lang="la">villicus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">illius ordinis</lemma>, that to which Sex. Roscius belonged, viz. that of the <foreign lang="la">rustici Romani</foreign>, who managed their estates themselves: <foreign lang="la">rusticanis</foreign>, <gloss>devoted to agriculture.</gloss> Cf. Verr. 2.1. 127, <foreign lang="la">an vero dubitamus, quo ore iste ceteros homines inferiores loco, auctoritate, ordine, quo ore homines rusticanos ex municipiis... solitus sit appellare?</foreign>


<pb n="19"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="44">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in agro</lemma>, <gloss>out in the fields.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aleretur</lemma>, <gloss>should get his food</gloss>, like a dog kept to guard the house.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad villam</lemma>, a colloquial term for <foreign lang="la">in villa</foreign>: cf. pro Tullio 20, <foreign lang="la">dominum esse ad villam</foreign>. Verr. 2.4.47, <foreign lang="la">apud villam</foreign>. Ter. Andr. iv. 4.6, <foreign lang="la">quid turbae apud forum est?</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">certis fundis frui</lemma>, <gloss>have the full enjoyment of certain estates.</gloss> This would be an honourable privilege, since it was one of the rights of <foreign lang="la">patria potestas</foreign> that the son could acquire or hold no property on his own account, unless the father handed over to him a <foreign lang="la">peculium</foreign> or private possession; though the father could withdraw even this whenever he pleased.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rusticana</lemma>, to be joined with <foreign lang="la">relegatio</foreign>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 46">46</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">rus relegasse</foreign> with <foreign lang="la">vita</foreign> understand <foreign lang="la">rustica</foreign>, as in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 48">48</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 75">75</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">amandatio</lemma>, a <foreign lang="greek">a(/pac lego/menon</foreign>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="45">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">usque eo ... non</lemma>, <gloss>so little </gloss>= <foreign lang="la">adeo non</foreign>; for either of which <foreign lang="la">tantum abest ut</foreign> could be said.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod arguas</lemma>, <gloss>what you can allege in proof</gloss>: cf. <foreign lang="la">criminaris</foreign> above, <gloss>allege in accusation</gloss>; Verr. 2.3.37, <foreign lang="la">defendere</foreign>, <gloss>allege in defence.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <pb n="93"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">contra consuetudinem</lemma>, because you represent as <foreign lang="la">novum</foreign> what is done <foreign lang="la">consuetudine</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 44">44</bibl>: <foreign lang="la">contra opiniones om.</foreign>, because no one thinks it exile when a son is sent by his father to take charge of the property. 

<milestone n="xvi" unit="chapter"/> 

<lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">At enim</lemma>, <gloss>But you will say.</gloss> Having shown so far that the <foreign lang="la">ruri esse pati</foreign> implies no ill feeling <emph>in itself</emph>, Cicero now shows that none need be inferred from a contrast with the treatment of the other son.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc</lemma>, what I am going to say. So &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 47">47</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">illud</foreign>, as often, refers to what follows. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="46">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">certo</lemma>, <gloss>known as such.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui animus patrius</lemma>.  Erucius might have known a father's feelings in his own person, and to appeal to him as a father would have been Cicero's most obvious course. But the hit at his parentage serves Cicero as an excuse for the allusion to the comedy. <foreign lang="la">Qui animus . . . esset</foreign>, after <foreign lang="la">posses</foreign>: note the sequence of tenses; we should say, <gloss>what <emph>is</emph> the disposition of parents</gloss>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">humanitatis</lemma>; often nearly = <foreign lang="la">doctrina</foreign>, in the sense of <gloss>high culture</gloss>; but here in contrast to <foreign lang="la">doctrina</foreign> =<gloss> human feeling.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non parum </lemma>= <foreign lang="la">satis</foreign>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 49">49</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">parum miseriae</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">studium doctrinae</lemma>, <gloss>taste for learning.</gloss>  Cicero allows this to his opponent, because he is about to allude to a <foreign lang="la">fabula</foreign>.


<pb n="20"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tandem</lemma>, <gloss>really</gloss>: cf. Ter. And. 5.3.4, <foreign lang="la">Ain tandem?</foreign> <gloss>You don't say so!</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Caecilianus</lemma>.  Caecilius Statius was a famous comic poet (floruit B.C. 168?), placed by some critics above Plautus himself: cf. Volcatius Sedigitus, ap. Gellius, N.A. 15. 24, <foreign lang="la">Caecilio palmam Statio do mimico; Plautus secundus facile exsuperat ceteros</foreign>. The play here alluded to was an adaptation of Menander's <foreign lang="greek">*(/upobolimai=os</foreign> (Subditivus) <foreign lang="greek">h)\ a)groi=kos</foreign>. Probably a father was introduced with two sons, of whom one was supposititious, the other true-born, which latter son the father caused to be brought up in the country.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Eutychus</lemma> from <foreign lang="greek">*)/eutuxos</foreign>, a rare form of <foreign lang="greek">*)eutuxh/s</foreign>.  Plautus uses the form <foreign lang="la">Eutychus</foreign> in the <title>Mercator</title>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut opinor</lemma>: Cicero disclaims accurate knowledge of such trifles.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">alterum in urbe</lemma>, etc.  We may suppose that those who had seen the play would at once feel the absurdity of such an idea.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="47">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quasi vero</lemma>, etc., like the English <gloss>As if it would be difficult!</gloss> abbreviated for <gloss>You speak as if it would be</gloss>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tribules</lemma>. "The Romans did not say <foreign lang="la">contribules</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">concives</foreign> (<foreign lang="greek">sumpoli=tai</foreign>), for men of the same tribe or city, but <foreign lang="la">tribules</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">cives</foreign>. Cf. <foreign lang="la">municeps, &sect;&sect;</foreign> 87, 105. Cicero as a citizen of Arpinum belonged to the <foreign lang="la">tribus Cornelia</foreign>; see Liv. 38. 36."  Osenbr&uuml;ggen.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">assiduos</lemma>; here nearly in its original sense, as iu the XII Tables, of <gloss>settled on the soil</gloss>, <gloss>permanently domiciled.</gloss>  See Mommsen, Rom. Hist. vol. I. p.96, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">homines notos</lemma>, <gloss>men personally known (to myself or others)</gloss>; a vague expression, contrasted with the "<foreign lang="la">homines ficti</foreign>" of the play, but taken up in a different sense in <foreign lang="la">cum nemo . . . magis notus futurus sit</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum  . .  incertum sit . . .  futurus sit . .  intersit</lemma>. Of the three clauses governed by <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign>, only the first gives a reason for <foreign lang="la">odiosum est</foreign>, so that the other two logically should have been independent. Perhaps they were joined to <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> as explaining some such idea as <foreign lang="la">inutile est</foreign>, suggested in <foreign lang="la">odiosum est</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">agro</lemma>, <gloss>district.</gloss> The <foreign lang="la">ager Veiens</foreign> is frequently mentioned: the fame of the city itself did not survive its capture by Rome. Cf. Florus, 1.6.11, <foreign lang="la">Hoc tunc Vei fuere : nunc fuisse quis meminit? quae reliquiae? quod vestigium? laborat annalium fides, ut Veios fuisse credamus</foreign>, <gloss>it is as much as the authority of records can do, to make us believe</gloss>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in alienis personis</lemma>, <gloss>in the characters, parts, of others.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">expressam</lemma>, the technical term for figures moulded or sculptured to represent the full bodily form, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">imagines adumbratae</foreign>, sketches on a flat surface:  hence <foreign lang="la">expressus</foreign> figurat. = <gloss>true to nature, lifelike.</gloss> 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="48">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">age nunc</lemma> marks a transition, as in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 93">93</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 105">105</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 108">108</bibl>; <foreign lang="la">refer</foreign> forms the protasis to <foreign lang="la">intelleges</foreign> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">desinamus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sis</lemma>, a colloquialism for <foreign lang="la">si vis</foreign>, as in pro Mu. 60, <foreign lang="la">cave sis mentiare</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad veritatem</lemma> as opposed to <foreign lang="la">fabulae</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in Umbria</lemma>, where Ameria was situated: <foreign lang="la">his veteribus municipus</foreign>, i.e. in Latium, as opposed to those more distant in Umbria.
</p>
<p> <pb n="21"/> 

<milestone n="XVII" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ipsi</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">sua sponte</foreign>, as opposed to <foreign lang="la">patrum voluntate</foreign>: <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">et</lemma> answers to <foreign lang="la">que</foreign> after <foreign lang="la">vitam</foreign>, for which see Cat. II. 28, Halm's note.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="49">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid censes. . . quo studio. . . </lemma> Strictly we should have <foreign lang="la">quo studio censes hunc esse?</foreign> <gloss>With what zeal do you think he is endued?</gloss> But the naturalness of the phrase <foreign lang="la">quid censes?</foreign> <gloss>what do you think?</gloss> led writers to begin sentences of the present kind with that phrase, and to think of it as accus. and infin. regardless of strict grammar. Cf. de Off. 2.25, <foreign lang="la">quid censemus . . . Dionysium quo cruciatu angi solitum?</foreign> An extreme case is Horace Ep. 1.6.5, where the construction is repeatedly broken by <foreign lang="la">quid.</foreign> Translate, <gloss>As to this Sex. Roscius himself, what do you suppose is the zeal</gloss>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">callidior</lemma>: Richter compares de Nat. Deor. 3.25, <foreign lang="la">callidos appello, quorum, tamquam manus opere, sic animus usu concalluit</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">his propinquis</lemma>; i.e. those who were present as <foreign lang="la">advocati</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 1">1</bibl>. 
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">artificio</lemma>, <gloss>handicraft</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">accusatorio</foreign>, <gloss>of accuser</gloss> : cf. de Imp. Pomp. 61, <foreign lang="la">senatorius gradus</foreign>, <gloss>rank of a senator.</gloss> In such cases the English substantive in the genitive is most frequently represented by a Latin adjective; cf. N&auml;gelsbach, Lat. Stil. &sect; 20.2.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">licebit</lemma>, ironically for <foreign lang="la">debebit</foreign>; as if it were a burden to be laid down. (Richter.)
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hanc calamitatem</lemma>, the loss of <foreign lang="la">vita et fama</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fraudi</lemma>, <gloss>harm</gloss>, <gloss>prejudice</gloss>, since his living in the country was to serve as a proof of his father's aversion to him. In his sense <foreign lang="la">fraus</foreign> is only found in the constructions <foreign lang="la">res est fraudi</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">sine fraude</foreign>, as in the phrase <foreign lang="la">quod sine fraude mea fiat</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aliis</lemma>, his enemies. 


 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="50">
<milestone n="XVIII" unit="chapter"/>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Ne tu</lemma>: <foreign lang="la">ne</foreign> is rarely found in the best writers vithout a personal or demonstrative pronoun. The spelling ,<foreign lang="la">nae</foreign> is contrary to the MSS.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Atilium</lemma>, supposed to be C. Atilius Regulus, surnamed Serranus, consul B.C. 257 and 250 : to be distinguished from is more famous relative M. Atilius Regulus, who died a captive in the hands of the Carthaginians.  The surname is found a coins as Sarranus, whence some derive it from the town Sarranum in Umbria.  But see Plin. N.H. 28. &sect; 20, <foreign lang="la">serenem invenerunt dati honores Serranum, unde ei et cognomen</foreign>: cf. Virg. Aen. 6. 845, <foreign lang="la">te sulco, Serrane, serentem</foreign>.

<pb n="22"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aliter existimabant</lemma>: cf. Plin. N.H. 18. &sect; 11, <foreign lang="la">agrum male colere censorium probrum iudicabatur, atque ut refert Cato</foreign> (de Re Rust. praef. &sect; 2), <foreign lang="la">cum virum bonum agricolam</foreign>
</p>
<p> <pb n="96"/>
</p>
<p> <foreign lang="la">bonumque colonum dixissent, amplissime laudasse existimabantur</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de ceteris</lemma>, as C. Quinctius Cincinnatus, M'. Curius Dentatus.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">itaque</lemma>, <gloss>and through such principles.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quibus rebus</lemma>, <gloss>by which qualities</gloss>, i.e. industry and contentment.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="51">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eo quo sint</lemma>, <gloss>on the ground that</gloss>, of a reason which is not the true one: cf. pro Quinct. 5, <foreign lang="la">non eo dico, C. Aquili, quo mihi veniat in dubium tua fides</foreign>.

</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">summi viri</lemma> refers to their position in the State; <foreign lang="la">clarissimi homines</foreign>, to their moral excellence (in that <foreign lang="la">non alienos agros cupide adpetebant</foreign>): this is shown by the collocation of the substantives. With <foreign lang="la">clarissimus</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">vir</foreign> is usually found, not <foreign lang="la">homo</foreign>. Similarly pro Rosc. Com. 42, <foreign lang="la">quem tu si ex censu spectas, eques Romanus est, si ex vita, homo clarissimus est</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">debebant</lemma>, <gloss>were called upon.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ei homini</lemma>, <gloss>a man.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Se fateatur esse rusticum</lemma>, in contrast with those who <foreign lang="la">ad gubernacula rei p. sedere debebant</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">assiduus</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">frequens</foreign>.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="52">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">immo vero</lemma> gives an affirmative answer where a negative would be expected. With this sentence the second point iu the <foreign lang="la">probabile ex causa</foreign> (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 40">40</bibl>) is entered on.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">audio</lemma>, <gloss>that I will listen to</gloss>: cf. Verr. 2.3.79, <foreign lang="la">non audio</foreign>, <gloss>I will not hear it.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">illa</lemma> refers to what follows, and is contrasted with <foreign lang="la">aliquid</foreign> just before.


<pb n="23"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quippe</lemma>, <gloss>of course</gloss>, as in pro Mil. 47.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in oppidum</lemma>, <gloss>into a town</gloss>; not <emph>the</emph> town (of Ameria), for his father was not usually there.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">domum suam. . . vocabat</lemma>; i.e. he was universally unpopular, which would account for his father's disliking him.
</p>
<p> <foreign lang="la">Vocabat</foreign>, sc. <foreign lang="la">ad cenam</foreign>; 50 <foreign lang="greek">kalei=n</foreign> alone.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">revocaturus esset</lemma>, <gloss>was in a position to invite them in return</gloss>.


<milestone n="XIX" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod coepimus</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">videre</foreign>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="53">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">exheredare</lemma>, etc.; the thesis of the second point in the <foreign lang="la">probabile ex causa</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mitto quaerere </lemma>= <foreign lang="la">non quaero</foreign>: cf. pro Quinct. 85, <foreign lang="la">mitto illud licere</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui scias</lemma>, how you know the <emph>fact</emph>, as opposed to the cause of it.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Id erat</lemma>, <gloss>would have been</gloss>, in our idiom. Latin and Greek constantly state an obligation, possibility, and the like, as a kind of absolute standard, in the indic., not conditionally as we do.  Cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 37">37</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 136">136</bibl> <foreign lang="la">perditi civis erat</foreign>; <bibl>Plato Rep. 474 D</bibl> <foreign lang="greek">a)/llw| e)/prepen le/gein a(\ le/geis</foreign>, <gloss>it <emph>would have been</emph> seemly  for another to say . . .</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">certi accusatoris</lemma>, <gloss>genuine, sincere</gloss>: the opposite to <foreign lang="la">calumniator</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>. So Div. in Caec. &sect; 29, <foreign lang="la">accusator firmus verusque</foreign> as opposed to <foreign lang="la">praevaricator</foreign>; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">certum crimen</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 62">62</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">testis incertus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vinceret . . . eiceret. . . oblivisceretur</lemma>, etc.; sc. in disinheriting his son. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="54">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">concedo</lemma>, <gloss>I permit</gloss>; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">concedis</lemma>, <gloss>you admit, confess</gloss>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">peto ... petat</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ea praetereas</lemma>; <foreign lang="la">ea</foreign> = the <emph>causes</emph> of the father's intention to disinherit the son: <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nulla esse</lemma>, <gloss>not to exist at all</gloss>; see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 128">128</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">voluisse exheredare</lemma>, the <emph>fact</emph> that he wished, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qua re</lemma>, <gloss>on the strength of which.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vere</lemma> with an emphasis, as opposed to <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">finge</lemma>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inludere</lemma>, sc. by alleging what he does not profess to be able to prove. With the dative <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dignitati</lemma> cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">illudamur</foreign>: the verb in the active can take either dat. or accus.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cogitabat</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">exheredare, i.e</foreign>. <gloss>Oh, he was only <emph>thinking about</emph> disinheriting him.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <milestone n=" 24 " unit="page"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">maiestate</lemma>, vested in the <foreign lang="la">iudices</foreign> as representatives of the <foreign lang="la">populus Romanus</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad libidinem</lemma>, <gloss>at the bidding of gain and desire</gloss>; i.e. desire for gain. <foreign lang="la">Ad</foreign>, as in such phrases as <foreign lang="la">ad voluntatem</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">ad nutum</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">ad arbitrium</foreign>, etc.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="55">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inimicitias nullas esse</lemma>: Cicero admits that no personal enmity prompted Erucius to accuse Sex. Roscius. Cf. Lysias, Eratosth. &sect; 2:  <foreign lang="greek">tou)nanti/on de/ moi dokou=men pei/sesqai h)\ e)n tw=| pro\ tou= xro/nw|. pro/teron me\n ga\r e)/dei th\n e)/xqran tou\s kathgorou=ntas e)pidei=cai, h(/tis ei)/h pro\s tou\s feu/gontas: nuni\ de\ k.t.l.</foreign> i.e. formerly it was taken for granted that an accuser was prompted by personal enmity against the accused, and he was even required to state the grounds of it; but now the case is different, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">huiusce pecunia</lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 30">30</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quid ergo est</lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 2">2</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ita</lemma>, in a limiting sense, as in <foreign lang="la">verum tamen hoc ita est utile</foreign>, below; <foreign lang="la">tamen, </foreign>i.e. even allowing that to be a proper motive, yet, etc.  <gloss>Your wish for gain ought to be compatible with a feeling that these men's opinion, and the lex Remmia, should have some weight.</gloss> Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 4">4</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">horum existimationem</lemma>, the opinion the jurors will form about you.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">legem Remmiam</lemma>, "<foreign lang="la">qua qui calumniabatur damnabatur, si crimen adprobare non poterat.</foreign>" It is not known by whom or when the law was passed. An accused person could apply for a <foreign lang="la">calumniae iudicium</foreign> against his accuser before his trial ended; if he was acquitted, the same jury which had tried him decided the case of the accuser, who, if found to have knowingly urged a false charge (<foreign lang="la">calumniari</foreign>), was probably branded on the forehead with the letter K (<foreign lang="la">kalumniator</foreign>), and lost the right of acting again as accuser. 

<milestone n="xx" unit="chapter"/> </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="56">

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Accusatores</lemma>.  There was no official public prosecutor at Rome; it was left to private persons to prefer the accusations in criminal trials, and if they proved their case they were rewarded. Hence during the reigns of terror accusation amounted to a trade for earning a livelihood; accusers were hired, as in the present case (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>); even clubs or associations of accusers were formed.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut ne</lemma>, in sense = <foreign lang="la">ut caveatur ne</foreign>; <gloss>provided that we are not</gloss>, etc. Cf. ad Fam. 16. 9.3, <foreign lang="la">sed tamen ita velim, ut ne quid properes</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">abest a culpa</lemma>; as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 95">95</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">longe absum ab cius modi crimine</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tametsi. . . ignoscere</lemma> forms the apodosis to the protasis <foreign lang="la">innocens . . . non caret</foreign>, though in form the two are co-ordinate. For the position of <foreign lang="la">tamen</foreign>, cf. Phil. 2. &sect; 39, <foreign lang="la">homines, quamvis in turbidis rebus sint, tamen</foreign>, etc
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possum</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">criminose ac suspiciose</lemma>, <gloss>so as to imply guilt and arouse suspicions</gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 76">76</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">argui suspiciose</foreign>; Brut. 131, <foreign lang="la">qui suspiciosius aut criminosius diceret, audivi neminem</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">calumniari</lemma>: see above on <foreign lang="la">leqem Remmiam</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sciens</lemma>, <gloss>knowingly</gloss>; <foreign lang="la">scienter</foreign> would mean <gloss>cleverly.</gloss>  There is a similar difference between <foreign lang="la">prudens, imprudens feci</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">prudenter, imprudenter feci</foreign>. 
</p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">absolvi</lemma>, i.e. (to be accused and) acquitted. <foreign lang="la">causam non dicere</foreign> here = <foreign lang="la">reum non fieri</foreign>; see on &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">anseribus</lemma>: cf. Pun. N.H. 10. &sect; 51, <foreign lang="la">est et anseri vigil cura</foreign> (i.e. the goose is a wakeful bird), <foreign lang="la">Capitolio testata defenso, per id tempus canum silentio proditis rebus; quam ob causam cibaria anserum censores in primis locant</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">locantur</lemma>, the technical term for letting out contracts for purposes of state.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">significent</lemma>, absolute, <gloss>make a sign, give warning.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">at fures internoscere non possunt</lemma>. Cicero anticipates the objection : <gloss>It is true they cannot distinguish thieves; but yet</gloss> (<foreign lang="la">tamen</foreign>) <gloss>they give a sign</gloss>, etc.


<pb n="25"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tametsi bestiae sunt</lemma>, etc., i.e. though they are brute creatures, they err on the side of caution; they are cautious to a fault.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">salutatum</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">veneratum</foreign>.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="57">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">est ratio</lemma>, <gloss>the case is the same with.</gloss> The comparison, though it must have amused and delighted the audience, fails in several points : e.g. the geese were not kept to guard the Capitol, but by way of reward (cf. <foreign lang="la">sacri Iunonis</foreign>, Liv. 5.47); and accusers were not officially paid by the State.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cibaria</lemma> answers to the money given to Erucius by Magnus and Capito, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 30">30</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 58">58</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commisisse</lemma>, absolute, <gloss>has been guilty of a crime</gloss>; unless <foreign lang="la">aliquid</foreign> has fallen out from confusion with <foreign lang="la">aliquem</foreign>, as Hotoman conjectures : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 67">67</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">litteram iliam</lemma>, viz. K, perhaps referring to the voting tablets with which the jurors voted for a condemnation, which had K marked on them, standing for the initial of <foreign lang="la">condemno</foreign>. If so, the expression seems metaphorical; <foreign lang="la">caput</foreign> = civic status.  <gloss>With such energy will bring to bear upon your position as citizens that letter which . . .</gloss> etc. K has also been explained as the initial of <foreign lang="la">calumniator</foreign>, and it has been alleged that false accusers were actually branded with a K. In either case there is a punning allusion to K as = <foreign lang="la">Kalendae</foreign>, the day on which debtors had to pay interest. Cicero implies, as Mr. Stock remarks, that the accusers were an impecunious set. For the above note I am chiefly indebted to Mr. W. Y. Fausset's article, Classical Review 1893, p.128.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">neminem</lemma>; the <foreign lang="la">calumniator</foreign> besides being branded incurred <foreign lang="la">infamia</foreign>, and could not act again as accuser.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fortunas suas accusare</lemma> was said proverbially of those who suffered through their own fault. In the sense of <gloss>fortunes</gloss>, <gloss>destiny</gloss>, the singular is more common; cf. pro Sulla, &sect; 66, Halm's note. 

 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="58">
<milestone n="XXI" unit="chapter"/>
<p>Here the digression on the <foreign lang="la">accusatores</foreign> ends. With the question <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid mihi</lemma>, etc., Cicero recalls the subject of c. XIX., the contents of which are recapitulated in the form of <foreign lang="la">altercatio</foreign> (opposed to <foreign lang="la">perpetua oratio</foreign>: see on pro Sulla, &sect;48). Cf. &sect;94.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad defendeudum</lemma>, <gloss>as subject matter for my defence</gloss>: ad suspicandum, <gloss>as ground for suspicion.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">audio</lemma>, different from <foreign lang="la">audio</foreign> in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 52">52</bibl>; here in the sense <gloss>I hear you <emph>say</emph> so, (but I want proofs).</gloss>
</p>
<p> <pb n="26"/> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Nihil est</lemma>, is reiterated in <foreign lang="la">non . . .</foreign>; <gloss> You have nothing to say; not a word as to whom he conferred with, whom he informed, whence that suspicion entered your minds.</gloss> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fraudem</lemma>, i.e. the false accusation.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="59">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">operae pretium erat</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">si. . . </foreign>, lit. <gloss>to consider his negligence, if you observed it, was a reward for your trouble.</gloss> We say, <gloss>would have been worth your while</gloss>. Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">id erat</foreign>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">credo</lemma>, not ironically, but in jest; <gloss>I cannot help thinking that he must have inquired</gloss>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quaesisse</lemma>, without <foreign lang="la">eum</foreign> as subject  see Madvig, &sect; 401, and cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 61">61</bibl> <foreign lang="la">venisse</foreign>, 74 <foreign lang="la">fecisse</foreign>, 97 <foreign lang="la">audisse</foreign>, 84 <foreign lang="la">paratum esse</foreign>, 100 <foreign lang="la">proditurum esse</foreign>, 126 <foreign lang="la">occisum esse.</foreign> Halm notices the last three as instances of the rare omission of the subject where there is a separate predicate (<foreign lang="la">paratum</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">proditurum</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">occisum</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in hisce subselliis</lemma>, as <foreign lang="la">advocati</foreign> of the accused: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 12">12</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">hic in foro</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causam publicam</lemma>: see <ref n="1" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 1</ref>, note 1.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cenam imperaret</lemma>, as if the trial would soon be over.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">consessu</lemma>, the jury; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">conventu</lemma>, see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl> in init. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Pro summa solitudine</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">quasi esset summa solitudo</foreign>. Cf. Verr. 2.1. 113, <foreign lang="la">nos, si alienam vicem pro nostra iniuria</foreign> (=<foreign lang="la">perinde quasi nobis iniuria inlata esset</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">doloremus, vestigium istius in foro non esset relictum.</foreign>

 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="60">
<milestone n="XXII" unit="chapter"/>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aurrexi ego</lemma> ; the last word is emphasized: <gloss>it was I, none of the</gloss> <foreign lang="la">summi oratores nobilissimique viri</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 1">1</bibl>), <gloss>who arose</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">usque eo</lemma> goes with <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iocari</lemma>, and by a confusion of constructions is correlative with <foreign lang="la">antequam</foreign>; either <foreign lang="la">usque eo . . . dum</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">antea . . . quam</foreign> would be expected.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">alias res agere</lemma>, i.e. <gloss>pay no attention.</gloss> 

<pb n="27"/></p>
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vexari pessime</lemma>, <gloss>was being very roughly handled.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="61">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commode</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 9">9</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quem dedi. . . vides indicare</lemma>, explanatory of the previous clause, and forming a kind of parenthesis, as if it were, <foreign lang="la">quem enim dedi</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quos</lemma>, i.e. the <foreign lang="la">iudices : iudicare</foreign>, 'are sitting in judgment, s.c. weighing both sides, not betraying one.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">restitue nobis</lemma>, etc. <gloss>Show us once more that old acuteness and foresight of yours.</gloss> Cicero says jestingly that Erucius could only re-establish his reputation by confessing that he had rested his case on such slender proofs, because he expected no opposition.  On <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">venisse</lemma> without <foreign lang="la">te</foreign>, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 59">59</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">latrocinium</lemma>, an act of robbery, a crime: or concrete, <gloss>a band of robbers</gloss>; so Richter. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="62">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de parricidio causa dicitur</lemma>, etc. An instance of a <foreign lang="la">universi generis oratio</foreign>, or statement in general terms ; Greek <foreign lang="greek">qe/sis</foreign>.  <gloss>A charge of parricide is being preferred : yet no reason is given by the accuser why the son should have murdered the father.</gloss>  See Cic. Topica, &sect; 79; Orator, &sect; 46; and cf. de Imp. Pomp. &sect; 28 sqq.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">his levioribus</lemma>; <foreign lang="la">his</foreign> implies <gloss> these that we all know so well.</gloss>


<pb n="28"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">neque levi coniectura res penditur</lemma>, <gloss>is not weighed by means of careless conjecture</gloss>; i.e. mere guesswork does not influence the decision.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">incertus</lemma>, <gloss>untrustworthy</gloss>, whether as to his knowledge of the facts, or as to the chance of his telling the truth.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ingenio</lemma>, according to the accuser's ability, according as he has framed his accusation well or ill.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Haec cum sint omnia</lemma>, <gloss>though all these circumstances be present.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">expressa sceleris vestigia</lemma>, <gloss>the footprints of the crime</gloss>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 47">47</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per quos</lemma>, <gloss>by what agent?</gloss>: cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 74">74</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 79">79</bibl>.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="63">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">portentum atque monstrum</lemma>, and <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">immanitate</lemma> below : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 38">38</bibl> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">esse aliquem</lemma>; <foreign lang="la">esse</foreign>, not <foreign lang="la">aliquem</foreign>, has the emphasis ; <gloss>that there should exist a creature.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">propter quos</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">educatio</lemma> : cf. de Fin. 2. 62, <foreign lang="la">etiam in bestiis vis naturae perspici potest ; quarum in fetu et in educatione, laborem cum cernimus, naturae ipsius vocem videmur audire.</foreign>


 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="64">
<milestone n="XXIII" unit="chapter"/>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Tarracinensem</lemma>, of Tarracina, the ancient Anxur, a town in Latium in the Volscian territory.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">servus quisquam</lemma> : <foreign lang="la">quisquam</foreign> is used, as here, adjectivally only with substantives denoting persons (as &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 74">74</bibl> <foreign lang="la">cum homine quoquam</foreign>; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 94">94</bibl> <foreign lang="la">quisquam quemquam sicarium</foreign>) or classes of persons (as Verr. 2.2.7, <foreign lang="la">cuiquam ordini</foreign>) ; not with those denoting inanimate objects.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id aetatis</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">ea aetate</foreign>, as <foreign lang="la">id temporis</foreign> = <foreign lang="la">eo tempore</foreign>, placed first for emphasis ; the sons were not children, but youths.


<pb n="29"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suspiciosum autem</lemma>, <gloss>merely <emph>suspicious</emph>, did I say? that neither of them noticed it ? </gloss> (implying that such a statement was not merely suspicious, but a clear sign of guilt). On <foreign lang="la">autem</foreign> correcting an inadequate phrase, cf. Or. in Pis. fragm. <foreign lang="la">Quod minimum specimen in te ingenii? ingenii autem? immo ingenii hominis ac liberi?</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">se committere</lemma>, <gloss>to venture into.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">defendere absolute</lemma>, <gloss>give protection.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="65">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non modo </lemma>=<gloss> not only not</gloss>, the second <foreign lang="la">non</foreign> being omitted when the common verb <foreign lang="la">possunt</foreign> is in the second clause ; when it is in the first, as &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 137">137</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">id non modo re prohibere non licet, sed ne verbis quidem vituperare</foreign>, or when there are two verbs, as &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 54">54</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quod planum facere non modo non possis, verum ne coneris quidem</foreign>, the second <foreign lang="la">non</foreign> is added.


 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="66">
<milestone n="XXIV" unit="chapter"/>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">videtisne </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 113">113</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">itane est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quos Orestes and Alcmaeon</lemma>, known to the Romans as matricides through the plays of Ennius, Pacuvius, and Attius
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eum praesertim</lemma> not here =<gloss> especially since</gloss>, but <gloss>and that though</gloss>, as often. In such cases <foreign lang="la">cum</foreign> is concessive = <gloss>although</gloss>, and <foreign lang="la">praesertim</foreign>, <gloss>especially</gloss>, emphasises the greatness of the concession ;  <gloss>although--and note the fact--they are said</gloss>, etc. Cf. Brut. 267, <foreign lang="la">M. Bibulus, qui et scriptavit accurate, cum praesertim non esset orator.</foreign> See Mayor, Cic. Phil. &sect; 80, note ; Wilkins, Cat. 3. 28, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">deorum immortalium</lemma>. sc. Apollo, the <foreign lang="greek">profh/ths</foreign> of Zeus, who commanded them through oracles to avenge their fathers.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pii</lemma>, towards their fathers.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">necessitatem</lemma>, <gloss>restraining force </gloss> ; religionem, <gloss>sanctity, which should protect them from injury.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="67">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nolite putare</lemma>, etc. : cf. Cicero's later expression of the same thought, in Pisonem, &sect; 46, <foreign lang="la">nolite enim putare, ut in scaena videtis, homines consceleratos impulsu deorum terreri Furiarum taedis ardentibus : sua quemque fraus, suum facinus, suum scelus, sua audacia de sanitate ac mente deturbat ; hae sunt impiorum furiae, hae flammae, hae faces.</foreign> The original passage appears to be Aeschines in Tim. 180.


<pb n="30"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sua quemque</lemma>: the asyndeton enforces the antithesis between this and the last clause.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fraus</lemma>, <gloss>sin, evil deed </gloss> ; terror, i.e. the fears of a guilty conscience, = <foreign lang="la">angor conscientiae</foreign>, de Leg. 1.40.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">consolentiae</lemma>, stings of conscience ; for the plural cf. Parad. &sect; 18, <foreign lang="la">te conscientiae stimulant maleficiorum tuorum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">domesticae</lemma>, <gloss>belonging to their home</gloss>, i.e. familiar, abiding ; perhaps at the same time implying <foreign lang="greek">patro\s h)\ mhtro\s  *)eri/nues</foreign>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="68">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">manifestum</lemma>.  Gellius, N.A. 11. 18.11, <foreign lang="la">mansfestum furtum est, ut ait Masurius, quod deprehenditur dum fit.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praerupta</lemma>, literally, <gloss>broken off suddenly </gloss> ; i.e. headlong, impetuous.  Cf. Tac. Ann. 16.7, <foreign lang="la">iuvenis animo praeruptus.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">accedat</lemma> etc. : <foreign lang="la">odium parentis</foreign> would come under the head of <foreign lang="la">probabile ex causa</foreign> (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 40">40</bibl>); <foreign lang="la">amici improbi</foreign> and what follows would be the <foreign lang="la">signa et argumenta</foreign> of the crime : see note on <foreign lang="la">esto</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 73">73</bibl>, and cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 62">62</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">exstent oportet expressa sceleris vestigia, uti, qua ratione, per quos, quo tempore maleficium sit admissum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">credituri sunt</lemma>, <gloss>are to believe </gloss> ; for this use of the future part. with <foreign lang="la">sum</foreign> cf. de Fin. 11.26, <foreign lang="la">si veri amici futuri sumus</foreign>, <gloss>if we are to be true friends.</gloss> See Madvig, &sect; 341, Obs.


 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="69">
<milestone n="XXV" unit="chapter"/>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">multis ex rebus </lemma>: we should say, <gloss>from many <emph>other</emph> things</gloss>; Verr. 2.4.174, <foreign lang="la">cum multa, tum etiam hoc me memini dicere.</foreign>


<pb n="31"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="70">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dum ea rerum potita est</lemma>, i.e. as long as it held the supremacy among the Greek states : cf. ad Fam. 5.17.3, <foreign lang="la">et in nostra civitate et in ceteris, quae rerum potitae sunt</foreign> (i.e. have had dominion over other <foreign lang="la">civitates.</foreign>)  For the rare sense of <foreign lang="la">potior</foreign>  <gloss>to be in possession of</gloss>, cf. Cic. Acad. Pr. II. 126, <foreign lang="la">Cleanthes Solem dominari et rerum potiri putat</foreign> ; Val. Max. 9.15.5, <foreign lang="la">Sulla rerum potiente</foreign>, <gloss>during Sulla's supremacy</gloss>; Tac. Ann. 11.42, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hodie quoque utuntur</lemma>.  Though Greece was at this time a Roman province, Athens as a <foreign lang="la">libera civitas</foreign> enjoyed autonomy.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">admonere</lemma>, <gloss>bring to mind</gloss>, <gloss>suggest the idea.</gloss> Cf. pro Tullio, &sect; 9, <foreign lang="la">quod enim usu non veniebat, de eo si quis legem aut iudicium constitueret, non tam prohibere quam admonere videretur.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quanto nostri maiores</lemma>, etc. ; from here to <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">conquiescant</lemma> is in its own way one of the finest passages Cicero ever wrote, though he afterwards depreciated it.  See <ref n="n.,63" targOrder="U">Introd. note 63</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">supplicium singulare</lemma> : see Introd. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 10">10</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="71">
<milestone n="XXVI" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ex rerum natura</lemma>, <gloss>out of the world </gloss> ; by denying him the four elements (<foreign lang="la">coelum, solem aquam, terram</foreign>), "<foreign lang="la">ex quibus omnia nata esse dicuntur</foreign>."
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">scelus</lemma>, concrete, <gloss>horror, abomination.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">uteremur</lemma>, <gloss>we should find </gloss> : cf. Dem. Olynth. I. &sect; 9.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sic nudos</lemma>, <gloss>naked as they are</gloss>, i.e. in their natural nakedness. Mr. S. Stanley in Class. Rev. 1897, p.346, argues in favour of explaining thus : "They did not wish to throw the offenders <emph>under such circumstances</emph> (sic), i.e. <emph>being so wicked</emph>, into the river naked": and similarly Livy 2.10. <foreign lang="la">sic armatus (Cocles) in Tiberim desiluit.</foreign>  But in both passages the sense usually given to <foreign lang="la">sic</foreign> seems best.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ipsum</lemma>  Cf. Macbeth, II.2 :

<quote><l>No, this my hand will rather</l>
<l>The multitudinous seas incarnadine,</l>
<l>Making the green one red.</l></quote>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">violata</lemma>, i.e. defiled by crime.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">expiari putantur</lemma> : so Iphigenia seeks to purify her brother Orestes with sea-water, since <foreign lang="greek">qa/lassa klu/zei pa/nta ta)nqrw/pwn kaka/</foreign>, Eur. Iphig. Taur. 1193.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="72">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vivis</lemma>, etc. : the substantival use of adjectives, which is most common in the plural, is especially found in an enumeration of several adjectives, as here ; cf. Zumpt, &sect; 363.


<pb n="32"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nunquam adluantur</lemma>, <gloss>may never be washed, touched.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">Abluantur</foreign> is also read.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad saxa</lemma>, the hardest kind of resting-place.  Cf. <ref n="10" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 10</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">diligentius paratiusque</lemma> : cf. Brut. 241, <foreign lang="la">is ad dicendum veniebat magis audacter quam parate</foreign> ; Phil. 2.79, <foreign lang="la">invectus est copiosius multo in istum et paratius Dolabella quam nunc ego.</foreign> Usually Cicero does not use the adverb, but says <foreign lang="la">paratus aliquis ad dicendum venit</foreign> ; but here <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">paratius</lemma>, corresponding with the preceding adverb <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">diligentius</lemma> (= <foreign lang="la">diligentius meditatus</foreign>) ; and similarly in the passages quoted.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">venisses</lemma>, not <gloss>you would have come</gloss>, but <gloss>you ought to have come</gloss> = <foreign lang="la">venire debuisses</foreign>, the <gloss>past jussive.</gloss>  Cf. pro Sest. 45, <foreign lang="la">restitisses, repugnasses, mortem pugnans oppetisses</foreign> ; Ib. 54 ; pro Sulla, 25 ; Aeneid 8. 643, <foreign lang="la">At tu dictis, Albane, maneres.</foreign>  See Roby, 1604.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="73">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">neminem ne . . . quidem</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 22">22</bibl>, note in fin.


<milestone n="XXVII" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Esto</lemma>, <gloss>Be it so</gloss>, marks the transition from the <foreign lang="la">probabile ex vita</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 39">39</bibl>) and <foreign lang="la">probabile ex causa (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 40">40</bibl></foreign> sqq.) to the particular <foreign lang="la">argumenta et signa</foreign>, i.e. the evidence bearing directly on the crime.  Cf. Verr. 2.5. 43, <foreign lang="la">esto : nihil</foreign> ex <foreign lang="la">fugitivorum bello laudis adeptus</foreign> es : <foreign lang="la">at vero</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vicisse debeo</lemma>, <gloss>ought to have gained the victory </gloss> ; i.e. though my victory ought to be an accomplished fact at once.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non quaero . . . quaero.</lemma>  For the absence of the adversative particle, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 1">1</bibl>, note ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">mitto quaerere . . . quaero</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">meo loco</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">i.e. nunc cum meus est dicendi locus</foreign> ; Greek, &lt;<foreign lang="greek">e)n tw=| e)mw=| u(/dati</foreign>.


<pb n="33"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="74">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ipsum</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">percussisse.</foreign>  <foreign lang="la">Romae non fuit</foreign>, abbrev. for <foreign lang="la">respondeo eum Romae non fuisse.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si liberos</lemma>, wanting in the MSS. ; but the words are indispensable, since here Cicero begins discussing the latter of the two alternatives, <foreign lang="la">servosne an liberos</foreign> ; the other follows in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">reliquum est ut per servos id admiserit.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ubi eos convenit</lemma>.  Auct. ad Her. ii. &sect; 8 : <foreign lang="la">Argumentum est, per quod reus coarguitur certioribus argumentis et magis firma suspicione. Id dividitur in tempora tria : praeteritum, instans, consequens.  In praeterito tempore oportet considerare, ubi fuerit, ubi visus sit, quicum visus sit ; num quid adpararit, num quem convenerit.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui conlocutus est</lemma>, <gloss>how did he confer with them </gloss> ; not necessarily implying <gloss>by word of mouth</gloss>, as we find <foreign lang="la">colloqui per litteras, per internuntios.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">unde</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">a quo</foreign>, <gloss>through whom.</gloss> The Romans frequently paid debts, as in modern times, by orders on bankers, <foreign lang="la">argentarii</foreign> ; a transaction expressed by the phrase <foreign lang="la">scribere</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">solvere ab argentario</foreign>, <gloss>to write an order for payment <emph>through</emph> or on a banker.</gloss> Ramsay, Rom. Ant. p.315.  Hence the phrases <foreign lang="la">dare, solvere, numerare ab aliquo</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">caput</lemma> <gloss>origin, source.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nunquam cum homine quoquam</lemma>, an exaggeration ; see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 52">52</bibl> sub fin. : &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 76">76</bibl> is more exact, <foreign lang="la">qui nunquam inter homines fuerit.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">constitisse</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">moratum esse</foreign> ; Verr. 1. l. 101, <foreign lang="la">qui Romae vix triduum constitisset.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="75">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praetereo illud</lemma>, etc. Richter remarks that the commonplace about the innocence of a rustic life is put into the form <foreign lang="la">praeteritio</foreign> (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 106">106</bibl>), being really of little value as evidence, in spite of Cicero's <foreign lang="la">quod mihi maximo</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inculta</lemma>, <gloss>uncivilized.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">omnia</lemma>, <gloss>of every kind.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">agrestem</lemma>, <gloss>boorish</gloss>, <gloss>wild</gloss>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 74">74</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">hunc hominem ferum eique agrestem fuisse.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">diligentiae</lemma> <gloss>economy</gloss>. Cf. Auct. ad Her. 4. 35, <foreign lang="la">diligentia est accurata conservatio suorum</foreign>  </p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">magistra</lemma>, <gloss>teacher.</gloss>


<pb n="34"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="76">
<milestone n="XXVIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tam occultum</lemma>, since even the accuser had nothing to say as to the particular circumstances under which it was committed.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suspiciose</lemma>, <gloss>so as to arouse suspicion</gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl> sub fin.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suspicio</lemma> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl> in init.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causa dicitur</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 5">5</bibl>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="77">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">reliquum est</lemma>, the other alternative of the dilemma: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 74">74</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">si per liberos</foreign>.  <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut</lemma>: see 28, first note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in quaestionem</lemma>, here = <gloss>for examination under torture</gloss>. The evidence of slaves was only taken under torture in Rome.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">polliceantur</lemma>: It was forbidden, except in special cases (cf. pro Mu. &sect; 59), to examine slaves in order to elicit evidence against their masters ; but the master could <emph>offer</emph> his slaves voluntarily for examination.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">unus puer unus puer  . . relictus non est</lemma>, instead of <foreign lang="la">ne unus quidem puer relictus est</foreign>, as would be expected, in order to bring <foreign lang="la">unus</foreign> as the first word into sharper contrast with <foreign lang="la">omnes servos.</foreign>  Cf. de Prov. Cons. 7, <foreign lang="la">nisi C. Vergilius intervenisset (spoliationi Byzantii), unum signum Byzantii ex maximo numero nullum haberent</foreign>; below &sect; 102, <foreign lang="la">ut in minimis rebus . . . non dicerent.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">P. Scipio</lemma>, supposed (though with very little certainty) to be P. Cornelius Scipio Nasica, a grandson of Scipio Nasica Serapio (who killed Ti. Gracchus), and son-in-law of the orator L. Crassus, praetor 94 B.C.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Metelle</lemma>.  If M. (as supplied in Halm's text) is the true initial wanting in the MSS., M. Metellus, the brother of Q. Metellus Creticus, may be meant, who was praetor B. C. 69.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">advocatis . . . agentibus</lemma>, i.e. they were present to support his claim and act for him (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 1">1</bibl>) when he made the application.  Similarly the examination itself had to be performed <foreign lang="la">privatim</foreign>, in the presence of friends and witnesses ; cf. pro Cluent. &sect; 176.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">T. Roscium</lemma>, sc <foreign lang="la">Magnum</foreign> (cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 119">119</bibl>), to whom as bailiff of Chrysogonus the demand was addressed.


<pb n="35"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="78">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ne quaerendi . . . permittitur</lemma>, sc. by the refusal of Magnus to surrender the slaves for examination. <foreign lang="la">Quaerere</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">quaestionem habere de morte alicuius</foreign> = <gloss>to hold an investigation into a person's death</gloss>: cf. pro Cluent. &sect; 176.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in caede</lemma>, as <foreign lang="la">sicarii</foreign> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ex caede</lemma>, as <foreign lang="la">sectores.</foreign>  (Richter.)
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">erit</lemma> in sense = <foreign lang="la">licebit esse</foreign>, <gloss>is he not to be.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dum . . . quaeratur</lemma>, <gloss>long enough to give time for an enquiry . . .</gloss>  ; <foreign lang="la">dum</foreign> is used with subj. when suspense and design are involved ; Gildersleeve and Lodge 572.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad hunc locum</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 19">19</bibl>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="79">
<milestone n="XXIX" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">conveniat mihi</lemma>, etc., recapitulation of the last two chapters.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id quod negas</lemma>.  Cicero could now assume this, as he had disposed of the hypothesis <foreign lang="la">ipsum fecisse</foreign> by the words <foreign lang="la">Romae non fuit</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 74">74</bibl>), and as Erucius had not taken advantage of the permission there given him to make objections.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut potuerit</lemma>: <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> = <gloss>how </gloss> ; cf. ad Att. L 16, <foreign lang="la">credo te audisse ut me circumsteterint.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">temere</lemma>, <gloss>without reason</gloss>, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 62">62</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">servorum nomen</lemma>, <gloss>the mention of slaves</gloss>, in sense = <foreign lang="la">ut nominares servos.</foreign> The substantive is chosen to suit the following words, <foreign lang="la">quo quasi in portum</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">reiectus a ceteris suspicionibus</lemma>.  The last word seems to be used loosely ; we should say, <gloss>ways of rousing suspicion</gloss>, or the like. Cf. <foreign lang="la">suspiciose dicere</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, in the same sense. Similarly in Sall. Frag. ap. Non. 2.900, <foreign lang="la">multis suspicionibus volentia plebi facturus videbatur</foreign>, our word <gloss> suspicions </gloss> will hardly express the Latin substantive ; cf. above &sect; 28, <foreign lang="la">in qua re nulla subesset suspicio</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">scopulum</lemma> : see the first six lines of &sect; 120.


<pb n="36"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="80">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">una mercede duas res adsequi</lemma>.  For other forms of the proverb, cf. ad Fam. 7. 29. 2, <foreign lang="la">duo parietes de eadem fidelia</foreign> (pot of paint) <foreign lang="la">dealbare</foreign> ; Plaut. Casin. 2.8.40,  <foreign lang="la">iam ego uno in saltu lepide apros copione duos</foreign> ; and the English equivalent. <foreign lang="la">Una mercede</foreign> is abl. of price.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">perfundere</lemma>, <gloss>to wet all over the surface </gloss> (not <gloss>to drench </gloss> ) seems here the meaning.  Cic. says, <gloss>You are trying to give us a merely superficial splashing with your legal process, but genuinely to accuse those in whose pity you are</gloss>, since the arguments of Erucius tell against his own side.  Professor Clark supports this sense of <foreign lang="la">perfundere</foreign> by comparing Suet. Dom. S <foreign lang="la">perfusoriis assertionibus</foreign>, <gloss>superficial, unauthorised claims for freedom.</gloss>  So, perhaps, Seneca 23. 4, <foreign lang="la">tenuis et perfusoria voluptas</foreign>, <gloss>a pleasure only skin deep.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">Perfundere</foreign> misunderstood has led to weak emendations, e.g. <foreign lang="la">pervertere</foreign>, <gloss>overthrow.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per quos et de quibus</lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 97">97</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quoniam cuius <emph>consilio</emph> occisus sit invenio, cuius <emph>manu</emph> sit percussus non laboro.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nonne cogitas</lemma>. A question with <foreign lang="la">nonne</foreign> sometimes expresses, not the conviction that a thing is, but surprise that it is not ; as if <foreign lang="la">non</foreign> stood in the place of <foreign lang="la">nonne.</foreign>  So <foreign lang="la">nonne cogitas</foreign> is not <gloss>Do you not think?</gloss> but<gloss> Do you not think, do you forget ? </gloss> Cf. Tusc. i.17, <foreign lang="la">quid, si te rogavero aliquid, nonne respondebis</foreign>, <gloss>will you make no reply ? </gloss> de Fin. 5.86, <foreign lang="la">nonne igitur tibi videntur, inguit, mala?</foreign>  <gloss>do you think they are <emph>not</emph> evils ?</gloss> Cat. 1. l. 27.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sectoribus</lemma>, and below, <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sectores collorum et bonorum</lemma>: see <ref n="n.,23" targOrder="U">Introd. note 23</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quid postea?</lemma>  <gloss>What then ?  What follows ? </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nescisne per ista</lemma>, etc. ; i.e. <emph> the</emph> <foreign lang="la">sectores bonorum</foreign>, <gloss>such as Chrysogonus, Magnus, and Capito were usually also the</gloss> <foreign lang="la">sectores collorum</foreign> <gloss>(cut-throats) ; so that if you talk of the multitude of assassins, you accuse the very persons in whose pay you are.</gloss>  In the repeated <foreign lang="la">sectores</foreign> there is of course a play on the two meanings.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="81">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">denique</lemma> implies indignation.


<pb n="37"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="82">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dissoluta est</lemma>, the phrase for solving catch-questions (Acad. Pr. 2.46, <foreign lang="la">fallaces et captiosas interrogationes dissolvere</foreign>), also said, like the more common <foreign lang="la">diluere</foreign> of the refutation of charges which it required dialectical skill to subvert.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">exspectatis ut</lemma>, <gloss>wait in the expectation that </gloss> : see Madvig, &sect; 360, Obs. l.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de peculatu</lemma>, <gloss>embezzlement of State property.</gloss> The accuser had insinuated that Sex. Roscius had secretly kept back some of his father's confiscated property : cf. the fine passage &sect; 145, <foreign lang="la">rogat oratque te</foreign>, etc., which alludes to the same thing.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">declamare</lemma>, <gloss>to repeat, recite</gloss>, the term for a rhetorical display in a <foreign lang="la">causa ficta</foreign> at school, or, as here, for rehearsing a speech to be delivered in public : <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commentaretur</lemma>, <gloss>was preparing, studying.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">verbo</lemma>, merely by assertion.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad testes</lemma> ; witnesses were examined after the speeches on both sides had been heard.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ipsa causa</lemma>, i.e. <gloss>my speech for the defence.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="83">
<milestone n="XXX" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Venio nunc</lemma>. The transition to the second main division of the speech ; see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 35">35</bibl>.  Cicero now turns accuser, and shows that the guilt of the murder really attaches to Magnus and Capito themselves.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non cupiditas ducit</lemma>, explained in the following words, <foreign lang="la">nam si mihi liberet accusare</foreign>, etc., i.e. if I were an accuser by inclination, these would not be the opponents whom I should choose, but <foreign lang="la">alios potius</foreign>, more distinguished men : cf. 91 sub fin., <foreign lang="la">studio.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">crescere</lemma>, <gloss>to rise, become famous.</gloss> An accusation in a <foreign lang="la">causa publica</foreign> was regarded as a service to the State ; and it was by undertaking such an accusation, especially against a man in high position, that young Romans tried to make a name.  Cf. pro Cael. &sect; 73, <foreign lang="la">industriam suam ex aliqua illustri accusatione cognosci.</foreign>  Cicero speaks of the misuse of the practice, de Off. 2.49 foll.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod</lemma>, adversative, <gloss>this however </gloss> ; as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 118">118</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quod ita promptum est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sua virtute</lemma>, <gloss>through his own merit.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iam intelleges</lemma>, the apodosis to <foreign lang="la">desinamus</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">quaeramus</foreign> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 48">48</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">refer . . . intelleges</foreign>; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 93">93</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quaere . . . reperies</foreign> ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 138">138</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">decerne . . . adprobabunt.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">certum crimen</lemma> : <foreign lang="la">certum</foreign> = <gloss>genuine</gloss>; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suspicionibus</lemma>, <gloss>suspicious circumstances </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 79">79</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id facerem</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">accusarem.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id erit signi</lemma>, quod, etc.  The common phrases <foreign lang="la">id negotii habeo ; hoc praemii ; quid consilii datis? quid hominis es?</foreign> and the like, seem to show that <foreign lang="la">id</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">signi</foreign> should be joined : <gloss>there will be this much proof</gloss> : lit. this of proof.  Cf. pro Cael. &sect; 38, <foreign lang="la">quid signi?</foreign> Auct. ad Her. 4. 1, <foreign lang="la">satis erit signi.</foreign>


<pb n="38"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="84">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causam</lemma>, <gloss>motive </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 40">40</bibl>. Erucius had professed to discover one, but Cicero refuted him, and hence can say <foreign lang="la">nullam reperiebas</foreign> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 79">79</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">negas.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">istic</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">in subselliis accusatorum</foreign>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">post viderimus</lemma> : the fut. perf. sometimes expresses what will <emph>soon</emph> be done ; cf. Madvig, &sect; 340, Obs. 4.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">palmas</lemma> : see &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 100">100</bibl>, notes. <foreign lang="la">alias</foreign>, as opposed to the present <foreign lang="la">palma</foreign>, viz. the murder of the elder Sex. Roscius, in which Capito was an accomplice.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cognoscet</lemma>, <gloss>he shall hear of </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 100">100</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">audiet.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">L. Cassius</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">Longinus</foreign>, who as tribune of the people in 137 B.C. introduced the <foreign lang="la">lex tabellaria</foreign>, which established voting with <foreign lang="la">tabellae</foreign>, tickets, in public trials : <foreign lang="la">homo non liberalitate, ut alii, sed ipsa tristitia et severitate popularis</foreign>, Brut. &sect; 97. So Halm. There are others of the same family who may be meant : l. The Cassius of Liv. Epit. 63, who in 114 or 113 B.C. accused the orator Antonius of incest ; <foreign lang="la">cuius tribunal propter nimiam severitatem scopulus reorum dicebatur</foreign>, Val. Max. 3.7.9. 2. The Cassius of Sal. Jug. 32, Praetor in B.C., who invited Jugurtha to Rome.  Asconius (ad Mu. &sect; 32) takes the first of these two as the hero of <foreign lang="la">cui bono</foreign> ; but they may be one and the same.  (Richter.)
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">verissimum</lemma>, <gloss>truthful</gloss>, <gloss>conscientious</gloss> ; often joined with <foreign lang="la">religiosus</foreign>, as in Verr. Act. l .3, <foreign lang="la">vere ac religiose iudicare.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quaerere</lemma>. Asconius ad Mil. &sect; 32 : <foreign lang="la">L. Cassius fuit summae vir severitatis. Is quotiens quaesitor iudicii alicuius esset, in quo quaereretur de homine occiso, suadebat atque etiam praeibat iudicibus, ut quaereretur cui bono fuisset perire eum, de cuius morte quaeritun</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cui bono</lemma> : often misquoted in the sense <gloss>to what good end, for what purpose</gloss>, as if <foreign lang="la">cui</foreign> agreed with <foreign lang="la">bono</foreign> ; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 13">13</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quibus</foreign>
</p>
<p> . . <foreign lang="la">bone.</foreign> The literal meaning is,  <gloss>to whom it had been for-an-advantage.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="85">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">periculum</lemma>; used in reference to the accused in a <foreign lang="la">causa publica</foreign> (<ref n="1" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 1</ref>), not in private suits : cf. de Imp. Pomp. &sect; 2, Halm's note.  Shakespeare, Merchant of Venice, act iv. so. 1, <quote><l>You stand within his danger, do you not?</l></quote>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">applicatus</lemma>. The MSS. give <foreign lang="la">implicitus</foreign>, which needs emendation.  Graevius suggested <foreign lang="la">implacatus</foreign> = <foreign lang="la">implacabilis</foreign>,  <gloss>unrelenting </gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">ad severitatem</foreign> would then have to mean, <gloss>to a degree amounting to sternness </gloss> (cf. pro Cluent. 183 <foreign lang="la">callidus ad fraudem</foreign>). <foreign lang="la">Applicatus</foreign> is preferable, as <foreign lang="la">ad</foreign> follows more naturally ; <gloss>given to, with a leaning to, severity.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praeest quaestioni</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 11">11</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ab innocentia</lemma> ; <foreign lang="la">ab</foreign> = on the side of, in favour of, as opp. to <foreign lang="la">contra</foreign> : cf. 104, <foreign lang="la">a nobis contra vosmet</foreign> ; Auct. ad Her. 2.12, <foreign lang="la">a rumoribus . . . contra rumores</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">facile me paterer dicere</lemma>, <gloss>I would willingly have acquiesced in speaking.</gloss> <foreign lang="la">illo ipse</foreign>, Sc. <foreign lang="la">Cassio  iudice . . . iudices</foreign>, <gloss>judge . . . jurors. </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Cassianos</lemma>, proverbial term for strict jurors ; as in Verr. 2.3.137, 146.


<pb n="39"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="86">
<milestone n="XXXI" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum viderent </lemma>: here <foreign lang="la">si viderent</foreign> would be purely conditional, <gloss>if they had seen</gloss>;   <foreign lang="la">cum viderint</foreign> assumes the condition, <gloss>when they saw</gloss>, <gloss>on seeing, </gloss> as they would do if present.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eo perspicuo</lemma>, <gloss>that point being clear</gloss>, sc. <foreign lang="la">cui bone fuisset.</foreign> For the abl. abs. with adjective and no participle see Draeger, Syntax 11.585.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eodem</lemma>, to the <foreign lang="la">praeda</foreign>, i.e. to the fact that you have got it.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="87">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praefers</lemma>, <gloss>you display </gloss> ; a rare form for <foreign lang="la">prae te fers.</foreign> Ov. Her. 17.36, <foreign lang="la">si modo quem praefers non simulatur amer.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">societatem coieris</lemma> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 20">20</bibl> sub fin.  We do not know whether Cicero knew this as a fact, or assumes it here, to serve as a proof of <foreign lang="la">avaritia.</foreign>  "The proof of <foreign lang="la">avaritia</foreign> is illogical, since what is given as evidence of it could only be shown through the trial itself." Halm.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">solus tu inventus es</lemma>, <gloss>you alone have <foreign lang="la">let yourself</foreign> be found, fixed on</gloss>: this brings out the sense of the following imperfects ; <gloss>as the man to sit, </gloss> etc.  The same idea is expressed differently, &sect; 95 : <foreign lang="la">tene tibi partes istas depoposcisse, ut in iudicio versarere et sederes cum accusatore?</foreign> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">os</lemma>, <gloss>your shameless face</gloss> : Verr. 2. 2, &sect; 48, <foreign lang="la">Nostis os hominis, nostis audaciam.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">offerres</lemma>, <gloss>thrust into view</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inimicitias . . . rei familiaris controversias</lemma>.  The latter give the grounds of the former.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="88">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc dubitemus</lemma>, <gloss>that we weigh this point.</gloss> Cf. Virg. Aen. 9. 191, <foreign lang="la">quid dubitem</foreign>, <gloss>what I am debating</gloss>, see Page's note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quaestum here in a narrow sense</lemma>, <gloss>dishonourable gain.</gloss> For the contrast with <foreign lang="la">fructum</foreign>, cf. Tusc. v.86, <foreign lang="la">quaestuosa mercatura, fructuosa aratio dicitur</foreign> : <gloss>commerce is lucrative, makes money ;  agriculture earns a livelihood.</gloss> Cf. the kindred verbs : <foreign lang="la">quaestus</foreign> = gain got by seeking it (<foreign lang="la">quaero</foreign>), implying avarice ; <foreign lang="la">fructus</foreign> = gain enjoyed, made use of (<foreign lang="la">fruor</foreign>) ; and cf. Liv. 21. 63, <foreign lang="la">quaestus omnis patribus indecorus visus</foreign>


<pb n="40"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fori iudiclorumque</lemma>, objective genitives ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">insolentiam</lemma>, <gloss>unfamiliarity with.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="89">
<milestone n="XXXII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tempus citius quam oratio</lemma>; cf. Sall. lug. 42, <foreign lang="la">de studiis partium si singillatim aut pro magnitudine parem disserere, tempus quam res maturius me deseret.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">neque ego non possum</lemma> ; repeated &sect; 91 sub fin., <foreign lang="la">et ego possum.</foreign> Note the words following this statement in the two passages. In &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl> Cicero merely says (as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>), <gloss>I, too, could dilate,--but I shall not do so, for I am not an accuser by choice.</gloss> Here he takes a different turn, in order to lead up to a digression (&sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 90">90</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl>) on Sulla's proscriptions : <gloss>I, too, could dilate--for I do not think you an abler speaker than myself, though (you might perhaps pass for such, since) I suffer by comparison with other</gloss> <foreign lang="la">patroni</foreign>, while you stand alone, <foreign lang="la">owing to the recent proscriptions in which so many accusatores fell.</foreign>  So Halm, who compares Momms. Rom. Hist. 3 p.353.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mihi derogo</lemma>, <gloss>depreciate myself.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in grege adnumerer</lemma>, <gloss>may be reckoned one in a crowd</gloss> : cf. <foreign lang="la">gregarius miles.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pugna Cannensis</lemma>, i.e. massacre.  The figure is carried out in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 90">90</bibl>.  <foreign lang="la">fecit</foreign>, has made you seem.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sat bonum</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">accusatorem. Sat</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">satis</foreign> has a limiting sense, like the French <foreign lang="fr">assez</foreign> : de Orat. 3. 84, <foreign lang="la">oratorem sat bonum, bonum denique</foreign>, <gloss>fairly good, nay, good </gloss> ; de Off. 2. 59, <foreign lang="la">bene pascere, satis bene pascere, male pascere.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="90">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad Servilium lacum</lemma>, an artificial reservoir, situated near the entrance of the <foreign lang="la">vicus iugarius</foreign> into the forum, and abutting on the <foreign lang="la">basilica Iulia</foreign> ; see Festus, p.290.  We learn from several authorities (Seneca, de Provid. c. 3 ; Iulii Firmici Astron. 1.3  Schol. ad Lucanum 2.161) that the heads of the proscribed were displayed at the <foreign lang="la">Lacus Servilius</foreign> as well as on the <foreign lang="la">rostrum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quis ibi</lemma>, etc., an imperfect trochaic verse, taken, according to the Scholiast, from the tragedy Achilles of Ennius, and spoken by Ulysses when the Greeks were driven back to their ships by Hector and their bravest heroes killed.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Curtios, Marios</lemma>; of these nothing further is known. Richter suggests for the latter name M. Marius Gratidianus, a connection of Cicero through his grandmother Gratidia, styled <foreign lang="la">aptissimus turbulentis concionibus</foreign>, Brut. 233, who at Sulla's command was murdered by Catiline.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Mammeos</lemma>, a corrupt reading : Ursinus suggests <foreign lang="la">Memmios</foreign> from Brut. 136, where the brothers C. and L. Memmii are described as <foreign lang="la">oratores mediocres, accusatores acres atque acerbi</foreign> ; but only one of these lived till Sulla's supremacy, for the elder Gaius had been murdered by the gangs of Saturninus and Glaucia, B.C. 100.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">a proeliis</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">forensibus.</foreign> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">avocabat</lemma>: so that they were no longer to be feared as combatants in the legal <foreign lang="greek">a)gw=nes</foreign> and need not have been put to death. There is an allusion in <foreign lang="la">aetas avocabat</foreign> to the exemption of <foreign lang="la">seniores</foreign> or men between 45 and 60 years of age from military service in the field.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Priamum ipsum</lemma>, a mock-heroic title for the eldest or chief of the accusers. Cicero should have chosen a Greek name rather than a Trojan, after <foreign lang="la">ferro Phrygio</foreign> above ; but Priam's name was a <foreign lang="la">perpetuum</foreign> <foreign lang="greek">e)pi/qeton</foreign> <foreign lang="la">apud tragicos Latinos</foreign> (Orelli). Some take <foreign lang="la">Priamum ipsum senem</foreign> as a second quotation from Ennius.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Antistium</lemma> cannot be identified.  Some understand <foreign lang="la">P. Antistius, rabula sane probabilis</foreign>, <gloss>a likely fellow enough as a stump orator,</gloss> whom we hear of in Brut. 226.  But Cicero there names him as one of the <foreign lang="la">patroni</foreign> of the time, not as an <foreign lang="la">accusator</foreign> ; and he fell, net in the Sullan prescriptions here alluded to, but previously under the younger Marius, as a partisan of Sulla, 82 B.C. : cf. Mommsen, 3.336. Also the words <foreign lang="la">etiam leges pugnare prohibebant</foreign> do not suit this Antistius, as they point to an accuser who had suffered the penalties of <foreign lang="la">infamia</foreign> (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>), and hence could not again act as accuser ; while P. Antistius appears to have acted as an orator shortly before his death. We hear in pro Balb. &sect; 48, of a L. Antistius, <foreign lang="la">disertus home</foreign>, who m B.C. 95 accused T. Matrinius of Speletum for false assumption of civic rights.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sescenti</lemma>, of indefinite numbers ; as in Att. 14. 12.1, <foreign lang="la">sescenta similia</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inter sicarios</lemma>, <ref n="n.,74" targOrder="U">Introd. note 74</ref>. Accusers who were wont to attack such crimes, were those most likely to be feared and slain by Sulla s assassins.


<pb n="41"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui omnes . . . viverent</lemma> shows Cicero's confidence in the strength of his case.  <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">canes</lemma>, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 56">56</bibl>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="91">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">verum</lemma>, i.e. <foreign lang="la">verum</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">etsi nihil mali est</foreign>, etc., <foreign lang="la">occisi sunt nam</foreign>), etc. <foreign lang="la">turba</foreign>, <gloss>commotion, confusion.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dum . . . erat occupatus</lemma>: this is here an imperfect tense, not pluperfect. <foreign lang="la">Dum</foreign> = <gloss>during the time that</gloss> more usually has a present (Roby 1661). Halm thinks the imperfect due to the fact that a long-continued or repeated state of things is spoken of.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">summam rerum</lemma> <gloss>the sum total of affairs, the whole business of the State </gloss> : de Rep. 1.42, <foreign lang="la">cum penes unum est omnium summa rerum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vulneribus</lemma>, i.e. private losses, the stings of avarice or desire for revenge, etc.  Cicero means that one way of healing such wounds often consisted in destroying the <foreign lang="la">accusatores.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ita</lemma>, correlative to <foreign lang="la">tamquam</foreign> : Verr. 2. 4. 75, <foreign lang="la">quasi face percussus est, ita flagrare coepit.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iudices</lemma>.  These, before Sulla's supremacy, consisted of the equites, of whom about 1,600 were proscribed by Sulla : Appian&lt;, B. Civ. 1.95 ; cf. Mommsen, 3.353.
</p>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc commodi est</lemma>, <gloss>there is this much advantage.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut . . . si cuperent . . . non possent</lemma>, <gloss>that, if they had wished, they could not have killed.</gloss>  In <foreign lang="la">possent</foreign> the subj. might seem to do double duty ; governed by <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>, and in the apodosis of an unreal condition (ap. &sect; 102, <foreign lang="la">misit . . . ut poneret</foreign>, note).  But without <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> the condition might regularly be put thus : <foreign lang="la">si cuperent . . . non poterant</foreign> ; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, note. Thus it is only <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> that necessitates the subjunctive.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut coepi dicere</lemma> = <gloss>as I began by saying</gloss> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 89">89</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quamvis diu</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 47">47</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possum</lemma>, lit. <gloss>I <emph>can</emph>. I have the power (but shall not use it).</gloss> In English we say, <gloss>I <emph>could</emph> (if I chose ; but I do not choose.)</gloss> Cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 107">107</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 135">135</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">transire</lemma> <foreign lang="la">leviter tangere</foreign>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 123">123</bibl>. So de Inv. 1.98, <foreign lang="la">transire breviter</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">studio . . . officio</lemma>.  The ablatives are adverbial : <gloss>intentionally accusing, defending as in duty bound.</gloss> Cf. Hor. Sat. 1. 4. 79 ; and <foreign lang="la">fraude</foreign> (=<foreign lang="la">fraudulenter) agere, furto fallere, consilio petere</foreign>= (on purpose), etc.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="92">
<milestone n="XXXIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">video causas esse . . . impellerent</lemma>, <gloss>I see that there <emph>are</emph> (perceptible <emph>now</emph>) many motives which might <emph>then</emph> have been urging him.</gloss>  A passage often noticed because of the non-sequence of tenses.  But the rule of sequence need not here apply. The direct statement would have been <foreign lang="la">causae multae istum impellerent</foreign>, <gloss>many motives might have been urging him,</gloss> <foreign lang="la">impellerent</foreign> being potential subj., implying an <gloss>if</gloss> dause, <gloss>if they had chanced to be operative,</gloss> or the like. When the statement is oblique after <foreign lang="la">video</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">esse</foreign> is a natural tense to use, as shown above ;  <foreign lang="la">impellerent</foreign>, the original subjunctive, is not changed. So in Vatin. 5, <foreign lang="la">quaero a te cur Cornelium non defenderem</foreign> :  I ask you why I was not to defend . . .'  The above explanation is on the lines suggested by Gildersleeve and Lodge 519, and seems the best. Some explain <foreign lang="la">esse</foreign> as imperf. infin.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">facultas</lemma> : de Inv. 1.41, <foreign lang="la">facultates sunt, aut quibus facilius fit aut sine quibus aliquid confici non potest.</foreign>  Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 68">68</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">amici . . . servi . . . tempus . . . locus.</foreign>


<pb n="42"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U"> quid ad rem?</lemma> sc. <foreign lang="la">id pertinet</foreign> ; as in Phil. 2. 72, <foreign lang="la">ius postulabas ; sed quid ad rem?  et alii multi</foreign>, sc. <foreign lang="la">Romae erant.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quasi nunc</lemma>, etc. (cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 47">47</bibl>, note), i.e. Cicero did not name the place of the murder in order to search all Rome (<foreign lang="la">tanta multitudine</foreign>) for the murderer, but as a crucial test applied to two given persons.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="93">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ceteras facultates</lemma>.  Cicero now shows that Magnus had a further <foreign lang="la">facultas</foreign> in being a professed <foreign lang="la">sicarius</foreign>, or in league with <foreign lang="la">sicarii</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commemoravit</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 80">80</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">opinor . . . occiderent</lemma>.  Cicero includes under <foreign lang="la">sicarii</foreign> besides the actual assassins, the men who employed them for avaricious purposes : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 80">80</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">eosdem fuisse sectores collorum et bonorum  aut . . . aut</foreign> implies that there was no <foreign lang="la">third</foreign> sub-division.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">eorum</lemma>, <gloss>consisting of those</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">genitivus definitivus</foreign>, Madvig, &sect; 286, Ohs. 3.  Cf. Verr. 2.5.156, <foreign lang="la">quid de illa multitudine dicamus eorum qui . . . producebantur?</foreign> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in bonis erant occupati</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">sc. emendis</foreign>, = <foreign lang="la">sectores</foreign>, <gloss>who did business in property.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si eos putas . . . sin eos</lemma>; i.e. from either point of view, Magnus was a <foreign lang="la">sicarius</foreign> or in league with <foreign lang="la">sicarii</foreign>  For <foreign lang="la">alienuot</foreign> as a subst., cf. Sall. Cat. 5.4, <foreign lang="la">alieni appetens, sui profusus.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in eo numero</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">in eorum numero</foreign>, as &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 126">126</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quo in numero</foreign> ; &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 124">124</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">sub quo nomine.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">leviore nomine</lemma>, <gloss>in gentler phrase,</gloss> as in Tusc. 1.95.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in cuius fide sint et clientela</lemma>, <gloss>under whose protection and patronage.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aliquem</lemma>, <gloss>some one or other </gloss> ; hinting at Chrysogonus.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="94">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid postea </lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 80">80</bibl>.  The ensuing sentences are in the so-called figure <foreign lang="la">altercatio</foreign> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 58">58</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ego</lemma> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 32">32</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non continuo</lemma>, <gloss>it does not follow that . . </gloss> ; cf. N&auml;gelsbach Lat. Stil. &sect; 185. l.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">absum a crimine</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 55">55</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quare</lemma>, <gloss>through which, </gloss> referring to <foreign lang="la">permulta</foreign>.  For the adverb instead of a pronoun, cf. ad Fam. 10. 21.1, <foreign lang="la">omnia feci quare . . . resisterem</foreign>, and the similar uses of <foreign lang="fr">dont,</foreign> <foreign lang="de">wo,</foreign> etc., in French and German.


<pb n="43"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">plures</lemma>, <gloss>a number of persons,</gloss> viz. all who had taken part in the proscriptions.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="95">
<milestone n="XXXIV" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sicut cetera</lemma>.  Supply <foreign lang="la">vidimus.</foreign> After examining the <foreign lang="la">causas quae T. Roscium impellerent</foreign>, and the <foreign lang="la">facultates suscipiendi maleficii</foreign>, Cicero now proceeds to the so-called <foreign lang="la">consecutio</foreign>, i.e. inferring the guilt or innocence of a suspected person from his behaviour after the event.  See pro Mi]. &sect; 61, Halm's note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dius Fidius  Mommsen</lemma>, 1. p. 174, identifies the god of good faith with Hercules.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cuicuimodi es</lemma>, euphem. for <foreign lang="la">quamvis sis homo nequam</foreign> : cf. Verr. 2.5.106, <foreign lang="la">non quo illum ipsum, cuicuimodi est, quisquam supplicio dignum putaret. cuicuimodi</foreign> is genit., substituted for the regular form for euphony.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ita . . . ut tibi omnino non pepercerim</lemma>, <gloss>in a way which involved my not sparing you </gloss> = at your expense.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod possim</lemma>.  For the subjunctive, cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quod sciam.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">oris tui</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>. The genit. is put as after simple verbs of remembering or forgetting ; Roby 1332.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">socii tui</lemma>, your confederates in the murder : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ex tot sicariis.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de morum praeda</lemma>.  The rule would require <foreign lang="la">de nta praeda</foreign>, but exceptions are found : cf. Verr. 2.1.86, <foreign lang="la">Milesios navem poposcit, quae eum praesidii causa Myndum prosequeretur</foreign> ; and <foreign lang="la">illorum</foreign> makes a stronger antithesis with <foreign lang="la">huius</foreign>  Similarly <foreign lang="la">ut . . . non</foreign> (instead of <foreign lang="la">ne</foreign>) before <foreign lang="la">sed</foreign>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="96">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">antea</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 19">19</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid attinuit</lemma>, <gloss>what object was there in,</gloss> etc. differing little from a simple <foreign lang="la">cur</foreign> : cf. Verr. 2.5. 169. <foreign lang="la">eum</foreign>, not the obj. after <foreign lang="la">attinuit</foreign>, but the subj . to <foreign lang="la">nuntiare.</foreign>


<pb n="44"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U"> si . . . inieras</lemma>: Cicero chooses to put the condition not as unfulfilled but as open : <gloss>assuming that you had formed no design.. . ,</gloss> hence the pluperf. indicative. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod . . . ad te minime omnium pertinebat.</lemma> Cicero pretends that the murder <gloss>did not concern </gloss> Magnus, because the deceased was his enemy: but the very fact of the <foreign lang="la">magnae rei familiaris controversiae</foreign> (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 87">87</bibl>) gave Magnus an interest in the death of the elder Roscius.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qua ratione</lemma>, <gloss>on what principle.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">liberi</lemma> does not imply that Sex. Roscius had left other children (see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 41">41</bibl>), as <foreign lang="la">liberi</foreign> is frequently used rhetorically for a single child : cf. de Imp. Pomp. &sect;33.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">optime convenientes</lemma>, <gloss>on the best of terms with him.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="97">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nihil est quod metuas</lemma>, <gloss>there is no reason for you to fear </gloss> : so &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 138">138</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">nihil est quod quisquam dicat.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">excutio</lemma>, of searching a person's dress : cf. Val. Max. 5.4, &sect; 7, <foreign lang="la">aditum filiae, sed diligenter excussae, ne quid cibi inferret, dedit.</foreign> The present tense is figurative, as though he still had the weapons upon him .
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si quid . . .  habuisti</lemma>, <gloss>in case you had . . </gloss> : theoretically an apodosis must be understood ; <gloss>I do not search you (so that I may find a weapon) if you had one.</gloss>  But in such expressions the apodosis was not distinctly conceived. Roby 1754.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non laboro </lemma>= <foreign lang="la">non curo. Unum hoc</foreign>, i.e. leave to ask the question <foreign lang="la">ubi aut unde audivit?</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tantum itineris</lemma> : see on &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 19">19</bibl>. <foreign lang="la">contendere</foreign>, <gloss>to traverse</gloss> ; rare in this sense with an accus. : cf. Virg. Aen. 5. 834, <foreign lang="la">contendere cursum.</foreign>  For an analogous use, see Hor. Ep. 1.1.28, <foreign lang="la">non possis oculo quantum contendere Lynceus</foreign>,  <gloss>you cannot reach as far with your eyesight.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="98">
<milestone n="XXXV" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">etiamne</lemma> asks an indignant question.


<pb n="45"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nonne</lemma>, etc. The passage is cited by the rhetorician Aquila Romanus, de Fig. Sent. &sect; 13, as an example of <foreign lang="greek">diatu/pwsis</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">descriptio</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">deformatio)</foreign>, i.e. graphic or dramatic style of narrative : cf. de Orat. 3. 202, <foreign lang="la">rerum quasi gerantur</foreign> sub <foreign lang="la">aspectum paene subiectio.</foreign>  The effect is heightened by the rapid succession of questions.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ignarum</lemma>, <gloss>without a suspicion of</gloss> : pro Planc. &sect; 40, <foreign lang="la">me ignaro, necopinante, inscio.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Automedontem</lemma>, the charioteer of Achilles, figurative term for a swift driver ; cf. Suvenal, 1. 61.  Iliad 16. 684 ; 17. 459, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">honoris causa</lemma>, <gloss>from personal regard for him</gloss> (the French <foreign lang="fr">en egard</foreign>) ; ironically for the simple <foreign lang="la">sua causa</foreign>, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 132">132</bibl>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="99">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quid erat . . .</lemma> <gloss>What reason was there for his wishing . . . ? </gloss> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nisi hoc</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">hoc tamen</foreign>. <foreign lang="la">Nisi</foreign> here is nearly equivalent to <foreign lang="la">sed</foreign> ; instances are frequent in the comic poets : cf. Pl. Rud. 751, <foreign lang="la">nescio nisi scio</foreign> ; Ter. Eun. 827, <foreign lang="la">nescio nisi credo.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="100">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">palmas </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, note. <foreign lang="la">lemniscatam</foreign> : Fest. p.115, <foreign lang="la">lemnisci, id est fasciolae coloriae</foreign> (coloured ribbons), <foreign lang="la">dependentes ex coronis.</foreign> The <foreign lang="la">lemnisci</foreign> were an additional mark of distinction, as a reward for a special victory : Auson. Epist. 5.20, <foreign lang="la">Et quae iamdudum tibi palma poetica pollet, Lemnisco ornata est, quo mea palma caret.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quae Roma ei deferatur</lemma>, <gloss>which is transmitted to him from Rome </gloss> : a figurative way of saying that the murder had been committed, unlike Capito's former crimes, in Rome ; and that it was the greatest of them all, since a gladiator would prize most highly a victory won in the capital. Cf. Phil. 2.11, <foreign lang="la">Sexta palma urbana etiam in gladiatore difficilis</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hominis occidendi</lemma>, in English <gloss>of murder</gloss> : cf. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 80">80</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 93">93</bibl>. Hor. Epist. 1. 2. 32, <foreign lang="la">ut iugulent hominem, surgunt de nocte latrones</foreign>. Cf. below, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 145">145</bibl>, where <foreign lang="la">hominem occidere</foreign> is in a different sense.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">habeo dicere</lemma>, <gloss>I am able to mention </gloss> ; as in de Nat. Deor. 3. 93, <foreign lang="la">haec fere dicere habiti de natura deorum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de ponte</lemma>.  Cicero alludes to a proverb well-known in his time, <foreign lang="la">sexagentarios de ponte</foreign>, <gloss>throw the sixty-year-old men from the bridge </gloss> He means, jestingly, that Capito's crime was all the worse because the man he threw was <emph>under</emph> sixty, in defiance of the proverb.  Whence did this strange saying originate?  Dr. Warde Fowler ("Roman Festivals," pp. 111-121, and "Religious Experience of the Roman People," pp.321-2) deals with the question, and his conclusions, which we may safely follow, may be summarised thus. Two explanations were current among the Romans (for even they were in doubt).  One of these may be at once set aside, though it deserves a mention. According to this view the <foreign lang="la">pons</foreign> of the proverb had nothing to do with the Tiber, but meant one of the <foreign lang="la">pontes</foreign> or gangways by which voters in the Comitia passed into the <foreign lang="la">ovile</foreign>, or enclosure for polling ; and it was said that men over sixty years of age were thrust from the <foreign lang="la">pontes</foreign> as no longer entitled to vote. Some learned Romans held this theory ; see Festtis, p.334.  But it is baseless ; the gangways were a late invention, whereas the proverb goes back to remote antiquity. The other explanation connected the proverb with a ceremony which it is well known took place in Rome.  (Cf. Nonius, p.533.)  On the ides of May the Vestal Virgins cast into the Tiber from the <foreign lang="la">pons sublicius</foreign> puppets made of rushes, resembling men bound hand and foot ; and a common notion as to this ceremony, in Rome, was that old men had in earlier days been offered in sacrifice, and that the puppets had been substituted for men in more merciful times : and so, it was thought, the proverb arose.  It did unquestionably arise from the ceremony of the puppets.  But that the "old ones" thrown had ever been <emph>human</emph> is very improbable : human sacrifice is far too contrary, on the whole, to the Roman character for this idea to be accepted as true.  Modern investigations show that this primeval ceremony, like many analogous rites elsewhere, represented, among other ideas, a <foreign lang="la">casting out of old things</foreign>, a dismissal of winter when spring had come, or the like.  In some rites of this kind the puppet used was called "the old one" ; in others, "the white man" : and in Rome the rush figures were named <foreign lang="la">Argei</foreign>, a word perhaps = <gloss>white</gloss> (<foreign lang="greek">a)rgh/s</foreign>), which might suit at once the colour of the rushes, and the conventional notion that <gloss>old ones,</gloss> human or otherwise, ought to be white-haired.  From this there could easily be a gradual transition to the idea that the puppet "old ones" represented human "old ones." With this proverb cf. the similar phrase <foreign lang="la">senes depontaiti</foreign> (Festus). For other details see Warde Fowler.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">atque adeo</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 29">29</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">audiet</lemma>.  The cross-examination of witnesses at Rome often grew into a formal trial of or an entire speech against a witness : cf. the extant speech against Vatinius, a witness in the trial of P. Sestius. So Cicero threatens to disclose all the crimes of Capito in the <foreign lang="la">testium interrogatio</foreign>, so as to shake his credit as a witness.


<pb n="46"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="101">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">volumen</lemma>, <gloss>roll.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pro testimonio</lemma>, <gloss>as evidence</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">gravitatem</lemma>, <gloss>personal weight</gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vitam</lemma>, <gloss>character, personage,</gloss> an exalted term for <foreign lang="la">virum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ius iurandum accommodetis</lemma>, <gloss>fit the claims of your oath to suit his evidence. </gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="102">
<milestone n="XXXVI" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">alter</lemma>, Magnus ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ex ipsa caede</lemma>, <gloss>immediately after</gloss> : cf. Tac. Germ. 22, <foreign lang="la">statim e somno lavantur.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut si cuperent . . . poneret</lemma>, lit. <gloss>so that, if all had been wishing, he would have been placing . . </gloss> <foreign lang="la">Cuperent</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">poneret</foreign> are precisely the tenses and moods we should have had if the sentence had not been governed by <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>  As it is, the subjunctive in <foreign lang="la">poneret</foreign> does double duty ; consecutive subj. after <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign>, and hypothetical subj. after a si-clause. This is allowed frequently when the tense is imperfect subj., as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 119">119</bibl> below, and Cic. Prov. Cons. 4, <foreign lang="la">civitas sic spoliata est ut, nisi Vergilius intervenisset, unum signum Byzantii . . . nullum haberent</foreign>.  See Roby 1521; Gildersleeve and Lodge 597. An original <foreign lang="la">pluperf.</foreign> subj. <foreign lang="la">posuisset</foreign> would have been turned into <foreign lang="la">positurus fuerit.</foreign>  Contrast with the present passage the clause in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl> above, ending <foreign lang="la">non possent</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">alter</lemma>, Capito  <foreign lang="la">si diis placet</foreign> expresses astonishment and indignation, as though the matter could not even be mentioned without an apology to the gods.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">utrum . . . credendum</lemma>:  Supply the alternative <foreign lang="la">necne  ac non</foreign>, <gloss>and not rather </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 92">92</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">comparatum est </lemma>= <foreign lang="la">institutum</foreign>, <gloss>it was laid down as a principle </gloss> : so &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 153">153</bibl> ; de Domo sua 77, <foreign lang="la">ius comparatum est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut vel in minimis rebus . . . non dicerent</lemma>, more commonly
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut ne minimis quidem in rebus dicerent</lemma> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">unus puer . . . relictus non est</foreign>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="103">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tertiam partem orbis terrarum</lemma>, a rhetorical exaggeration.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si ageretur . . .  diceret</lemma>, <gloss>if an affair of his own had been in hand he would not have given evidence.</gloss> The imperf. subj. need not imply that Africanus never really found himself so situated. His contemporaries would have said, <foreign lang="la">si . . . agatur, non . . . dicat</foreign>, the contingency being a possible one. Cicero, from a later standpoint, puts their pres. subj. into the imperf., with the same idea of possibility. The subjunctive in either tense is <gloss>prospective,</gloss> as Prof. Sonnensehein well calls it. He cites Livy 21.5.11, <foreign lang="la">invicta acies</foreign> si aequo <foreign lang="la">dimicaretur campo</foreign> (Class. Rev. 1897).


<pb n="47"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">crederetur</lemma>, impersonal ; its object would be a dative, <foreign lang="la">ei</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">testimonio</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="104">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid tu?</lemma> Cicero addresses Magnus direct, who had tried to interrupt him or made a gesture of indignation at the plain statement of Capito's guilt, <foreign lang="la">occidendum, curarit.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ne tibi desis </lemma>(<foreign lang="la">tibi</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">tua</foreign> are emphasized) = <gloss>you must think of yourself, not only of Capito </gloss> Cf. Hor. Sat. 1.9.56, <foreign lang="la">haud mihi deero.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">audaciter</lemma> : so spelt here by Cicero (see Priscian, 15.21) for the commoner syncon. form <foreign lang="la">audacter</foreign> ; on which Quintilian  (1. 6. 17) says, <foreign lang="la">inhaerent quidam molestissima diligentiae</foreign> (pedantry) <foreign lang="la">perversitate, ut audaciter potius dicant quam audacter</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">neque accusatore mute quisquam utitur</lemma> : i.e. if you are an accuser (see <ref n="7" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 7</ref>), you ought to have spoken against Sextus in due course, and not to have sat silent by the real accuser's side.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">paulo tamen</lemma>, <gloss><emph>at least</emph> a little more hidden </gloss> ; <gloss>bad <emph>though it be, yet still</emph> a little more hidden.</gloss> Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">esset</lemma>, Sc. <foreign lang="la">si istic non sederes.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">a nobis</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 85">85</bibl>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="105">
<milestone n="XXXVII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quadriduo quo </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 20">20</bibl>, notes.


<pb n="48"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">municipem</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 47">47</bibl>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="106">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suspiciosum</lemma>, <gloss>merely a matter of conjecture,</gloss> as opposed to <foreign lang="la">perspicuum</foreign> : cf. Auct. ad Her. 2. &sect; 11, <foreign lang="la">cum multa concurrant argumenta et signa quae inter se consentiant, rem perspicuam, non suspiciosam videri oportere.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non enim ita disputabo</lemma>, in antithesis with <foreign lang="la">certo scio</foreign> below. Cicero says, <gloss>I will not argue for the <emph>probability</emph> that Chrysogonus got his information from the two Roscii, for it is a known fact ; they admit it themselves.</gloss> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">erat enim</lemma>, etc., and <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nam cum</lemma>, etc., hint two reasons which <foreign lang="la">might</foreign> be given for the probability, but are let pass ; an instance of the figure <foreign lang="la">praeteritio</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">occupatio</foreign> ; cf. Auct. ad Her. 4. &sect; 37. Note that <foreign lang="la">nam cum</foreign>, etc., is not a reason for <foreign lang="la">erat antea amicitia</foreign>, but a second reason for <foreign lang="la">verisimile est Roscios detulisse</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum multos veteres </lemma>. . . <gloss>though the Roscii had many patrons and guest-friends through ties long since inherited from their ancestors ...</gloss> The ties of <foreign lang="la">patrocinium</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">hospitium</foreign> were hereditary.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="107">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possum</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 91">91</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">indicii partem</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">partem praedae</foreign> below ; <foreign lang="la">indicii</foreign>, not the information itself, but the thing about which information was given.  On the other hand, cf. Ulp. Dig. 12. 5. 4, <foreign lang="la">si tibi indicium dedero ut futitivum meum indices</foreign>, where <foreign lang="la">indicium</foreign> = <gloss>regard for</gloss> your information. So <foreign lang="la">lis</foreign> in Liv. 3.72= <foreign lang="la">id de quo lis erat.</foreign> Clark gives <foreign lang="la">indici causa partem.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Qui sunt igitur in istis</lemma>, <gloss>Who are the persons, then, in the case of these goods, to whom Chrysogonos has given a share?</gloss> (Stock's translation. ) The subj. <foreign lang="la">dederit</foreign> characterises : <gloss>Who are such persons as fit the description "recipients from Chrysogonus ?" </gloss>,  So <foreign lang="la">acceperit</foreign> above.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="108">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">age nunc</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 48">48</bibl> 814) init.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iudicio</lemma>: sarcastic. Chrysogonus has convicted the Roscii of the murder, by rewarding them so richly.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pugna</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>


<pb n="49"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">satis fuit</lemma>, <gloss>it <emph>would have been</emph> enough.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">denique</lemma>, <gloss>at most,</gloss> as in Hor. Ep. ad Pis. 267, <foreign lang="la">vitavi denique culpam, non laudem merui.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">honoris</lemma>, <gloss>acknowledgment, douceur,</gloss> in which sense <foreign lang="la">honorarium</foreign> was used later. Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 135">135</bibl>, Verr. 2. 1.38, <foreign lang="la">ei postea praemia tamen liberaliter tribuit ; habuit honorem ut proditori</foreign> ; ad Fam. xvi. 9.3, <foreign lang="la">Curio misi, ut medico honos haberetur</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praedia tantae pecuniae</lemma> : cf. Verr. 11.4.88, <foreign lang="la">signum</foreign> (a statue) <foreign lang="la">magnae pecuntae.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">manubias</lemma>, <gloss>spoils taken in war,</gloss> instead of <foreign lang="la">praedam</foreign>, to carry out the figure of <foreign lang="la">ista pugna.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">re cognita</lemma>, emphatic, <gloss>when he knew what they had done.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="109">
<milestone n="XXXVIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">decem primis</lemma>, <ref n="n.,31" targOrder="U">Introd. note 31</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">integrum</lemma>, <gloss>inviolable.</gloss> So sometimes <foreign lang="la">infectus</foreign> = impossible, <foreign lang="la">invictus</foreign> = invincible, <foreign lang="la">involatus</foreign> = inviolable, <foreign lang="la">intactus</foreign> = not to be touched, <foreign lang="la">inaccessus</foreign> = inaccessible. N&auml;gelsbach, Lat. Stil. 72 b. 2.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">indicatote</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 18">18</bibl>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="110">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">palam</lemma>, i.e. before Sulla.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">auctore</lemma>, <gloss>at his advice, suggestion</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">intercessore</foreign>, <gloss>he undertaking the matter, on his security </gloss> ; not = <foreign lang="la">impediente</foreign>, but in the sense of one who represents or acts for another. Capito undertook that the object of the <foreign lang="la">legati</foreign> should be attained. So Halm ; otherwise explained as =<gloss> owing to his interference.</gloss>


<pb n="50"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non adlerunt</lemma>, <gloss>did not demand admittance.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">fide</lemma>, <gloss>promise</gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">perfidia</lemma>, <gloss>neglect of it </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 116">116</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">testimonium eis denuntiare</lemma> ; lit. <gloss>signify to them evidence,</gloss> i.e. that they will be required to give evidence.  Witnesses at Rome were either <foreign lang="la">necessarii</foreign> (obliged to bear witness) or <foreign lang="la">voluntarii.</foreign> The former were recognized only in criminal cases, and could be compelled to appear only by the accuser, not by the accused. Hence the words <foreign lang="la">si occusator voluerit</foreign>, in which there is a covert <foreign lang="la">sed nolet.</foreign> Cf. Quintil. 5.7.9 : <foreign lang="la">duo genera sunt testium, aut voluntariorum aut eorum quibus iudex in iudiciis publicis lege denuntiare solet, quorum altero pars utraque utitur, alterum accusatoribus tantum concessum est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">re certa</lemma>, <gloss>an accomplished fact.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="111">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rem mandatam </lemma>: a matter entrusted to a person's charge ; a commission.  A <foreign lang="la">mandatum</foreign> was a contract by which one person undertook to transact an affair for another without remuneration : of the two parties, the former was termed by the jurists <foreign lang="la">mandatarius</foreign>, by Cicero <foreign lang="la">is cui mandatur</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">qui mandatum recipit</foreign> ; the latter <foreign lang="la">mandans</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">mandator</foreign>, by Cicero <foreign lang="la">qui mandat</foreign>. The Romans classed <foreign lang="la">mandatum</foreign> among the so-called consensual contracts, i.e. those which were entered on merely <foreign lang="la">consensu</foreign>, by mutual agreement. The <foreign lang="la">mandatarius</foreign> was bound to execute the affair with the <foreign lang="la">diligentia diligentis patris familias</foreign> ; if he overlooked it, the <foreign lang="la">mandans</foreign> could bring an <foreign lang="la">actio mandati</foreign>, if he had been injured either intentionally (<foreign lang="la">dolo malo</foreign>, in Cicero <foreign lang="la">malitiose</foreign>), or through neglect (<foreign lang="la">culpa</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">neglegentia</foreign>, the opposite of <foreign lang="la">diligentia</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non modo malitiosius verum etiam negiegentius</lemma>. Note the position of the adversative particles, next to the specially contrasted words.  So placed in English, they would combine <foreign lang="la">malitiosius</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">neglegentius</foreign> into one idea, and make no sense. To give the required sense we put them at the head of the two clauses : <gloss>not only if a man had culpably mismanaged, but even if he had merely neglected . . . our ancestors thought,</gloss> etc. Cf. pro Deiot. 15, <foreign lang="la">tanto scelere non modo perfecto, sed</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">etiam cogitato</lemma>. Madvig, &sect; 461 b, Obs. 2. <foreign lang="la">malitiosius</foreign> : in the comparative, only to answer to <foreign lang="la">neglegentius</foreign> ; for <foreign lang="la">malitiose gerere</foreign> was punishable in all cases, irrespective of degree.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iudicium non minus turpe quam furti</lemma>. A <foreign lang="la">turpe iudicium</foreign> was one which brought <foreign lang="la">infamia</foreign> upon the offender if found guilty : cf. pro Cluent. 119, <foreign lang="la">turpi iudicio damnati omni honore ac dignitate privantur</foreign> ; and a <foreign lang="la">iudicium mandati</foreign>, or trial for neglect of a commission, was of this class, as much as a trial for theft.  Under the republic a man convicted of theft, besides restoring twice or four times the value of the stolen goods according as the theft was <foreign lang="la">nec mansfestum</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">manifestum</foreign>, suffered <foreign lang="la">infamia.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">operae nostrae . . .</lemma> <gloss>the good faith of friends is substituted in place of our own exertions.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">gubernetur</lemma>, <gloss>may be promoted.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="112">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">officio . . . officis</lemma>; there is a play on the two meanings; <gloss>by a pretended service you do a disservice to . . .</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de medio</lemma>, Sc. <foreign lang="la">stadio</foreign> ; a term perhaps borrowed from the language of games : cf. Herod. 8.22, <foreign lang="greek">e)k tou= me/sou h(mi=n e(/zesqe</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suscipis onus . . .</lemma>  The clue to this difficult passage is found by taking the verbs in the 2nd person throughout the section as addressed, not to Capito specially, but to the typical rash man who rushes in where the <foreign lang="la">vir gravis</foreign> would fear to tread.  <gloss>You undertake the burden of a service which you think you can support : but the burden seems most heavy, i.e. serious, to those who are least light, i.e. frivolous, worthless, themselves.</gloss>  Professor Clark accepts the emendation <foreign lang="la">maxime</foreign> (given in the text) for MSS. <foreign lang="la">minime</foreign> ; and supports the 2nd person in a general sense by comparing Cat. 2. 18, <foreign lang="la">tu agris tu aedificus . . . ornatus</foreign>, etc.  Halm-Sternkopf (1910) also takes it as general. To take the 2nd person as definitely referring to Capito and his misdeed involves the difficulty that, so far from <gloss>thinking he could</gloss> support the burden, Capito always meant not to support it. Other emendations, less satisfactory, are <foreign lang="la">non posse ; minime leve</foreign>


<pb n="51"/>
 

<milestone n="XXXIX" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">credidisset</lemma>, without object, = <foreign lang="la">fidem habuisset</foreign>, as in Tusc. 5.58.  Richter compares &sect; 59 <foreign lang="la">defensurus esset</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 61">61</bibl> <foreign lang="la">iudicare</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 70">70</bibl> <foreign lang="la">prohibere</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">admonere</foreign>, etc., used absolutely.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="113">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Itane est </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 34">34</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">commendatae</lemma>, stronger form for <foreign lang="la">mandatae</foreign> (so <foreign lang="la">concreditae</foreign> for <foreign lang="la">creditae</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inter vivos numerabitur </lemma>: i.e. he deserves to count for dead as a citizen. The same expression is used of a dishonoured citizen, pro Quinct. 49, <foreign lang="la">cuius bona venierunt, cuius . . . etiam victus vestitusque necessarius sub praeconem cum dedecore subiectus est, is non modo ex numero vivorum exturbatur, sed si fieri potest, infra etiam mortuoa amandatur.</foreign> Cf. post Red. ad Quir. 10.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">etiam neglegentia . . . vocatur</lemma>, <gloss>even mere neglect is compelled to meet an accusation for breach of trust and a trial with the penalty of dishonour. </gloss> <foreign lang="la">Crimen mandati</foreign> = an accusation for (breach of) trust, like <foreign lang="la">iudicium mandati</foreign>, &sect; l 11, where see notes.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si recte fiat</lemma>, <gloss>if all were done as it should be.</gloss> Cicero says, it is the giver of a commission, not the receiver, who may take no concern about it (<foreign lang="la">neglegere</foreign>) ; since the former has transferred the whole care to the latter.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">publice</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 25">25</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">decurionum decretum statim fit</foreign>, and &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 115">115</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">legationis ipsius</lemma>.  Cicero regards an embassy as the most sacred form of a <foreign lang="la">mandatum</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">maculaque adfecerit</lemma>, instead of the more common <foreign lang="la">adsperserit</foreign> (pro Planc. 30), for a play on <foreign lang="la">poena adficietur.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="114">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ei</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">i.e. Capitoni</foreign> ; fidem suam, i.e. Capito<gloss>s own credit</gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">interponeret</lemma>, <gloss>stake </gloss> ; decideret, <gloss>strike a bargain </gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ille</lemma>, Capito.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inque eam rem</lemma>. Cicero more often writes <foreign lang="la">in eamque rem.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">recepisset</lemma>, <gloss>had undertaken, promised.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per arbitrum</lemma>. There were many lawsuits which depended on considerations of equity and the weighing of circumstances, and in which the judge could give his own opinions free play. Such of these cases as dealt with matters of good faith (<foreign lang="la">bonae fidei negotia</foreign>) were called <foreign lang="la">arbitria</foreign> (or <foreign lang="la">bonae fidei iudicia</foreign>), and the judge <foreign lang="la">arbiter.</foreign>  One of this class was the <foreign lang="la">iudicium mandati</foreign> ; hence <foreign lang="la">per arbitrum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rem restitueret</lemma>, <gloss>make restitution, pay damages.</gloss> Cf. Paullus in Dig. L. 16.75, <foreign lang="la">restituere is videtur, qui id restituit quod habiturus esset actor</foreign> (the plaintiff) <foreign lang="la">si controversia ei facta non esset.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">honestatem</lemma> (<gloss>good name </gloss> ) <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">amitteret</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">infamis fieret.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="115">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nunc</lemma>, <gloss>as it is </gloss> =<foreign lang="greek">nu=n de\</foreign> : as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 148">148</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">publice</lemma>, <gloss>in the name of the <foreign lang="la">municipium</foreign> </gloss>: cf. <foreign lang="la">voluntatem decurionum ac muiticipum</foreign> below.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ex eo</lemma>, <gloss>out of all this,</gloss> sc. <foreign lang="la">fama, vita, bonis.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">paulum nescio quid</lemma>, <gloss>a small trifle</gloss> : cf. de Or. n 95, <foreign lang="la">paullum aliquid</foreign> (literally, not <gloss>some small thing,</gloss> but <gloss>a small something</gloss>). In both cases <foreign lang="la">paullum</foreign> is adjectival, and the pronoun substantival ; otherwise it would be <foreign lang="la">paulli aliquid</foreign> (cf. <foreign lang="la">pulcri aliquid, quiddam novi</foreign>, etc.), or else <foreign lang="la">paullum aliquod</foreign>


<pb n="52"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="116">
<milestone n="XL" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">videto</lemma>, etc. Infidelity to Sex. Roscius, represented as neglect of a <foreign lang="la">mandatum</foreign>, was the first aspect (c. XXXIX.) of Capito's guilt as emissary ; the next aspect (c. XL.) is infidelity to his co-emissaries, <foreign lang="la">socii.</foreign> A <foreign lang="la">societas</foreign> or association of several persons for a common object, especially for mercantile purposes, belonged, like <foreign lang="la">mandatum</foreign>, to the consensual contracts (&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 111">111</bibl>); and virtually the same regulations were current for both.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rem communicavit</lemma>, <gloss>has entered into partnership</gloss> : cf. Verr. 2.3.50, <foreign lang="la">socii putandi sunt quos inter res communicata est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">per eius fidem</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">datam nec servatam</foreign> ; <gloss>to whose good faith shall he have recourse, when he is injured through the bad faith of the man to whom he has entrusted himself? </gloss> <foreign lang="la">Fides</foreign> takes its colour from the context, as often ; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 110">110</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">istius fide ac potius peifidia decepti.</foreign>  Cic. de Inv. 1.71, <foreign lang="la">qui saepenumero nos per fidem deceperunt, eorum orationi fidem habere non debemus.</foreign>; Seneca, de Prov. 3.7, <foreign lang="la">multa milia civium Rom. uno loco post fidem, immo per ipsam fidem trucidata.</foreign> Note the expressive subj. <foreign lang="la">commiserit</foreign>, implying <gloss><emph>though</emph> he entrusted,</gloss> etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad alienos</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">ad</foreign> =<gloss> in the direction of, towards.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">multa apertiora videant</lemma>.  One would expect <foreign lang="la">intimis multa apertiora sint</foreign>, or <foreign lang="la">intimi multa apertius videant.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">etiam</lemma>, with <foreign lang="la">metuimus</foreign>, in contrast to <foreign lang="la">cavere</foreign> : <gloss>if we do but <emph>fear</emph> him,</gloss> etc.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="117">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rei pecuniariae </lemma>: pecuniary matters were the most usual object of a <foreign lang="la">societas</foreign>, which in such cases was called <foreign lang="la">societas quaestus et lucri</foreign>  <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui de eius scelere . . . </lemma> <foreign lang="la">qui</foreign> goes with the first three verbs that follow ; its antecedent with the fourth.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">parum</lemma>, with <foreign lang="la">cauti</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">providi</foreign>


<pb n="53"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">terret etiam</lemma>, <gloss>still keeps us in fear. </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ornatus</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl> fin. Note the concessive sense of the participle: <gloss>though adorned.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">flagitiis</lemma>, <gloss>disgraceful actions</gloss> ; <foreign lang="la">maleficium</foreign>, <gloss>crime,</gloss> viz. the murder.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="118">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc quidem</lemma>, sc. the <foreign lang="la">scelus</foreign> : <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod</lemma>, relative pronoun, but adversative, <gloss>but it</gloss> ; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quod certum est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inteUegatur</lemma>, <gloss>is to be inferred </gloss> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 25">25</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si quo de</lemma>, as in de Inv. 1.41, <foreign lang="la">quod simile erit ei negotio, quo de agitur.</foreign> Here the object of the transposition is to bring <foreign lang="la">quo (=aliquo</foreign>) next to <foreign lang="la">si</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dubitabitur . . . convincatur</lemma>, impersonal.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid tandem</lemma>. Supply (not <foreign lang="la">sequitur</foreign>, but) <foreign lang="la">videtur nobis</foreign>, from what follows.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">lanista</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>. <foreign lang="la">a gladio recessisse</foreign> ; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 126">126</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ab armis recessesse.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hic</lemma> is put instead of <foreign lang="la">iste</foreign> (though not meaning the defendant) as an antithesis to <foreign lang="la">ille</foreign> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 17">17</bibl>, note. The comparison serves to lead to the transition to Roscius Magnus, &sect; 119.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="119">
<milestone n="XLI" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">iam antea </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>. <foreign lang="la">ab</foreign> (from) <foreign lang="la">istis ab adversarus</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl> ; in both places Magnus is specified as answering the request, as being the bailiff of Chrysogonus.


<pb n="54"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qui postulabant </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">res ipsa</lemma>, <gloss>the request in itself.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tales putantur</lemma> : present, in spite of <foreign lang="la">postulabant</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">vixerunt</foreign> ; the imperfect might have implied that their reputation was <foreign lang="la">now</foreign> lost.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nemo esset . . . </lemma>; as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 102">102</bibl> the subjunctives do double duty ; <gloss>that there would have been no one who would not have thought . . .</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="120">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum</lemma>, <gloss>at the moment when </gloss> ; joined with the present tense, as <foreign lang="la">dum</foreign>, though the construction is very rare.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">oppugnari</lemma>, with <foreign lang="la">ne</foreign> following, like verbs of hindering, <foreign lang="la">repugnari</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">obsisti</foreign>, etc. Cf. pro Lig. 13, <foreign lang="la">id ne impetremus oppugnabis?</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod vero</lemma>, <gloss>but inasmuch as . . .</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in dominos quaeri</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">at si quaeritur . . . in dominum quaeritur</lemma>.  The reading is uncertain, but the general meaning is clear : the opponent defends the non-surrender of the slaves, by the argument <foreign lang="la">in dominos quaeri de servis iniqunni est</foreign>, as if Sex. Roscius was the <foreign lang="la">dominus</foreign> ; Cicero replies that he is no longer the <foreign lang="la">dominus</foreign>, for his property has passed into the hands of Chrysogonus, Magnus, and Capito.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum Chrysogono sunt</lemma> ; a new argiiment : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>.  <gloss>They are the attendatits on the powerful favourite of the dictator, and cannot be exposed to the risk of torture.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">puerulos</lemma>, <gloss>delicate, effeminate boys.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">elegantissimis</lemma>, <gloss>highly trained.</gloss> Perhaps of Greek origin. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">homines paene</lemma>, <gloss>men who are scarcely above labourers, of Amerian (= country) training under a rustic householder.</gloss>


<pb n="55"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="121">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut</lemma> follows <foreign lang="la">veri simile est</foreign> only in a negative sentence or in a question expecting a negative answer : see Madvig &sect; 374, Obs. 2.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut . . . cognorit</lemma>; i.e. probably there had been neither time nor opportunity for this.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="122">
<milestone n="XLII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">meministis me distribuisse </lemma>; <foreign lang="la">memini</foreign> is followed by the pres. infin. even of a past event. when the person witnessed it ; by the perf. infin. when he did not witness it but can vouch for its having happened. Here, then, we expect <foreign lang="la">distribuere.</foreign> But by the perf. infin. Cicero lays a momentary stress on the fact that the thing happened, not on the fact that the jurors wititessed it.  The sense is, <gloss>you bear in mind the fact that I subdivided</gloss> ; not, <gloss>you heard me and can remember how I subdivided </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in crimen et in audaciam</lemma> ; a remarkable abbreviation for <foreign lang="la">in criminis refutationem et in audaciae impugnationem.</foreign>


<pb n="56"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="123">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dixit initio</lemma>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">possunt</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 9">9</bibl> l, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">diligenter</lemma>, <gloss>accurately,</gloss> i.e. proving everything in detail.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si coepero . . . sit disserendum</lemma>; the difference of mood in protasis and apodosis may be thus explained : <foreign lang="la">suspicionibus de quibus . . . disserendum sit</foreign> = <gloss>suspicions <emph>such as</emph> must be treated of at greater length.</gloss> This apodosis need not affect the mood of the protasis which is a mere parenthesis.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ingeniis coniecturaeque</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">per sententias.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="124">
<milestone n="XLIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nomen aureum Clirysogoni</lemma>, periphrasis for <foreign lang="la">ad Chrysogonum.</foreign> In <foreign lang="la">aureum</foreign> there is an allusion not only to the name (<gloss>gold-born</gloss>), but also to the wealth amassed by Chrysogonus through the proscriptions.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sub quo nomine</lemma> =<foreign lang="la">sub cuius nomine</foreign>, as in Verr. 2.5.177, <foreign lang="la">quam</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">legem</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">non is promulgavit, quo nomine proscriptam videtis</foreign> ; so <foreign lang="la">eo nomine</foreign> freq. = <foreign lang="la">eius rei nomine</foreign> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 93">93</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">in eo numero</foreign>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">latuit</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">manceps fit Chrysogonus.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nihil attinet</lemma> ; i.e. which I care nothing for.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">In communem causam sectorum</lemma> ; i.e. I have no wish to attack the <foreign lang="la">sectores</foreign> as a body.

<pb n="57"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="125">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qua ratione </lemma><gloss>on what principle</gloss> : cf. &sect;96.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si . . . audientur</lemma>, etc. The meaning seems to be this:  Cicero is discussing the purchase merely as <emph>illegal</emph> because the late owner had not been proscribed, not as <emph>unjust</emph> because he was an inoffensive man ; and he says, If complaints of this latter kind (viz. <foreign lang="la">hominis innocentis bona veniisse</foreign>) shall ever (in happier times) be freely discussed and listened to, there will be more distinguished men than Sex. Roscius to complain about.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sIve Valeria est sive Cornelia</lemma> : see <ref n="n.,21" targOrder="U">Introd. note 21</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non enim novi nec scio</lemma>.  <gloss>For I am not acquainted with it, and so do not know which it is </gloss> is Stock's translation.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="126">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">In adversariorum praesidiis </lemma>= <gloss>within the enemy's lines, outposts</gloss>: see pro Lig. 27, Halm's note, and cf. pro Caec. 83, <foreign lang="la">in meis castris praesidusque versaris.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si lege</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">occisus est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">veteres leges</lemma>, by which it was forbidden to kill a <foreign lang="la">homo liber</foreign> wilfully and with hostile intent, <foreign lang="la">dolo malo</foreign> (see pro Mu. &sect; 10 sqq.), but permitted to kill a <foreign lang="la">homo sacer</foreign>, a <foreign lang="la">perduellis</foreign>, and one who lay under <foreign lang="la">aquae et ignis interdictio.</foreign> There is no allusion to the <foreign lang="la">leges Porcias</foreign> and <foreign lang="la">Sempronias</foreign>, which forbade the slaying of a citizen <foreign lang="la">iniussu populi.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quo modo</lemma>, <gloss>in what way,</gloss> i.e. as the property of a proscribed person, or as that of an enemy, or on what other principle : <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qua lege</lemma>, <gloss>by what law,</gloss> since those just mentioned do not authorize it.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="127">
<milestone n="XLIV" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quem vis</lemma>, sc. <foreign lang="la">in quem vis</foreign>  Cicero often omits a monosyllabic preposition with the relative, when the same preposition is used just before in the demonstrative clause : cf. Tusc. 1.111, <foreign lang="la">esse cum aliquo sensu in iis malis, quibus vulgo opinantur</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">oratio mea</lemma>, <gloss>my express statement </gloss> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 21">21</bibl> sqq.

<pb n="58"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">. . . ut ementiretur . . . fingeret . . . diceret</lemma>, <gloss>namely, making false statements . . . pretending . . . saying,</gloss> etc. The clauses with <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> do not express an intention, but explain <foreign lang="la">omnia</foreign> ; for this explanatory use of <foreign lang="la">ut</foreign> cf. the phrases <foreign lang="la">in eo esse ut, est ut</foreign> (<gloss>it is the fact that</gloss>), <foreign lang="la">tantum abest ut</foreign>, etc. <foreign lang="la">Ementiretur</foreign> is without object, as in Cic. Part. Or. 50, <foreign lang="la">dolorem fugientes multi in tormentis ementiti persaepe sunt.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut . . . passus non sit</lemma>, <gloss>not having allowed </gloss> ; the change of tense distinguishes the general result from the repeated efforts which led to it. Sternkopf also remarks that Cicero would avoid <foreign lang="la">non pateretur</foreign> as ending like an hexameter.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">postea</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 132">132</bibl>, note on <foreign lang="la">Erucius.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="128">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Kalendas Iunias </lemma>; i.e. the 1st of June is named in the law as the <foreign lang="la">dies</foreign> (date), <foreign lang="la">ad quam diem . . . fiant.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">haec bona</lemma>, i.e. the proceeds of the sale (<foreign lang="la">sectio</foreign>) of this property; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nulla redierunt</lemma>, <gloss>were not entered at all</gloss> : a combination of two constructions, <foreign lang="la">nulla bona ex hic redierunt</foreign>, and <foreign lang="la">haec bona non redierunt.</foreign> Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 54">54</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tabulas publicas</lemma>, <gloss>the State accounts.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">facetius</lemma>, <gloss>more smartly </gloss> (not <gloss>more wittily, drolly</gloss>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">corruptae aliqua ratione</lemma> ; e.g. by a false entry of the proceeds of the sale amongst the receipts got in before the 1st of June.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">reduviam curem</lemma>, <gloss>attend to a hangnail on the finger,</gloss> a proverbial phrase. Cicero calls the property of Sex. Roscius a trivial matter, when the immediate question is to save his life (<foreign lang="la">caput</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">non ullius</lemma> instead of <foreign lang="la">nuflius</foreign>, for the sake of the <foreign lang="la">anaphora</foreign> of <foreign lang="la">non</foreign> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 29">29</bibl>, last note, and cf. pro Cluent. &sect; 39. Join <foreign lang="la">non ullius . . . sui commodi</foreign> <gloss>takes account of no advantage of his own.</gloss>


<pb n="59"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="129">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sensu ac dolore</lemma>, <gloss>painful feeling </gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>,
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sententias iusque iurandum</lemma>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quae . . . pertinent</lemma>.  The indicative implies <gloss>the facts which do actually concern </gloss> ; on the other hand, <foreign lang="la">quid . . . velit et qua . . . contentus sit</foreign> is said from the jurors'  point of view: <gloss>you will hear all that has reference to the case, and (at the same time learn) what Roscius wishes to have said in his defence</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">qua condicione</lemma>, <foreign lang="la">sc.</foreign> mere acquittal from the charge of parricide.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">In extrema</lemma>, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 143">143</bibl> sqq.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="130">
<milestone n="XLV" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mea sponte </lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 129">129</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">animi mei sensu ac dolore</foreign> ; &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 143">143</bibl> sqq. <foreign lang="la">remoto</foreign>, i.e. without regarding him.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">civis optimi</lemma>, <gloss>most loyal </gloss> ; not in a moral sense : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">conferri</lemma>, <gloss>all these responsibilities to be heaped on his patron . . . </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nihil egerit</lemma>. The future perf. expresses the result of future actions : <gloss>he will find that he has gained nothing.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">partim invito</lemma>, Madvig's conjecture ; the MSS. give only one <foreign lang="la">partim</foreign>, which demands another before or after. With it we want a word in the sense of <foreign lang="la">invito</foreign> ; notice Prof. Clark's far superior suggestion <foreign lang="la">improbante</foreign>, <gloss>disapproving</gloss> ; the scribe would more easily confuse this with <foreign lang="la">imprudente</foreign> and omit it. And the assonance confirms it, as above in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 22">22</bibl>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="131">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">placet</lemma>, <gloss>is it pleasing, is it as it should be?</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pernicii</lemma> ; so spelt here by Cicero, according to Gellius and Nonius ; the grammarian Charisius read <foreign lang="la">pernicies</foreign> ; MSS. <foreign lang="la">pernicie</foreign>  All three forms of the genitive are found.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">magnitudine rerum</lemma> : <foreign lang="la">magnitudine</foreign> seems said rather than <foreign lang="la">necessitate</foreign>, to answer to <foreign lang="la">propter magnitudinem rerum</foreign> above, which as referring to Sulla =<gloss> on account of the immensity of his affairs.</gloss> Here <foreign lang="la">rerum</foreign> = <gloss>nature.</gloss> The comparison of Sulla to Iuppiter is lame, since it was not the wide scope of Iuppiter's rule which prevented his checking harmful effects of nature, but, as the ancients thought, the immutability of the natural laws themselves.


<pb n="60"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nisi hoc . . .</lemma> <gloss>unless, forsooth, it is marvellous that the human mind has not attained to what divine power cannot compass</gloss>.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="132">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nomen deferendum </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cuius honoris</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 98">98</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Erucius</lemma>. Here there is a great lacuna in the MSS., in which only a few unconnected words are preserved. From the following words of the Scholiast, a fairly safe conjecture may be made as to the contents : <foreign lang="la">hoc enim dicebat Chrysogonus: "non quia timui ne mihi tollerentur bona Roscii, ideo eius praedia dissipavi, sed quia aedificabam, in Veientanam ideo de his transtuli"</foreign>; viz., that here Cicero discussed the question opened in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 127">127</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">omnino haec bona non venusse</foreign>, i.e. whether the sale of the property had ever really taken place. If Cicero could show that it had not, he would deprive his opponents of even that vestige of a legal footing. The words of the Scholiast go to show that Cicero had inferred that there had been no sale, from the <foreign lang="la">dissipatio</foreign> of the property, since property legally come by would not be squandered in such nervous haste.  Cicero seems then to have passed to a description of Chrysogonus' wealth and arrogance, the opening words of which are given by the Scholiast, <foreign lang="la">hic ego audire istos cupio</foreign> : on which he remarks, <foreign lang="la">in hoc capite de potentia Chrysogoni invidiam facit, ut enumeret singula deliciarum genera, quod habeat plures possessiones, mancipia, quae omnia dicit de rapinis ipsum habere.</foreign>


<milestone n="XLVI" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">aptam </lemma>: Lambinus supplies <foreign lang="la">hi domum aptam</foreign>, etc. ; apparently the end of a comparison between the requirements of Chrysogonus and those of Sulla's more modest freedmen.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Sallentinis . . . Bruttiis</lemma>; the former were a people dwelling at the extremity of the <emph>heel </emph> of Italy ; the latter at the <emph>toe.</emph>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="133">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">alter</lemma>, Chrysogonus ; <foreign lang="la">tibi</foreign>, <gloss>ethic,</gloss> dative, expressing here Cicero's indignation ; cf. pro Sest. 89, <foreign lang="la">ecce tibi consul, rraetor, tribunus pl. nova novi generis edicta proponunt.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">de Palatio</lemma>, from the Palatine hill, on which many Roman nobles had mansions. From the time of Augustus the Palatine was the site of the imperial residence, whence the derivation of <gloss>palace</gloss> (<foreign lang="la">palatium</foreign>).
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">animi causa </lemma>= <gloss>for his own enjoyment</gloss>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 134">134</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">animi et aurium causa</foreign>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">domus referta</lemma> ; the nom. is put graphically (cf. Virg. Georg. 2.133, 4), as though <foreign lang="la">ei est</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">sunt</foreign>) and not <foreign lang="la">habet</foreign> had preceded :
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praedia</lemma> links the two constructions, suiting either. Cf. pro Milo.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Corinthiis et Deliacis</lemma>, of Corinthian and Delian ore : see Verr. 4. 1, Halm's note ; <foreign lang="la">authepsa</foreign>, i.e. a self-acting cooking apparatus. The name implies a Greek invention.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">enuntiaret</lemma>, called out as the last and highest bid.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quid . . . putatis esse </lemma>: this and similar phrases frequently answer to our <gloss>what must be . . .?</gloss> cf. below, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 134">134</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">quos sumptus cotidianos fieri putatis?</foreign> <gloss>what must have been his daily expenditure ? </gloss> de Imp. Pomp. 32, <foreign lang="la">quam multas existimatis insulas esse desertas?</foreign> <gloss>how many islands must have been deserted? </gloss> ib. &sect; 42.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">stragulae vestis</lemma> ; referring especially to coverings for the couches used at meals, <foreign lang="la">triclinia.</foreign>


<pb n="61"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">marmoris </lemma>; i.e. not statues (<foreign lang="la">signorum</foreign>), but as used for the wainscotting of walls, and for inlaid floors.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="134">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">familiam</lemma>, <gloss>establishment of slaves.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">artificiis</lemma>, <gloss>qualifications.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hasce</lemma> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 62">62</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">his levioribus</foreign>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">officina nequitiae</lemma>, <gloss>a factory for the production of wickedness.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="135">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">togatorum</lemma>, said bitterly for <foreign lang="la">civium</foreign>, citizens, who disgraced the <foreign lang="la">toga</foreign>, their robe of honour, by attending and enjoying the patronage of a freedman.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut . . . ut . . . ut</lemma>, <gloss>how.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">beatum</lemma>, alluding to his wealth.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">causam nobilitatis</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">laedere</lemma>, because Chrysogonus was Sulla's favourite.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">meo iure</lemma>, because I am of that party myself.


<pb n="62"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="136">
<milestone n="XLVII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut componeretur</lemma>, impersonal : in substantival, <gloss>namely that an agreement should be made.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id defendisse</lemma>, <gloss>to have striven for the object that . . </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">humilitatem</lemma>, both of rank and disposition, <gloss>that the mean and low were contending for the highest place against personal worth.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">perditi civis erat</lemma>, <gloss>it would have been . . .</gloss> : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 53">53</bibl>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="137">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">contra</lemma>, adverbial ; against Sulla.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">viris fortibus</lemma>, Sulla's soldiers and supporters.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">honos habitus est</lemma>, <gloss>have been rewarded</gloss> : &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 108">108</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">In eo studio partium fuisse</lemma>, <gloss>that I was a partisan in that cause.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">id actum est</lemma>, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 142">142</bibl>, <gloss>if this was the aim . . .</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut</lemma>, namely that . . .
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">postremi</lemma>, <gloss>the lowest of mankind</gloss> (Stock's translation). <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">recreatus</lemma>, <gloss>endowed with new life.</gloss>


<pb n="63"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="138">
<milestone n="XLVIII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">haec</lemma>, the present regime.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">queruntur</lemma>, etc. : in one sense Cicero himself is making this complaint ; but he means that those who merely complain of Chrysogonus' power as an existent fact, only arouse discontent at the system under which that power has grown up ; while those who dispute his <emph>right</emph> to such power commend the present regime, for they imply that his power is not the legal outcome of it.  The point of the sentence is that the jurors are to give such a verdict as implies <foreign lang="la">concessum ei non esse.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nihil est quod</lemma>, <gloss>there is no reason why . . . </gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">improbus</lemma>, <gloss>shameless </gloss> as in &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 130">130</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 142">142</bibl>; Verr. 2. 4. 3, <foreign lang="la">improbissima ratione</foreign>, <gloss>in the most shameless manner.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">decrevissem refers here less to magistrates than to senators</lemma>, since <foreign lang="la">decernere</foreign> was said not only of decrees passed by the Senate as a body, but also of the proposals or motions of individual senators.  
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Indicassem</lemma>, in the capacity of a juror.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="139">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">magistratus creavit</lemma>.  In 82 B.c. Sulla was appointed dictator on the motion of the interrex L. Valerius Flaccus ; but he caused consuls to be chosen for the next year, in order to carry out his changes under constitutional forms.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">leges</lemma> ; referring partly to the constitution and the administration, partly to judicial matters, <foreign lang="la">leges iudiciariae</foreign> : see Mommsen, Rom. Hist. 3. p.349.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">procuratio</lemma>, <gloss>official activity, action.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ne ominis quidem causa</lemma> ; <foreign lang="la">ne</foreign> reiterates <foreign lang="la">nolo</foreign>, as it does <foreign lang="la">nihil</foreign> in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 38">38</bibl>. Cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 22">22</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">neminem</foreign> note. <gloss>I am unwilling--on the mere ground of its being a bad omen I am unwilling--to say anything too severe against them.</gloss>  The mere <emph>mention</emph> of a thing was looked on as a possible omen of its happening ; cf. Phil. 4. 10, <foreign lang="la">quibus Antonius</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">o di immortales avertite . . .  hoc omen</foreign>) <foreign lang="la">urbem se divisurum promisit.  "Ne ut ominari quidem male in eos videar, nedum quod iis grave aliquid imprecer."</foreign> Manutius.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nostri illi nobiles</lemma> (with a hint of sarcasm), <gloss>our illustrious aristocracy.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vigilantes</lemma>, <gloss>on the alert,</gloss> as opposed to <foreign lang="la">iners</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">ignavus</foreign> ; cf. de Imp. Pomp. 2 ; <foreign lang="la">fortes</foreign>, <gloss>courageous, steadfast</gloss>, to resist all unlawful claims.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">haec</lemma>, Sc. <foreign lang="la">vigilantia</foreign>, etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ornamenta</lemma> ; i.e. distinctions, positions of honour, hitherto the prerogative of their rank.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">necesse est</lemma> : a true prophecy. Ten years later, B.C. 70, the senators lost their exclusive judicial privileges.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="140">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">male</lemma>, <gloss>disloyally.</gloss>


<pb n="64"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cum Chrysogono</lemma>, shortly for <foreign lang="la">cum Chrysogoni causa</foreign> : cf. in Vatin. 41, <foreign lang="la">etiam illud dixeris, causam Milonis coniunctam cum hoc existimari.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">equestrem splendorem</lemma>.  Since the time of C. Gracchus the great cause of ill-will between the nobles and the <foreign lang="la">equites</foreign> was the <foreign lang="la">iudicia</foreign>, which had been restored by Sulla to the <foreign lang="la">ordo senatorius.</foreign> In the civil war the <foreign lang="la">equites</foreign> had been for the most part opposed to Sulla, who afterwards took terrible revenge.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">servi</lemma>, ironically for <foreign lang="la">liberti</foreign> ; viz. Chrysogonus.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quam nam . . . adfectet</lemma>; possibly a quotation from a poet. <foreign lang="la">Munitare</foreign> (intensive from <foreign lang="la">munire</foreign>) only occurs here : the phrase <foreign lang="la">iter ad aliquid adfectare</foreign> is common in Plautus ;
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">it is used again by Cicero</lemma>, de Lege Agr. 1.5.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad fidem </lemma>= <gloss>its aim is to deal a blow at your good faith . . .</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ad ius jurandum</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>, note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="141">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc</lemma>=<foreign lang="la">hoc re</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">propterea</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quod verear</lemma>, subjunctive as being the unreal reason.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ausus est</lemma>, <gloss>was so daring.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">speravit sese . . . valiturum</lemma>, <gloss>hoped he would have influence.</gloss> Another reading is <foreign lang="la">speravit se . . . posse</foreign> (mark the difference of tense), <gloss>hoped he possessed influence</gloss>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">expectata nobilitas</lemma>, <gloss>our long looked-for nobles</gloss> i.e. while Sulla was away and his party were not in power.


<milestone n="XLIX" unit="chapter"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rem publicam </lemma>; i.e. here the government.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="142">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc</lemma>, se <foreign lang="la">victoriam nobilium.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">inermis</lemma> ; i.e., without myself joining in the combat.


<pb n="65"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">se ipsum probe novit </lemma>; i.e. he understands that he is another such villain as Chrysogonus, since he feels hurt when Chrysogonus is attacked.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rationem communicatam</lemma>, <gloss>that he has a common interest with.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">laeditur . . . separatur</lemma>, <gloss>is injured in that he is shut out from this glorious cause</gloss>: i.e. invectives which, as Cicero's, deny any connection between Chrysogonus and the party of the nobles, deny it equally of any man who is the <foreign lang="la">fautor</foreign> of Chrysogonus.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="143">
<p><lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">haec omnis oratio</lemma>, <gloss>all this part of my speech</gloss>, from &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 129">129</bibl> onwards : cf. <foreign lang="la">extrema oratio</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 129">129</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mea est</lemma> ; i.e. the accused at least shall not suffer any evil consequences from Cicero's boldness.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">imperitus morum</lemma>, <gloss>with no knowledge of the world, ignorant of life</gloss> : in this sense <foreign lang="la">rerum imperitus</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">ignarus, nescius, indoctus</foreign>) is more common. If the phrase is not a mere variety for <foreign lang="la">rerum</foreign> (which has been suggested as an emendation), perhaps Cicero means by <foreign lang="la">mores</foreign> the <gloss>spirit of the age,</gloss> with which one who lived far from Rome would be unacquainted.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">more, lege, iure gentium</lemma> <gloss>in accordance with custom, law, and the principles of justice that all nations recognise.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="144">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si nihil</lemma>, etc. ; see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 82">82</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">de peculatu</foreign>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">optima fide sua</lemma>, <gloss>to the best of his belief.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">anulum</lemma>, signet ring, which was worn by every free Roman. Its surrender stands here for the renunciation of all rights or claims. <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">se ipsum nudum</lemma>, <gloss>his naked body</gloss> : <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">excepit</lemma>, <gloss>has reserved.</gloss> Halm quotes from the Pandects, <foreign lang="la">qui domum vendebat, excepit sibi habitationem</foreign>, <gloss>reserved for himself the right of living in it.</gloss>


<pb n="66"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="145">
<milestone n="L" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hominem</lemma>, not <gloss>a man,</gloss> but = Sex. Roscius, who has just been represented as speaking : here Cicero speaks again in his own person.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">si metus</lemma> ; MSS. <foreign lang="la">si metuis</foreign>, which old form of the genitive may perhaps be the true reading, chosen by Cicero, in order to resemble the following <foreign lang="la">metuis.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">praeter ceteros</lemma>, with a negative = <gloss>less than others</gloss> : see &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 2">2</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 16">16</bibl>. In this sense <foreign lang="la">praeter reliquos</foreign> is not found.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tu metuere non debeas</lemma>, because, even if Sulla should become more conciliatory to his former enemies, he would surely not wrest from <emph>you</emph> the possessions you have won : <foreign lang="la">ne</foreign>, <gloss>namely that,</gloss> as &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 136">136</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">ut componeretur.</foreign>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="146">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">facis iniuriam </lemma>; in the same sense as <foreign lang="la">facis iniuste, si putas</foreign>, pro Flacco, 41.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">spem emptionis</lemma>, shortly for <gloss>hope that your purchase will hold good.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">In iis rebus</lemma>, etc. ; i.e. the complete victory which Sulla had won over his enemies made it unlikely that a reaction would follow and his measures be overthrown.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">monumenti causa</lemma>, <gloss>as a reminiscence.</gloss>


<pb n="67"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">cruenta spolia </lemma>:  i.e. <foreign lang="greek">ai(mato/enta ta\ skeu/h</foreign>, not <foreign lang="greek">ta\ ai(mato/enta skeu/h</foreign> : <gloss>carry off the spoils when blood-stained.</gloss>

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="147">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nihil audere</lemma>, sc. with a view to recover his property.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">contra rem tuam</lemma> : <gloss>against your interests </gloss> ; cf. Phil. 2.3, <foreign lang="la">contra rem suam me venisse questus est.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">reliqui</lemma> : see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 83">83</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">id erit signi</foreign>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nisi</lemma>,  see on &sect; l3l sub fin.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Balearici filia</lemma>, Nepotis sorore : cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">Nepotis filiam</foreign>, which disagrees with this. Each seems to be a gloss. If the present is correct (as seems likely from the agreement of the relationships), Caecilia was a daughter of Q. Metellus, who as consul B.C. 123 and 124 subdued the Balearic Isles and received the <foreign lang="la">agnomen</foreign> Balearicus. Her uncles were L. Metellus Diadematus, consul B.C. 117 ; M. Metellus, consul B.C. 115, who repressed a revolt of the Sardinians, and triumphed on the same day with the next brother ; and C. Metellus Caprarius, who as consul B.C. 113 defeated the Thracians. Caecilia's brother was Q. Metellus Nepos, consul B.C. 98.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">mulier, virtute</lemma>: note the play on the original meaning of <foreign lang="la">virtus</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">quanto honore</lemma> should have been followed by <foreign lang="la">tanta ornamenta</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">tantum</foreign> (<foreign lang="la">honorem</foreign>). Cicero chose <foreign lang="la">non minora</foreign> in order to speak in a more moderate tone of the woman than of her male relations.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="148">
<milestone n="LI" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hospitiis </lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 15">15</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hospites</lemma>, viz. those of his father.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">copiose</lemma> alluding to the number of such <foreign lang="la">patroni</foreign>


<pb n="68"/></p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">pro magnitudine . . . proque eo quod . . . </lemma>, <gloss>in consideration of the greatness . . . and of the fact that . . .</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">summa res publica tentatur</lemma>, the State is attackcd in its highest point, i.e. in its most vital interests.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">nunc</lemma>: see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 115">115</bibl>,note.

</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="149">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">rationem</lemma>, <gloss>the department, the matter of</gloss> : cf. de Off. 1.76, <foreign lang="la">haec quidem res non solum ex domestica est ratione attingit etiam bellicam.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">M. Messalla</lemma> : <ref n="7" targOrder="U">Introd. &sect; 7</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sua causa cupere ac debere</lemma>, <gloss>that I wished and was bound to oblige him,</gloss> lit. <gloss>that I desired and owed for his sake.</gloss> Cf. ad Fam. 13.75, <foreign lang="la">cuius (hominis) causa omnia cum cupio, tum etiam debeo</foreign>, <gloss>whom it is alike my wish and my duty to oblige in all things.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">assiduitate </lemma><foreign lang="la">praesentia in iudicio</foreign> ; cf. pro Sest. 7, <foreign lang="la">assiduis officiis</foreign>  Probably Messalla had often appeared with Sex. Roscius at the preliminary investigation (cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 77">77</bibl>) before the praetor
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">auctoritate</lemma>, the weight of his name.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">haec acta res est</lemma>, <gloss>this movement (i.e. Sulla's revolution) took place.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">restituerentur</lemma> ; referring to the nobles banished by Marius and Cinna.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">et res publica . . . laborarent</lemma>, <gloss>they would be a cause of less trouble to the State, and would themselves be less troubled by unpopularity.</gloss>


<pb n="69"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="151">
<milestone n="LII" unit="chapter"/>

<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">sectores ac sicarii </lemma>: a play on the original sense of <foreign lang="la">sectores</foreign> ; cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 80">80</bibl>, <foreign lang="la">sectores bonorum et collorum.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">solent hoc racere . . . ut milites conlocent</lemma>, <gloss>are wont to adopt the practice of placing forces</gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">ut</lemma> explains <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hoc</lemma>: cf. &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 127">127</bibl>, note.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">prohibeant ut</lemma>, shortly for <foreign lang="la">prohibeant ne fiat ut</foreign>  This very rare construction occurs in Iulius Capitolinus Max. Iun. 2, <foreign lang="la">dii prohibeant, ut quisquam ingenuorum pedibus meis osculum figat.</foreign>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">consilium publicum</lemma> : the <foreign lang="la">consilium iudicum</foreign> could be called <foreign lang="la">publicum</foreign>, as one which a public official, viz. the presiding praetor, had assembled. Usually <foreign lang="la">consilium publicum</foreign> meant the Senate, as in &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 153">153</bibl>, but this did not prevent the term being used of other <foreign lang="la">consilia</foreign>, to which it applied for the same reasons and no less correctly, though not in its technical sense.


<pb n="70"/>
 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="152">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">tollantur</lemma>, from fear that they might in consequence of a political reaction be restored to their rights and property : see <ref n="n.,36" targOrder="U">Introd. note 36</ref>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">in</lemma>, <gloss>in the case of, in the opportunity offered by</gloss> ; <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">vestro iure iurando</lemma> =<foreign lang="la">vestris sententiis</foreign>, see &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 8">8</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">dubiumne est</lemma>, etc. : this recapitulation of a former argument seems suggested here by the words <foreign lang="la">in vestro iure iurando</foreign> ; <gloss>and if you are true to that oath, how you will decide the case cannot be doubtful, <foreign lang="la">cum videatis,</foreign></gloss> etc.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">hic</lemma>, <gloss>at the present juncture.</gloss></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="153">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">Quodsi </lemma>: here Cicero returns to the subject of the <foreign lang="la">proscriptorum liberi</foreign>, &sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 152">152</bibl> sub init.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">potuerunt</lemma> : <foreign lang="la">voluerunt</foreign> has been suggested ; but by <foreign lang="la">potuerunt</foreign> Cicero means to imply with rhetorical exaggeration that the sons of the proscribed were <emph>not</emph> able to bear arms, i.e. were all <foreign lang="la">impuberes et inermes</foreign>, deserving pity. So <foreign lang="la">infantium puerorum</foreign> below.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">suscipere noluit</lemma>, in that the Senate and the magistrates had had no share in carrying out the proscriptions : cf. Plut Sulla, 31, <gloss>Sulla immediately proscribed eighty persons, without referring to any of the magistrates.</gloss>
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">more maiorum</lemma> : cf. pro Sest. 65, <foreign lang="la">cur, cum de capite civis et de bonis proscriptio ferretur, cum et sacratis legibus et XII tabulis sanctum esset, ut ne cui privilegium inrogari liceret neve de capite nisi comitiis centuriatis rogari, nulla vox est audita consulum</foreign>, etc. See the speech of Caesar in Sall. Cat. 51, &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 22">22</bibl> and <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 40">40</bibl>.
</p>
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">videte . . . putetis</lemma>, a common form : cf. de Imp. Pomp. &sect;&sect; <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 26">26</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 27">27</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 38">38</bibl>, <bibl n="Cic. S. Rosc. 46">46</bibl> ; and ib. &sect; 11, Halm's note. <foreign lang="la">Videte quem in locum respublica ventura sit</foreign> would mean, <gloss>consider to what condition the State <emph>will</emph> come </gloss> ; but <foreign lang="la">putetis</foreign> gives the last verb the force of the Greek optative with <foreign lang="greek">a)/n</foreign>, <gloss>to what condition the State <emph>may</emph> (in your opinion) come.</gloss></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="154">
<p> <lemma lang="la" targOrder="U">domestica</lemma> = <foreign lang="la">in cives</foreign>
</p>
<p> Some editors have conjectured that the conclusion of the speech is lost. It would be difficult to say what Cicero could have added ; he concludes very suitably with the wish that the acquittal of Sex. Roscius might show the time of bloodshed to have passed away without extinguishing all the feelings of humanity in the hearts of men.</p>
</div2>
</div1></body></text></TEI.2>
